<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 16:59:19 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 16:59:19 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A (Social) Class Apart: The Hidden Biases Shaping Psychiatry]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/Matthew-Smith.jpg?itok=MauYw0FF" alt="Matthew Smith Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Psychiatry</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">A (Social) Class Apart: The Hidden Biases Shaping Psychiatry</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Prejudices against the poor and marginalized have long influenced ideas about mental health.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Social psychiatry studies have long been shaped by researchers' biases related to race and class.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Classic research tended to blame poor mental health on individual failures, rather than unjust social systems.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Though often unintentional, such biased approaches undermined preventive approaches to mental illness.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Even today, we have a tendency to blame individuals, rather than systems, for poor mental health outcomes.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>In my<a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/a-short-history-of-mental-health/202511/the-relationship-between-social-class-and-mental"> last article</a>, I talked about the New Haven Study, a psychiatric epidemiology project that examined the relationship between class and mental health in New Haven, Connecticut, during the 1950s. It demonstrated that people on the lower rungs of the social strata were much more likely to suffer from mental illness than those at the top. This social psychiatry study also showed that people representing the lower classes were more likely to be diagnosed with psychoses, rather than neuroses, and to be prescribed invasive, somatic treatments (such as electroconvulsive therapy, drugs, and lobotomy) rather than talk therapies, such as psychoanalysis.</p>

<p>The New Haven Study relied partly on mental health statistics, but it also included a qualitative element. Social psychiatrists investigated the conditions in which people lived and conducted interviews with them, in order to determine how these factors might impact their mental health. These researchers found that most people in the lowest class lived in “crowded old tenements.” The buildings were often dilapidated and lacked the pleasant gardens found in wealthier neighborhoods. </p>

<p>Such conditions should not be surprising. After all, these were people living in relative poverty. But details in the way researchers described such places—as well as those who lived there—indicated something else was going on.</p>
<h2>Blame vs. Sympathy: How Judgment is Shaped By Social Class</h2>
<p>One thing that these social psychiatrists (who tended to be white, upper-middle-class, male, and highly educated) tended to focus on was how a state of disrepair often characterized the buildings where those in the lower classes lived. If there were steps up to the door, they were likely to be wobbly or broken. Doors would hang on hinges and not close fully. Flooring would be worn through. Light bulbs were burnt out. Rather than laying blame on the landlords for such deficiencies, the researchers implied that they were the fault of the residents, even though they probably were not responsible for such conditions and likely couldn’t afford to repair anything.</p>

<p>The social psychiatrists also picked up on the dirty and unkempt nature of the tenements, mentioning broken bottles, uncut grass, cigarette butts, stained carpets, smeared countertops, and flies buzzing around. Again, such uncleanliness was put forward as a moral failing. The researchers didn’t think to mention that many of the upper-class homes would have employed housekeepers. Middle-class homes at this time (during the 1950s) were often maintained by a stay-at-home mom, who would have spent a great deal of her time cleaning up after her family. </p>

<p>In contrast, many men and women (and some adolescents) in the tenements would have been working long hours, possibly juggling multiple jobs. Those coping with ill-health, addictions, and/or chronic unemployment may have simply lacked the motivation or energy to clean up homes that were already in a poor state.</p>

<p>When describing other aspects of the interviewees’ lives, the researchers seemed to be quicker to judge than sympathize. They sniffed at the fact that most apartments had televisions (mainly rented), suggesting that the money spent on such luxuries could be expended on more edifying things, such as books. They pointed out how noisy the apartments were, seeming to blame the residents, rather than the thin walls. </p>

<p>Finally, they were aghast at how residents dealt with the inadequate provision of toilets (typically only two for an apartment block housing 20 families). An interviewee explained to a researcher that sometimes men would simply urinate out of the windows. As he was explaining, he spied someone in an adjacent building doing just that. In his horror, the researcher failed to comment on the fact that, when there were only two toilets for nearly 100 people, such things were bound to happen.</p>


<h2>Are Biases Still Blinding Us Today?</h2>
<p>Other studies occurring at the same time, such as the <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/a-short-history-of-mental-health/202504/is-rural-living-better-for-mental-health">Stirling County Study </a>or the <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/a-short-history-of-mental-health/202501/mad-in-the-metropolis-is-city-living-bad-for-mental">Midtown Manhattan Study</a>, reveal a similar tendency to condemn the actions of lower-class people, rather than seek explanations in an unequal social system. So, why does this matter? </p>
<p>Simply put, by bringing their prejudices about working-class people to their research, social psychiatrists were lured into blaming them for their situation—and, by extension, their poor mental health—rather than questioning a social structure characterized by chronic inequality and racism. The result was that social psychiatrists were reluctant to suggest societal solutions to prevent mental illness, such as reducing poverty, inequality, and racism, and instead implied that people at society’s margins ought to “educate” themselves out of poverty. Such thinking was most evident in the approach to Black families in the 1960s, as<a href="https://uncpress.org/9781469627304/whats-wrong-with-the-poor/"> Mical Raz’s research</a> shows.</p>

<p>Today, it’s not so different. We have even more evidence that social factors drive mental illness, but we remain largely unwilling to tackle these problems at the source, even as society grows more and more unequal. I have suggested that <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/short-history-mental-health/201911/universal-basic-income-and-mental-health">universal basic income </a>could be a good way to change this mindset—but changing our mindset could itself be a good starting point. Rather than leaping to judgment, we should seek to ask why people do, and feel, the way they do—even when they are urinating out of a window.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/a-short-history-of-mental-health/202602/a-social-class-apart-the-hidden-biases-shaping" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/a-short-history-of-mental-health/202602/a-social-class-apart-the-hidden-biases-shaping</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/a-short-history-of-mental-health/202602/a-social-class-apart-the-hidden-biases-shaping</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Matthew Smith Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/shutterstock_2333252331.jpg?itok=P29667GJ" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Experiencing Awe Through Music and Beyond]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2023-10/Main_photo-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=002r2_SB" alt="Raymond Leone MMT, MT-BC " style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Awe</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Experiencing Awe Through Music and Beyond</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Personal Perspective: What we experience when we feel something we can't put into words.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
                    <p dir="ltr">I’ve been thinking about the concept of awe recently. In fact, one of my "not New Year’s resolutions" this year is to experience more awe in my life. To be open to the beauty and power of life’s wonders and the experiences that give meaning and a sense that there is something bigger to everyday living.</p>

<p dir="ltr">In his book, <em>Awe: The New Science of Everyday Wonder and How It Can Transform Your Life</em>, psychologist Dacher Keltner offers this definition: “Awe is the feeling of being in the presence of something vast that transcends your current understanding of the world.”</p>
<p dir="ltr">In considering this idea, it certainly seems that we experience awe in nature—seeing the Grand Canyon for the first time, for example, or Niagara Falls or the sunrise over the Atlantic Ocean. But also the tree in your backyard when the leaves change to vibrant yellows and oranges in fall, or a blue heron taking flight over a lake.</p>

<p dir="ltr">While I don’t consider myself the most spiritual person, I imagine that people experience awe in the spiritual—in feeling the presence of some higher power, perhaps through prayer, meditation or a mystical experience. And certainly we experience awe in the arts. When you get chills from hearing a piece of music that moves you from Bach, Brahms, Miles, Coltrane, Lady Gaga, Green Day, or Norah Jones. (Sing to me, Norah!) When you see a painting by da Vinci or Monet, or Pollock, or a graffiti mural downtown. Or architecture, poetry, or a ballet dancer soaring across the stage with grace and strength.</p>

<p dir="ltr">And then there is tasting unbelievable homemade pasta in Tuscany (or at my mom’s house), seeing a baby giggle, or watching a couple in their 90s holding hands while slowly walking down the street. Feeling the immediate elation while letting out an unexpected primal roar, in concert with 40,000 others after a game-winning homer in the bottom of the 9th. Or hearing my daughter sing and seeing the excitement on my son’s face as he tries to explain an intricate math equation that, to me, looks like Arabic. Or your dog’s excitement when you get home at the end of the day.</p>

<p>Is awe simply a more intense feeling of beauty? Or is there more to it? There can be a sense of fear involved in experiencing awe: a massive thunderstorm rolling in or feeling the house shake from winds gusting over 60 miles per hour. The ocean certainly has elements of fear with its vastness and power.</p>

<h2>The power of music and awe</h2>
<p dir="ltr">As I contemplate awe, and seek more of it in my life, I realize that I actually experience awe every day in my work as a music therapist working in a hospital setting. In facilitating music experiences, and connecting on an aesthetic level with those who are suffering, I experience awe. And in thinking about how awe can be a unique combination of beauty and, perhaps, fear, I often see awe experienced in the patients I work with.</p>

<p dir="ltr">One such man was in his 80s. As cancer had gotten the best of him, he was on in-patient hospice care. As I’m often asked to do, I went to visit him and provide some music for comfort. When I walked into the room he was in bed with his eyes closed, non-respondent. His mouth was agape, and his breathing was shallow and labored. Fortunately, he didn’t seem to be in any pain or discomfort.</p>

<p dir="ltr">I took out my guitar and played a soothing soundscape, working to "hold" him in the space with the music. (Regardless of a patient's condition, I always believe the music gets through. I feel it. And I’ve seen indicators.) As I played, I thought about him—who he was, what he did, what his life was like. I wondered who would miss him. I concentrated on providing the right aesthetics and beauty for the moment. I felt connected to him within the music experience.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Then, after about 15 minutes he suddenly opened his eyes and looked right at me. It startled me. I was frozen and could not move away from his gaze. Somehow I kept the music going. Then I saw a single tear form in his right eye and run down his cheek. He looked unsure, but at the same time, peaceful. After a moment—I don’t know if it was a second or five minutes—his eyes were closed again. I played for a bit longer and then just sat in the silence with him, contemplating what had just happened, and that there may have been something bigger going on here. I later heard that he passed within an hour after I left his room.</p>



  


<p dir="ltr">I believe that while experiencing the aesthetics of the music, combined with a sense of mortal uncertainty about what is beyond this world, he experienced awe. I did too.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/music-therapy-music-musings/202602/experiencing-awe-through-music-and-beyond" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/music-therapy-music-musings/202602/experiencing-awe-through-music-and-beyond</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/music-therapy-music-musings/202602/experiencing-awe-through-music-and-beyond</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Raymond Leone MMT, MT-BC]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/shutterstock_2208437269.jpg?itok=wibjKNL5" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[When Morning Dread Takes Over During Fertility Treatment]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-10/IMG_3472_Copy_Copy_Copy_Copy-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=K8cNzEFs" alt="Fenella Das Gupta Ph.D., MFT" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Infertility</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">When Morning Dread Takes Over During Fertility Treatment</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Why survival mode intensifies during fertility treatment and how to reclaim your pace.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Morning dread during fertility treatment is a nervous system response, not weakness.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Survival mode can make even self-care feel like performance.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Small shifts in pace can restore steadiness when control feels lost.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/IMG_0005.jpeg.jpg?itok=b11nB2Tg" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" title="Prostock-studio / Shutterstock" alt="Prostock-studio / Shutterstock"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Prostock-studio / Shutterstock</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>No matter what stage you are in—early in treatment, in the middle of cycles, nearing the end, considering third-party reproduction or adoption, or resolving the journey altogether—the stress and anxiety can feel supercharged. Fertility treatment compresses time, hope, fear, and identity into a tight emotional space.</p>

<h2>The Dread That Arrives Before You Are Ready</h2>
<p>Perhaps one of the hardest and most commonly reported experiences is the dread that arrives first thing in the morning. It can hit like a ton of bricks. Sometimes, as soon as you properly open your eyes, the phone is already ringing. Or the emails have accumulated, decisions waiting to be made, all needing attention in a timely manner. Before you have even had a moment to orient yourself, your body shifts into hypervigilance mode, with the nagging worry: Is this the right thing? What if this does not work? The day has not yet begun, and already you are behind.</p>

<h2>When Stress Becomes Existential</h2>
<p>This is not just medical stress. It is deeply psychological. Deeply existential, even if you do not have the space to consciously name it. Many threads interweave in the tapestry of reproduction: history, identity, partnership, time, and meaning. Each appointment can feel like a verdict. Each phone call can feel like a turning point. The nervous system rarely gets to stand down. It stays slightly activated, always bracing for impact, always preparing for news—good or bad.</p>

<h2>Living in Anticipatory Tension</h2>
<p>Over time, this constant bracing takes a toll. The body wakes already tense. The day feels loaded before it has even begun. You can find yourself living in anticipatory tension, caught between hope and self-protection, longing and fear.</p>
<h2>All the Best-Laid Plans</h2>
<p>Even with the best intentions for self-care—plans for meditation, spirituality, breathing exercises, and gratitude practices—at the times of greatest stress, these can start to feel like extra tasks. Things we have to do on top of the things we have to do.</p>

<p>You may genuinely want to journal. You may believe in your affirmations. You may know that breathing slowly would help. But when the nervous system is in survival mode, those practices can begin to feel like obligations rather than support.</p>
<p>The mind is full, and it races. Fear predominates. And that makes sense. We are biologically wired to move into survival mode when our sense of safety feels threatened. Fertility treatment, with its uncertainty and high stakes, can feel like a direct threat to the life we imagined. Of course the body reacts. Of course it mobilizes. This is not weakness. It is wiring.</p>

<h2>The Exhaustion of Performing</h2>
<p>On our hardest days, we often feel the need to perform just to get through the day. To show up at work. To respond to messages. To sit across from friends and make conversation. Not to let others see how much fear or grief is running underneath.</p>
<p>That performance is exhausting.</p>

<p>It requires holding two realities at once: the external face and the internal storm. And if I were to give you a long list of coping tools right now, that might simply kick you back into performance mode. Another set of things to do correctly. Another standard to meet.</p>
<p>That’s a trap we should both avoid. So, what is left?</p>


<h2>The Smallest Shifts</h2>
<p>When the day feels excruciatingly painful to get through, the simplest things help. Small mantras or two-word reminders like “slow down.” Create small gaps in your day, even if they are only a few minutes long. When things feel heavy, take something off your plate. The world will not create spaces for you. You will need to create spaces in the day for yourself.</p>

<p>These shifts are not dramatic. They are not performative. They do not require spiritual alignment or perfect discipline. They are quiet adjustments in pace.</p>
<p>Or you might try a quiet internal question, such as, <em>Is this high risk or low risk? </em>Ask: <em>How important is this to my life right now? Is this moment actually dangerous, or does it just feel urgent? Does this email, this symptom, this thought about the future require my attention right now?</em></p>



  


<p>When we are under prolonged stress, everything can start to register as high risk. A delayed call from the clinic. A sensation in the body. A passing comment from someone else. The brain interprets it all as potentially catastrophic.</p>
<p>But often, in that specific moment, what we are facing is low risk. It is uncomfortable. It is uncertain. It is emotionally loaded. But it is not immediate danger. It does not require our immediate attention.</p>

<p>In many situations, we are not obligated to respond right away. Nor are we required to manage other people’s emotions in that instant. Asking the question gently—<em>High risk or low risk?</em>—creates space. It invites the thinking brain back online. It inserts a small wedge between stimulus and reaction.</p>
<h2>What You Can Control</h2>

<p>In an uncertain situation, control is limited. You cannot control outcomes. You cannot force timelines. You cannot eliminate risk.</p>
<p>But pace is something you can influence.</p>
<p>And sometimes, on the most stressful days of fertility treatment, reclaiming your pace is the most stabilizing move you can make.</p>
<p>No performance required.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/creating-2-pink-lines/202602/when-morning-dread-takes-over-during-fertility-treatment" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/creating-2-pink-lines/202602/when-morning-dread-takes-over-during-fertility-treatment</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/creating-2-pink-lines/202602/when-morning-dread-takes-over-during-fertility-treatment</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[S. Fenella Das Gupta Ph.D., MFT]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/IMG_0005.jpeg.jpg?itok=axhNVOvy" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Do You Find It Hard to Trust Others?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/Michelle-Mcquaid_0.jpg?itok=kqRvBYok" alt="Michelle McQuaid Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Trust</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Do You Find It Hard to Trust Others?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How to step out of the drama and stop abandoning yourself.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Waiting for others to change leaves us dependent on something entirely outside our control.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The hardest part of any broken trust isn't what others did—it's how we abandon ourselves.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">There is a practical path from feeling stuck to trusting yourself in relationships.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Trust feels genuinely difficult right now—and for many of us, for very good reason. Something has shifted. The certainties we relied on feel less certain. The systems we counted on feel less reliable. And the people around us? They can feel harder to read, harder to predict, harder to count on.</p>
<p>When trust feels this fragile, it’s natural to focus on what others need to do differently. If they were more honest, more consistent, more accountable—then things would feel safer. And sometimes that’s a fair assessment. But waiting for others to change leaves us dependent on something entirely outside our control.</p>

<h2>The More Practical Question</h2>
<p>What if the more practical question isn’t “Are they trustworthy?”—but “Can I trust myself to navigate whatever they do?”</p>
<p>This isn’t about lowering the bar for others’ behavior, or pretending difficult people aren’t difficult. It’s about recognizing that how we show up in our relationships is the one thing we can always work with.</p>

<h2>What Self-Trust Gives Us</h2>
<p>Psychologists describe this as <a href="https://www.michellemcquaid.com/making-leadership-work-podcast-series6/">secure attachment to ourselves</a>—and it’s different from confidence or optimism. It’s the quiet knowing that when things get hard, we will show up for ourselves. We’ll advocate for what we need. We’ll ask for help when we need it. We’ll set healthy limits when the situation calls for it. And we won’t abandon ourselves—even if others do.</p>

<p>When we have that self-trust, difficult relationships become more navigable—not because the other person has changed, but because we trust ourselves to handle whatever comes.</p>
<h2>Avoiding the Drama</h2>
<p>Without that self-trust, we’re vulnerable to a pattern that psychologist Stephen Karpman identified, called<a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/0886260520957696"> the Drama Triangle</a>. When we don’t feel safe enough, our nervous system tips into protection mode, and our brains generate stories to make sense of what’s happening. And these stories tend to follow a familiar shape:</p>

<ul>
<li>We cast someone as the Villain—the source of all our problems.</li>
<li>We look for a Hero—someone who can fix things and rescue us.</li>
<li>And see a Victim—overwhelmed, helpless, waiting for something outside themselves to change.</li>
</ul>
<p>This isn't a character flaw. It's just faulty maths. Our brains search for the fastest path back to safety—and the story of the Drama Triangle feels like an answer that's easy to understand. But when we place both the threat and the solution outside of ourselves, we abandon ourselves in the process.</p>

<h2>Start With Compassion</h2>
<p>The first step back toward trusting yourself is to start with compassion—particularly for yourself. When we can see the story we’re stuck in with some kindness and understanding, rather than judgment, something loosens. We’re not a bad person for casting Villains, hoping for Heroes, or seeing Victims. We’re a human being whose brain is trying to manage a situation that feels unsafe.</p>

<p>That moment of self-compassion—“Oh, I'm not feeling safe enough in this situation, and I need a better way to navigate what's unfolding”—is often what creates just enough space to slow down and calculate a more reliable path.<br><br><em>Try asking yourself: Are the stories I'm telling about this situation serving me and others well? Have I gotten myself stuck in a drama triangle? </em></p>

<h2>Then Get Curious</h2>
<p>Once there’s a little space, curiosity becomes possible. And curiosity changes everything—because it shifts the question from “What did they do wrong?” to “What is mine to learn?”<br><br>Drawing on the research of <a href="https://theempowermentdynamic.com/individuals/">David Emerald</a>, I’ve come to think of this as the Compassion Circle: Every Villain can become a Challenger—someone pushing us toward growth we wouldn’t have chosen but perhaps needed. The Hero we were searching for can become a Coach—someone who supports us while trusting we’re capable. And instead of staying stuck as the Victim, we can step into the role of Creator—someone who recognizes they can’t control others, but can choose their own response.</p>

<p>Personally, I find it helpful to imagine the person I’ve been casting as the Villain with a big red bow on top of their head—the unexpected gift of learning and growth I didn’t ask for, and didn’t want, but am being given nonetheless. </p>
<p><em>Try asking yourself: What might this situation be trying to teach me? What growth is being asked of me here, even if I didn’t sign up for it?</em></p>



  


<h2>Finally, Get Creative</h2>
<p>With compassion and curiosity as your foundation, more creativity becomes available. This is where we move from stuck to accountable—not waiting to be rescued, not rehearsing the blame story, but taking accountability for our own learning and growth.</p>
<p>It doesn’t have to be a grand gesture. Small experiments are often the wisest—a different kind of conversation, a boundary named for the first time, help asked for rather than waited on. The point is that you’re no longer waiting for someone to save you. You’re trusting yourself to be in relationships with others.</p>

<p><em>Try asking yourself: How do I want to show up for myself and others in this situation? How will this help me learn to trust myself to be in healthy relationships?</em></p>
<h2>Where to Start</h2>
<p>Trusting others will always be complicated. People will sometimes disappoint us—sometimes significantly, and sometimes for reasons entirely within their control. We don’t have to pretend otherwise.</p>

<p>But the question of whether we trust ourselves is one we can actually do something about. Learning to show up for ourselves, to advocate for what we need, to set healthy limits, and to not abandon ourselves when things get hard—this is the foundation that makes navigating who to trust, when to trust, and how to trust others possible.</p>

<p><em>What might change in your relationships if you trusted yourself more?</em></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/from-functioning-to-flourishing/202602/do-you-find-it-hard-to-trust-others" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/from-functioning-to-flourishing/202602/do-you-find-it-hard-to-trust-others</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/from-functioning-to-flourishing/202602/do-you-find-it-hard-to-trust-others</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Michelle McQuaid Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/Man_Woman_Fighting.jpeg.jpg?itok=Sa3KpntU" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[3 Ways to Inoculate a Narcissistic Co-parent's Alienation]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/erinleonardedit.jpg?itok=ObO6nG4A" alt="Erin Leonard Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Divorce</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">3 Ways to Inoculate a Narcissistic Co-parent's Alienation</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Salvage your attachment with your child by using these three strategies.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">A narcissistic co-parent almost always engages in parental alienation.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Parental alienation occurs when your ex plays the victim and shifts all blame onto you.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Kids are programmed to protect their attachment relationships and jump in to help one that seems victimized.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>A narcissistic co-parent can be vindictive and seems to have an insatiable need to “win” every power struggle during a divorce. In many instances, they involve the kids and have no qualms about turning your own kids against you. Alternatively, <em>you<strong> </strong></em>want to put the dysfunctional marriage behind you and move forward, prioritizing your kids' health and happiness. The last thing you want is for the kids to endure any additional suffering.</p>

<p>Parental alienation takes place when one parent plays the victim with the kids and manipulates them into taking care of them while influencing them to turn their back on you. For example, “You and your dad and your sisters are together in the home that used to be mine. I am completely alone in an apartment. I have never been so lonely. I’m not sure I’m going to make it through this.” When a child hears this, they instantly panic. Biologically, neurologically, psychologically, and emotionally, kids are programmed to protect their attachment relationship. Without a second thought, the child dives in to help a parent that they believe is in peril.</p>

<p>After the child drops everything to attend to this parent, the parent will further “chain” them to their side by making the child think that they are the only ones who can help them. For example, “What would I do without you? You help me so much. I always know I can count on you. You are the only one who truly helps me.” Now, the child believes that they are responsible for helping their vulnerable parent through hard times… that the parent’s well-being is on their shoulders. This is often referred to as parentification, and it creates intense and constant anxiety in a child and prevents them from enjoying their own childhood.</p>

<p>To boot, the narcissistic co-parent continually blames you for their “ruined life.” They say things like, “Your mom takes so much child support that I can barely survive. I cannot afford to buy groceries.” Or “Your dad took my entire retirement account. I’ll be working until I die.”</p>
<p>Basically, they exaggerate, manipulate, and continue to play the victim while blaming you for their terrible plight in life, and when the child rushes to their side and rejects you, the narcissistic co-parent immediately acts stable and happy. The child now thinks that they have no choice but to rebuff you because they believe it is the only way to keep their vulnerable parent stable. Constantly worried about this parent, they are relieved when they appear happy.</p>

<p>Because you do not play the victim and you would never ask your child to take care of your emotional needs, the child perceives you as strong and in no need of any help. They also blame you for “ruining” your co-parent’s life. In their mind, you deserve to be punished.</p>
<p>Once a child is manipulated by the co-parent, they are almost impossible to reach. It seems like the more you try to help them see the dysfunctional dynamic, the more they perceive you as the “bully” that the other parent says you are. Also, kids despise parental drama, and your child has already made up their mind, so they refuse to listen to you. It’s awful, and it may seem hopeless, but it is not. Several strategies may help.</p>

<h2>Three Strategies</h2>
<p>First, avoid bringing up the other parent. Help your child with the emotional mistreatment that they experience with your co-parent when <em>they<strong> </strong></em>identify that they need your help. When they ask for assistance, refrain from saying anything negative about your co-parent and instead empathize. For example, “You were really shocked and disappointed. I get it, honey. I would feel the same way. You have every right to feel like that.” By empathizing, you are helping them emotionally, but you are not doing what your co-parent does, which is to trash you at any chance they get. Also, you are keeping the focus on your child. This is essential. Next, assist them in thinking about how to manage the predicament in the future so they can protect themselves.</p>

<p>Second, honor their perspective any chance you get. For example, in the car, they mention that they like a new rapper. You may not like rap, but you honor your child’s perspective. For example, “I’m glad you like them, honey. It’s fun to discover new artists. Music is so therapeutic sometimes.” Validating their viewpoint, even though you have a different perspective, is something that your co-parent may find difficult. A narcissistic co-parent often lacks the ability to consider a different perspective due to their “my way or the highway” attitude. They also believe that they are always right, so they may continually rebuff your child for expressing an opinion that differs from theirs. Unfortunately, your child may have quickly learned to censor themselves and may have already trained themselves to think like your co-parent to avoid emotional abuse.</p>


<p>Third, tell them funny and adorable stories about them as babies and small children. Most kids love hearing about themselves when they were younger. The narratives also validate their deeper qualities. For example, perhaps the story is about your son saving an injured baby bird. Or it may be about your daughter standing up for a friend against a bully at the park. Meaningful stories are everything. They prove to your child that you have always been there, and that you have always <em>seen</em> them. You know who they are, and you can prove this by retelling sacred stories about them when they were much younger. Typically, a narcissistic parent has difficulties doing this. They are focused on getting what they want in the moment, and they prefer to keep things superficial and about themselves, so they lack the ability to identify and remember deep and profound attachment experiences with their children.</p>

<p>All three of these strategies have something in common. They allow you to differentiate yourself, relationally, from your co-parent. You can offer your child empathy, perspective-taking, and a deep understanding of who they are and have always been. Your co-parent has great difficulties with these things. Your child probably feels much different with your ex than they do with you. They must censor themselves, take care of your ex’s emotions, and endure the emotional abandonment that they experience when they fall short of their expectations. In time, they may recognize that one parent is emotionally safe, and the other is not. </p>



  


<p>You can find more information on this topic in my book, <em>How to Outsmart a Narcissist; Use Emotional Intelligence to Regain Control at Home, Work, and In Life</em>. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/peaceful-parenting/202602/3-ways-to-inoculate-a-narcissistic-co-parents-alienation" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/peaceful-parenting/202602/3-ways-to-inoculate-a-narcissistic-co-parents-alienation</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/peaceful-parenting/202602/3-ways-to-inoculate-a-narcissistic-co-parents-alienation</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Erin Leonard Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/D884192F-480C-40B7-AC9F-A65B24F6DE39.png.jpg?itok=bBCrWzcN" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>