<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 15:48:17 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 15:48:17 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How Your Mind Meets Retirement Determines Mood Gain or Pain]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-12/Loriann%20Oberlin.png.jpg?itok=z2gtNGqL" alt="Loriann Oberlin MS, LCPC" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Aging</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">How Your Mind Meets Retirement Determines Mood Gain or Pain</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">It's never too late to alter course and thrive in your second act.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Certain age markers drive more visits to therapy, but consider your options carefully for the best help.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">More than half of retirees take on other jobs to pay bills and get ahead. Passion-driven work is the best.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Loneliness, risks of depression, and alcohol misuse climb during the retirement years.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/pexels-cottonbro-4057763.jpg?itok=DGLVB_l1" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" title="cottonbro studio / Pexels" alt="cottonbro studio / Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: cottonbro studio / Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>“Often when you think you’re at the end of something, you’re at the beginning of something else,” the late Fred M. Rogers once said. Mister Rogers’ emotional intelligence impacts all ages of people who have big feelings around life changes, self-acceptance, new beginnings, loss, and loneliness.</p>
<h2>The Emotional Roller Coaster</h2>

<p>People anticipate the day they’ll have no commute, office gossip, or problematic people. Colleagues may offer gift cards, books, and travel advice, and pitch volunteer opportunities. Some fete with a party.</p>
<p>Those first few weeks may find the newly retired jetting to a well-deserved vacation. Some exhale responsi­bilities, sleep in, now off the clock. Yet for others, anxiety, disappointment, and despair surface when reality hits fantasy, especially if retirement was not their choice.</p>

<p>A business closes, artificial intelligence (AI) takes over a job, or a federal career ends amid RIF (reduction in force) or VERA (voluntary early retirement authority). In 2025, the term “fork in the road” quite aptly applied. Physically demanding jobs wear workers out; yet, with home and car payments, plus dependents, they cannot forgo work.</p>

<p>In a field clobbered by venture capital (VC) firms, even therapists have left practice rather than compromise licensure, ethics, and liability once they discover the downsides of large chains that lured them.</p>
<h2>Recognize the Symptoms</h2>
<p>An upcoming, zero-ending birthday summons reflection. Markers like 55 and 65 raise questions: Is this all there is? What have I accomplished? What’s left for me? How much longer can I survive in [said job]?</p>

<p>What if you’ve experienced a few months to decompress, then begin questioning whether ends meet amid inflation, housing, and other factors.</p>
<p>Mental health counselors see an uptick in requests due to anticipatory fear, sadness, and a loss of structure. Once retired, some experience morning chest heaviness, frequent headaches, tight muscles, aches and pains, evening dread, or a sense of malaise. Physical stress signs lead them to primary care doctors first.</p>

<p>As test results populate the patient’s portal and an anxiety diagnosis arises, referrals for counseling result. Research points to the relationship between depression and retirement; it’s not a normative part of growing older, according to a 2022 report in <em>Clinical Interventions in Aging</em>.<sup>1</sup></p>
<h2>Choosing the Right Help</h2>

<p>Those who anticipate this crossroads might use employee benefits while still at work. From a cost perspective, it’s smart. Beware, however, that employee assistance programs (EAPs) have drawbacks.</p>
<p>Market consolidation and VC-backed companies have subsumed EAPs into profit-driven networks. Because EAP provider pay is low, you may be assigned to therapists starting out. When you’re age 50 plus, discerning retirement and finances, you’ll often benefit from a seasoned, similarly aged counselor.</p>


<p>So, too, training matters. Social work degrees confer case management knowledge plus mental health care. To obtain a counseling degree at Johns Hopkins University, we were required to take career and life planning in addition to a range of clinical mental health and diagnosis courses.</p>
<p>If you opt for coaching, coaches who also have clinical licensure will better screen a client and slate them for mental health treatment when warranted.</p>

<h2>Retirement Counseling or Coaching</h2>
<p>If a client presents with anxiety, sadness, hopelessness, or worthlessness, hands down, I give them a mental health intake. They can also use most insurances to pay for my services. The 2022 aging study mentioned that Medicare reimbursement disincentivizes providers to accept Medicare. Yet, those on a fixed income often cannot afford $100 or more out of pocket for sessions.</p>



  


<p>Coaching, for new direction and life purpose, may mean fewer sessions, paid for privately at a negotiated rate. Because we tend to make life decisions based upon our values, I encourage values work, which is very experiential and thought-provoking, for all clients.</p>
<p>With a diagnosis, expect to monitor symptoms with short, weekly mental health assessments and delve into your circumstances. Research reports that marital satisfaction and strong, socially active relationships improve a retiree’s mental health. Marital therapy experience comes in handy. On the other hand, those who are removed from social networks and who move into residential long-term care are at greater depression risk.<sup>2</sup></p>

<p>Ask yourself who you miss from work. Think of all interactions, down to the barista in the lobby. What was the number of meetings, walk-abouts, conferences, even accolades you received on a formal or subtle basis? Without steady contact, loneliness sets in, which former Surgeon General Vivek Murthy dubbed a public health crisis.<sup>3</sup></p>

<h2>Opting to Work Differently</h2>
<p>Forecasting with a financial planner is wise, but when suddenly let go or forced out, it’s not too late. One in eight seniors has returned to work or plans to rejoin the workforce. More than half (54 percent) cite inflation and high costs of living as impacting their work/life decisions.<sup>4</sup></p>

<p>Those without sufficient savings can focus upon a different, less stress-filled job. Temp agencies offer short-term projects. Accountants can keep the books for small businesses; those knowledgeable in language, math, or other subjects might tutor. Childcare workers babysit for working parents. Live in a tourist-popular location? Consider renting your home while you travel.<sup>5</sup></p>

<p>Regardless of how you spend your days, passion-driven work helps best. Look at jobs with substantial employee discounts that lessen your cash outlay. Lastly, phase in retirement, working part-time or seasonally. This buffers the hit on your retirement portfolio while you add to Social Security.</p>
<h2>Overall Adjustments</h2>

<p>Whether you’re preparing to retire or already have:</p>
<ul>
<li>Write down changes you’d like: What do you want to see more of and less of, and what fills gaps so some things stay similar? This is a brain dump within a sectioned notebook for travel, volunteerism, and to-do lists. Ideas: Explore a new hobby or culture, learn a language or new software, tackle a clean-out project, or take up yoga, mindfulness, or gardening.</li>
<li>Identify mood and behavior changes, noticing irritability, lack of patience, anxiety, and hopelessness.<sup>6</sup> In a 2024 study on retirement happiness, 31 percent of retirees reported feeling forlorn, while those who reported more happiness filled their time with social activities, exercise, hobbies, and travel.<sup>7</sup></li>
<li>Don’t ignore problem behaviors. Compared to when they once worked, older adults often have higher alcohol con­sumption, less physical activity, poor dietary habits, and a higher incidence of smoking.<sup>8</sup></li>
<li>Engage in cognitively protective activities that involve memory and problem-solving. Break out the puzzles, books, and board games, inviting others. Start a game night, card, or Scrabble group, or host a book club.</li>
</ul>

<p><em>© 2026 by Loriann Oberlin, MS, LCPC</em></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-full-picture/202602/how-your-mind-meets-retirement-determines-mood-gain-or-pain" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-full-picture/202602/how-your-mind-meets-retirement-determines-mood-gain-or-pain</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-full-picture/202602/how-your-mind-meets-retirement-determines-mood-gain-or-pain</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Loriann Oberlin MS, LCPC]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-cottonbro-4057763.jpg?itok=pkHSgK8S" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Hunger Games: Why Diets Fail and Weight Loss Medicines Succeed]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/thomas-rutledge-edited-photo.jpg?itok=fUGEYwh1" alt="Thomas Rutledge Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Appetite</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Hunger Games: Why Diets Fail and Weight Loss Medicines Succeed</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Controlling hunger, not calories, is the Holy Grail of weight loss.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Until recently, weight loss has been a struggle and eventually a failure for most people.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">GLP-1 medicines not only enable broad weight loss success, but they also reveal the crucial role of hunger.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Whether via bariatric surgery, medicines, or lifestyle, hunger control is essential for long-term weight loss.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>After a century of futility, the seemingly impenetrable mystery of weight loss is nearly solved. Until late 2022, most of us were taught that the weight loss journey was paved with willpower. Our Sisyphean task was to create a caloric deficit through diet and exercise and maintain it indefinitely through deliberate effort, food, and activity tracking, and enduring lifestyle changes. For the minority, this formula succeeded.<sup>1</sup> Yet most people found that weight loss was a revolving door: No matter the method or the motivation, their weight eventually returned to roughly the same starting point.<sup>2</sup> </p>

<p>Then something unexpected happened. Following decades of clinical trials yielding ineffective or even dangerous weight loss medicines,<sup>3</sup> a new class of injectable medicines called GLP-1 agonists (GLP=glucagon-like peptide) arrived in 2022-2023.<sup>4</sup> Not only did the average GLP-1 user experience weight loss far surpassing that usually achieved through lifestyle changes alone, their weight loss generally came with minimal conscious effort. For the first time, people were suddenly achieving clinically significant weight loss without tracking calories, practicing specific diets, or willpowering themselves through high-volume exercise routines. The weight loss journey, for millions, had transformed from an uphill slog to a stroll in the park. </p>

<p>The purpose of this post is to explain this weight loss paradigm change, including how it benefits GLP-1 users and non-users alike. The greatest breakthrough from the GLP-1 medicine era was arguably not the novel psychopharmacology. It was shattering the illusion that weight loss was ever about calorie counting, exercise, or controversial diets. <em>Weight loss, instead, was always about controlling hunger.</em><sup>5 </sup></p>

<p>Turns out that weight loss was a real-life "Hunger Games." GLP-1 medicines simply offered us a reliable strategy for finally winning the game.</p>
<h2>Winning the Hunger Games</h2>
<p>To understand the remarkable effectiveness of bariatric surgery and GLP-1 medicines compared to traditional diet and exercise programs for weight loss, you must understand hunger. <em>Surprisingly to many people, the human body doesn't possess an internal calorie detector. </em>Your body doesn't know if you've eaten 500 calories or 5,000. Instead, our body evolved to rely on biological proxy systems that, until the recent era of ultra-processed food, functioned extraordinarily well to regulate our weight and appetite across times of feast and famine. These systems include:</p>

<ol>
<li>Stretch detectors in the stomach to register food volume.<sup>6</sup></li>
<li>Appetite hormones such as leptin, insulin, and GLP-1 that partly regulate hunger and satiety.<sup>7</sup></li>
<li>Nutrient sensors in our gastrointestinal tract (GI) that alert the brain to essential nutrients such as proteins, fatty acids, and micronutrients (the complexity of these nutrient sensors is a reason that the human stomach/GI tract has more neurons than the entire brain of many other animals).<sup>8</sup></li>
<li>Palatability detectors in the mouth and brain (e.g., taste buds, brain reward pathways) to help us identify foods that are safe and nutritious.<sup>9</sup></li>
</ol>

<p>Consider the above mechanisms in understanding why many diets and exercise programs fail for long-term weight loss. </p>
<ul>
<li>Diets are generally low in food volume (failing to activate satiety through stretch receptors).</li>
<li>Diets tend to be low in nutrients (failing to stimulate nutrient sensors) and often low in palatability.</li>
<li>And, if too low calorie or too high in exercise volume, many diets and exercise programs activate leptin-signaling pathways that drive compensatory increases in appetite and reduced metabolic activity for many—but not all—people (i.e., lowering energy expenditure).<sup>10</sup> </li>
</ul>

<p><em>Increased hunger is the predictable result. </em>And if hunger is a horse, weight gain is the wagon it pulls closely behind. </p>
<p>The modern era of ultra-processed food consumption also appears to have driven dramatic rises in obesity and obesity-related health condition rates (e.g., diabetes, liver disease, many forms of cancer) by bypassing the above human satiety mechanisms. For instance:</p>


<ul>
<li>Ultra-processed foods frequently contain large amounts of energy (calories) in a size-condensed, low-nutrient, and highly palatable form. An ultra-processed diet is a near-perfect formula for producing fat gain, increased hunger, and frequent emotional cravings (i.e., psychological hunger) in humans due to the way it uniquely hijacks our brain and GI systems.</li>
<li>Alternatively, a nutrition plan consisting of high fiber and high protein from nutrient-dense whole foods is the single best eating strategy for achieving and maintaining a healthy weight.<sup>11</sup> Ideally, this nutrient plan is coupled with a moderate exercise routine that mitigates the compensatory metabolic responses often induced by high-volume exercise programs.</li>
</ul>

<p>Through precisely the same hunger mechanisms through which diets generally fail, bariatric surgery and GLP-1 medicine succeed. </p>
<ol>
<li>As a hunger control strategy, bariatric surgery is a blunt force instrument. Bariatric procedures directly modify the stomach and—in the case of gastric bypass surgery—the intestinal tract. The result is a long-term or even permanent reduction in hunger through improved stretch detector mechanisms (far less food is required post-surgery to trigger them) and increased function of appetite hormones.</li>
<li>If bariatric surgery is a sledgehammer approach to controlling hunger, GLP-1 medicines are a scalpel. First-generation (e.g., Wegovy), second-generation (e.g., Zepbound), and approaching third-generation (e.g., retatrutide) selectively enhance the function of specific appetite hormones and appear to modify palatability and food reward mechanisms. The result is reductions in both physical and psychological hunger for most users. </li>
</ol>



  


<h2>Takeaway</h2>
<p>No matter how you approach your goal of healthy weight loss, hunger is likely to be your most formidable opponent. Although the methods by which they control hunger vary, every effective dietary, physical activity, surgical, and medicinal approach to weight loss capitalizes on known human hunger and satiety mechanisms. In contrast, weight loss methods that fail to adequately control hunger through one or more of these mechanisms rarely produce lasting weight loss. All of us seeking long-term healthy weight management can benefit from the revelations yielded by the new GLP-1 medicines in enhancing our results. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-healthy-journey/202602/hunger-games-why-diets-fail-and-weight-loss-medicines-succeed" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-healthy-journey/202602/hunger-games-why-diets-fail-and-weight-loss-medicines-succeed</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-healthy-journey/202602/hunger-games-why-diets-fail-and-weight-loss-medicines-succeed</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Thomas Rutledge Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/openclipart-vectors-baby-2028307_1280.png.jpg?itok=fSOsC56V" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Self-Care Tips for Overwhelmed Parents]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2023-06/Lumanlan.jpg?itok=u-qf3M5y" alt="Lumanlan" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Parenting</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Self-Care Tips for Overwhelmed Parents</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How to deal with parental exhaustion when you can barely get through the day.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Tips for overwhelmed parents can start with the HALT framework: hunger, anger, loneliness, and tiredness.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">It may be better to be truly present for shorter periods than depleted all day.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">"Special Time" — 10 minutes of consistent daily play — can be more powerful than an unpredictable hour.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p dir="ltr">In Parts <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/parenting-beyond-power/202602/why-exhausted-parents-keep-snapping-at-their-kids">1</a> and <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/parenting-beyond-power/202602/parental-burnout-symptoms-and-the-shame-cycle-explained">2</a> of this series, we looked at what happens when your needs go unmet — your window of tolerance narrows, you snap at your kids, and then guilt keeps you stuck in the same patterns. You know you need to take care of yourself. But how do you actually do that when you're already running on empty?</p>

<h2 dir="ltr">Identifying what you actually need</h2>
<p dir="ltr">The HALT framework helps you identify the basic states that make everything harder. HALT stands for Hungry, Angry, Lonely, Tired — and when you're in any of these states, your window of tolerance gets narrower.</p>
<p dir="ltr">So before you can think about some elaborate self-care routine, start here:</p>

<p dir="ltr"><strong>Physical needs:</strong> Do you have food that's actually easy to eat? Are you getting actual rest, or just scrolling through your phone? Are you moving your body in ways that feel good to you?</p>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>Emotional needs:</strong> When was the last time another adult really saw you? Someone who actually <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/9599440/">asked how you're doing</a> and listened to the answer?</p>

<p dir="ltr"><strong>Connection needs:</strong> <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/25825706/">Brief conversations with people</a> who get it can matter more than you think. Sometimes it's just being around other people who treat you like a person instead of just someone's parent.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><a href="https://psycnet.apa.org/record/2001-03012-001"><strong>Autonomy</strong></a><strong>:</strong> Do you get to make any choices about your own time? Even small ones help — choosing what to eat, when to go to bed, whether to read or watch something.</p>

<h2 dir="ltr">What small changes actually look like</h2>
<p dir="ltr">When parents finally start making progress with their triggers, they usually don't do anything dramatic. The changes are small and concrete:</p>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>Reduce the number of decisions you make when you're already depleted.</strong> Cook batches of food on the weekend. Lay out clothes the night before. Create simple routines that require less mental energy.</p>

<p dir="ltr"><strong>Protect your </strong><a href="https://yourparentingmojo.com/captivate-podcast/boundariesrevisited/"><strong>energy by saying no.</strong></a><strong> </strong>Each yes to something else is a no to your own capacity to stay regulated.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>Ask for specific help.</strong> Try: "Could you watch the kids Saturday morning so I can rest?" Make it easy for people to actually help.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>Find small moments of connection.</strong> Brief conversations with neighbors, a text exchange with a friend who gets it, five minutes of chat with another parent at pickup. Being seen as a person, not just as someone's parent.</p>

<h2 dir="ltr">When you're already depleted</h2>
<p dir="ltr">When you're already running on empty, dealing with parental exhaustion requires recognizing that you're depleted and making small choices that create tiny pockets of relief throughout your day.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>Use screens strategically.</strong> Put on a show your child will actually watch, and rest. Don't scroll through social media comparing yourself to everyone else. Actually close your eyes and rest.</p>


<p dir="ltr"><strong>Go outside if you possibly can.</strong> Even if all you do is sit while your child plays. Fresh air and a change of environment can help reset your nervous system a little bit.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>Ask yourself: What's ONE thing I can remove from today?</strong> Can you eat a frozen pizza instead of cooking? Skip one activity? Let some things stay messy?</p>

<p dir="ltr"><strong>How to talk with your child about this:</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">Be honest in <a href="https://psycnet.apa.org/record/1991-23887-001">age-appropriate ways</a>. "I’m feeling very tired. Even sleeping doesn't help right now."</p>
<p dir="ltr">Use metaphors that kids understand. "You know how when you're tired, and you go to sleep and wake up with energy? For me right now, my tank is so empty that sleep isn't enough. It's like a car with no gas. There's no gas station available. It takes time to refill."</p>



  


<p dir="ltr">Be clear about what's yours: "When I'm this tired, I get impatient. That's about me, not about you. You didn't do anything wrong."</p>
<p dir="ltr">Don't use terms like "parental burnout". That sounds to a child as though it's their fault for being too much.</p>
<p dir="ltr">After you recharge, even a little bit, repair: "I was grumpy earlier. That wasn't about you. I was very tired and I didn't handle it well. I'm sorry."</p>

<h2 dir="ltr">Building ongoing support</h2>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>If you have a partner, talk together about the balance of stressors and resources.</strong> What's draining each of you? What helps? You're recognizing when one person's tank is lower and shifting the load temporarily.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>Find your village (even when it feels impossible).</strong> Friends who won't judge are worth their weight in gold. Online communities can help if they actually support rather than create more comparison. If a group makes you feel worse about yourself, leave it.</p>

<p dir="ltr"><strong>Getting professional support matters too.</strong> There's a free online tool called the <a href="https://en.burnoutparental.com/suis-je-en-burnout">Parental Burnout Assessment</a> developed by researchers at UC Louvain. It can help you see where you are and which factors are weighing on you most heavily.</p>
<h2 dir="ltr">What this actually looks like</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Researcher Moïra Mikolajczak puts it this way: It's better to be truly present for shorter <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29946278/">periods than depleted all day</a>.</p>

<p dir="ltr">That might sound like this: "I'll play with you for 10 minutes and we can build blocks together. Then I need some quiet time. After that, we'll have a snack together."</p>
<p dir="ltr">The key is follow-through. When you say you need quiet time, actually take it. And when you say you'll reconnect, actually do it.</p>
<p dir="ltr">This is where "Special Time" comes in. Special Time is about 10 minutes of consistent, daily play where your child chooses the activity and you offer your full attention. Ten minutes every day is far more powerful than an hour that happens unpredictably.</p>

<p dir="ltr">This routine communicates something essential to your child: "You're special. I love you. I want to spend time with you."</p>
<p dir="ltr">They also learn something else: Adults have needs, too. Meeting those needs is healthy and normal and not something to apologize for.</p>
<p dir="ltr">You're modeling self-care. You're showing them how to recognize when their own tank is getting low and honor that.</p>

<h2 dir="ltr">Final Thoughts</h2>
<p dir="ltr">The process of learning to recognize when you're getting depleted and actually doing something about it takes practice. You might try things that don't work. You might forget and push through anyway. Eventually, you get better at catching yourself earlier.</p>
<p dir="ltr">But even with all these strategies, guilt still shows up. In Part 4, we'll look at how to deal with parental guilt when it comes — because knowing you should meet your needs and actually doing it without feeling terrible about it are two different things.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/parenting-beyond-power/202602/self-care-tips-for-overwhelmed-parents" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/parenting-beyond-power/202602/self-care-tips-for-overwhelmed-parents</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/parenting-beyond-power/202602/self-care-tips-for-overwhelmed-parents</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Jen Lumanlan M.S., M.Ed.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-ekaterina-bolovtsova-7113344.jpg?itok=OpTgnzIx" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>