<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 13:08:14 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 13:08:14 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Quiet Power of Awe]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-12/Sam%20Goldstein.png.jpg?itok=kLaUD2vO" alt="Sam Goldstein Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Awe</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Quiet Power of Awe</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Why curiosity matters more then certainty.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Awe shifts attention away from the self and opens perspective.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Awe supports meaning without needing certainty or belief.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Small moments of attention can counter burnout and numbness.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>As children, awe came naturally. We would carefully watch an ant walking across the street, look at the clouds, and ask thousands of silly questions. As time progressed, a lot of us learned to bypass those moments and instead fo­cus on efficiency, knowledge, and busyness. In our fast-paced lives, most of us seem to have lost that quiet sense that life is an endless source of mystery and beauty. We should take the time to appreciate both.</p>

<p>Awe is not childish or naive. It is not about pretending everything is magical or good. Awe is simply the ability to be moved by what we do not fully understand, and right now, we need it more than ever. Awe helps us see beyond ourselves. Several times per day, we tend to have a very narrow point of view—our thoughts are focused on deadlines, fears, and an incredibly long list we need to work through to fix. The concept of awe is a tool for interrupting our regular, everyday routines and allows us to step back and look at the bigger picture; we are a part of this huge picture, not just one small area of it.</p>

<p>Psychologists studying wonder and awe have found that when one experiences awe, the normal mindset has loosened—be it through nature, thoughts, artwork, or another person demonstrating goodness. This results in decreased defensiveness and self-absorption. Numerous studies have demonstrated that experiencing awe increases one's sense of connectedness to others; at the same time, an individual's receptivity to other viewpoints increases (Keltner and Haidt, 2003). The significance of this cannot be overstated in a culture that fosters speed and certainty. Hence, astonishment allows us to stop, be humble, and know that there is no need to overpower or explain everything right away. Simply acknowledging and feeling differently as a result of what we see can be sufficient.</p>

<p><strong>Awe Brings Meaning Without Demanding Answers</strong></p>
<p>Many people today are hungry for meaning but wary of grand explanations. Awe offers a middle ground. It does not hand us answers. It gives us a sense that meaning is present even when clarity is not. Aristotle believed that wonder and knowledge from our personal experience and reflection were essential. To Aristotle, the act of awe and exploring why things happen in the world is at the root of all thinking and the desire to learn and grow (Aristotle, 1933). Modern research supports this ancient way of thinking. Studies have demonstrated that individuals who have greater opportunities to experience awe and wonder and express their awe tend to have a greater sense of meaning and purpose in their lives. They are more likely to act kindly and think beyond their immediate self-interest (Piff and colleagues, 2015). Wonder shrinks the ego just enough to make room for empathy.</p>

<p>While it is not exclusively religious or an epiphany, the experience of awe can come from discovering information that alters your perception of the world around you, watching someone demonstrate tremendous strength of character without the need for validation, or even realizing how fragile and improbable your personal existence is. Thus, it is an emotional reaction rather than a logical or defined explanation. Awe protects individuals from suffering from <em>burnout</em>, but it is more than just feeling tired. It is an emotional state in which everything around the individual loses its vibrancy. Individuals experience everything as <em>heavy</em> or <em>dull</em>. The act of experiencing wonder helps to add vibrancy back into life.</p>

<p>When we engage in an experience that generates awe, our personal clocks appear to have slowed down. As our personal worries recede into the background, it does not mean that we are escaping; it means we are restoring ourselves as individuals. Research shows that experiencing awe positively impacts mental health. It decreases repetitive thought patterns and egocentric thought processes. Thus, it provides mental reprieve from the continuous sounds that echo inside our heads (Shiota and colleagues, 2007). The smallest forms of awe are a catalyst for change. For example, experiencing nightfall while standing under a clear sky; listening to a musical composition that communicates a meaning you would not have been able to articulate; reading a sentence that changes how you view yourself. These moments do not fix everything, but they remind us that life contains more than our current stress.</p>

<p>The problem is not that awe is rare. The problem is that we are distracted. When every spare moment is filled, when silence feels uncomfortable, when everything must be explained or shared immediately, awe struggles to survive.</p>
<p><strong>Making Room For Wonder Again</strong></p>
<p>Awe cannot be forced, but it can be invited. It begins with attention. By letting some moments remain unresolved while choosing curiosity over judgment. This might mean walking without headphones or reading slowly instead of skimming, and allowing yourself to feel moved without immediately reaching for analysis or commentary. It might mean asking questions you do not expect to answer.</p>

<p>Awe does not erase grief and frustration or eliminate fear. However, awe creates a framework for dealing with negative emotions. It allows us not only to acknowledge that grief, frustration, and fear exist but also to gain a greater perspective on life as a whole. Those negative emotions are part of the bigger picture and do not define our entire lives. Life has become more about control than curiosity. Awe provides us with an avenue for quiet defiance. In doing so, awe reminds us that there are still things out there that could catch us off guard.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/common-sense-science/202601/the-quiet-power-of-awe" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/common-sense-science/202601/the-quiet-power-of-awe</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/common-sense-science/202601/the-quiet-power-of-awe</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Common Sense Science]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/Screen%20Shot%202026-02-22%20at%209.10.06%20AM.png.jpg?itok=oEIJLLHS" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What to Do When You Start Racing Too Fast]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2023-06/Gerlach.jpg?itok=G33R7vSa" alt="Gerlach" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Anxiety</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">What to Do When You Start Racing Too Fast</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Running in a million directions can leave you stuck in one place.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 23, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Anxiety, mania, stress, and other causes can speed us up.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Slowing down a racing mind can be tricky.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Mindfulness is a strategy of experiencing the present moment rather than racing to the next.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <blockquote><p>"It takes all the running you can do, to keep in the same place" –Lewis Carroll, Alice in Wonderland</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I glanced between my planner, book, computer, and phone. Where did I put my keys? I'd like to finish writing this PowerPoint before work, but I need to eat. Man, I've got that popcorn! Wait, who's texting me? Where are my keys again?</p>

<p>Racing: Some might call it the American way. In industrialized countries like the United States, we even walk faster (Levine and Norenzayan, 1999)—and in the U.S. are more likely to get hit by a vehicle while walking (Buehler and Pucher, 2023). </p>
<p>Productivity is often glorified in our culture. Taking on several tasks at once may be glamorized as a sign of hard work and dedication. But when is fast too fast?</p>

<blockquote><p>"I'm in a hurry to get things done. </p>
<p>Oh, I rush and rush until life's no fun. </p>
<p>All I've really got to do is life and die </p>
<p>but I'm in a hurry and don't know why" –Alabama, 'I'm in a Hurry' </p>
</blockquote>
<h2>A Virtue or a Problem?</h2>
<p>On a societal level, some have argued that a faster pace of life could be in part responsible for much of our growing mental health crisis, particularly in urban areas (Prakash et al., 2023). From a more individual perspective, speeding through days can lead us to miss out on the little details, new opportunities to align with our values, and the small interactions that build meaningful relationships.</p>

<p>Still, with so much to do and so little time to do it, what can we do? What strategies can help us organize our thoughts without getting overwhelmed? When does fast become too fast or indicative of a greater challenge?</p>
<p>Times of high activity are relatively normal, particularly during specific phases of life, like young adulthood. Many people have a heightened need for activity and novelty. Still, speeding day after day can sometimes be indicative of a larger struggle.</p>

<h2>The Clinical Significance of a Racing Pace</h2>
<p>A racing pace of life does not give us time to dwell. For some, consistently working extra hours or taking on multiple projects can be a way of avoiding painful thoughts and memories like those associated with grief. Still, what we are avoiding does not go away. It often has a message that needs to be processed. Without taking the time to hear it, our emotional well-being takes a toll.</p>

<p>Racing thoughts can also be common during times of high anxiety and for people with ADHD. Jumping from worry to worry can be exhausting and fuel a fire of nervous energy without giving time to solve the problems at hand. Creating a strategy for addressing worry through a mix of dedicated planning time, relaxation tools, and social connection is likely to foster more relief.</p>

<p>Finally, extreme, racing thoughts and activity can be a sign of hypomania or mania. These towering mind states are linked with bipolar disorder and cause a leap in energy. When racing accompanies mania, it accelerates past a person's normal pace of interacting with the world. The mood also will involve other symptoms like decreased need for sleep, spending sprees, grandiosity, and irritability.</p>


<p>Mania usually requires evaluation and treatment by a mental health professional.</p>
<h2>5 Ways to Regroup</h2>
<p>If you are struggling with a racing mind, here are five steps that you can take to regroup.</p>
<p><em>1. Take Time to Set Intentions</em></p>
<p>As someone with a propensity to fly, I've learned the value of five minutes. Whether it's time lying in my hammock while listening to the birds, or just being on the couch, I try to give myself moments throughout the day to set my intentions. What do I hope for today? Who should I check in with? What do I have planned, and what values do I wish to enact as I walk through my day? Those five minutes have sometimes been the difference between a haphazard sprint and a purposeful stride as I navigate the coming hours.</p>

<p><em>2. Write (or Draw) a Plan By Hand</em></p>
<p>In this digital age, most of us utilize some virtual resource, like an email calendar or app, to organize our time. There's nothing wrong with this. We can only write so quickly, and so in a way this forces us to gather our thoughts. Writing by hand also helps with memory. A meta-analysis of studies involving handwritten notes consistently found that college students who handwrote their notes had higher achievement than those who typed them (Flanigan et al., 2024). Specifically, writing an agenda by hand—whether for your day or life dreams—gives space for intentionality that digital tools often lack.</p>



  


<p><em>3. Engage Imagery</em></p>
<p>Imagery is a powerful style of meditation. Most are familiar with the concept of bringing to mind a picture of a beautiful place. Still, possibilities for visualization are endless. One imagery technique from compassion-focused therapy is called compassionate self-meditation. In your mind's eye, you can create an image of your core compassionate self. The picture might resemble you, or it could be a symbol, like an animal or a color. You imagine the image holding qualities of compassion-like wisdom and courage, in addition to any other attributes you would like to add. You can envision merging with it. This exercise helps us to clarify our values and strengthen our core (Gilbert, 2009).</p>

<p><em>4. Reminisce</em></p>
<p>If setting intentions is for the beginning of something, reminiscence is for after. Often, when we encounter a positive experience, we are so quick to move on to the next thing that we miss out on appreciating our first experience to the fullest extent. Reminiscing on and savoring the good things are vital skills to enjoying life.</p>

<p><em>5. If You Can't Slow Down on Your Own, Get Help</em></p>
<p>Changing your pace of life is not an easy endeavor. Still, if you are finding that your mind is racing out of control, it may be time to talk to a mental health professional. Specific psychotherapies can strengthen skills for focus and mindfulness. In addition, when relevant, biological treatments can be utilized to treat underlying conditions like ADHD or bipolar disorder.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>In most cases, a quick pace of life is not indicative of a greater concern. Many people are simply active people. Yet, there can be serious drawbacks when we continue to spin in excess without taking time to slow down. For some, it can also be indicative of clinical conditions like avoidance, anxiety, ADHD, mania, or a coping mechanism for trauma. Keeping a pulse on your life pace can help you make the most of it.</p>

<p><em>To find a therapist, please visit the </em><a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/therapists"><em>Psychology Today Therapy Directory</em></a><em>. </em></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/beyond-mental-health/202503/what-to-do-when-you-start-racing-too-fast" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/beyond-mental-health/202503/what-to-do-when-you-start-racing-too-fast</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/beyond-mental-health/202503/what-to-do-when-you-start-racing-too-fast</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Jennifer Gerlach LCSW]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2025-03/pexels-goksutaymaz-26892608.jpg?h=d7f1de5d&amp;itok=h37Fpgm9" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>