<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Psychology Today – Latest]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Latest articles from Psychology Today (full content)]]></description>
        <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 05:02:36 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 05:02:36 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Risks of Replacing Human Subjects With NPCs]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-08/Ian%20MacRae.png.jpg?itok=iQv3Utdx" alt="Ian MacRae" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Artificial Intelligence</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Risks of Replacing Human Subjects With NPCs</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Understanding human uniqueness is more vital than ever.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 22, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Digital participation follows a 90-9-1 rule; most text is generated by a handful of people.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">LLMs shift their persona to appear more socially desirable when evaluated.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Synthetic data often amplifies superficial stereotypes found in correlated datasets.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Studying "Non-Player Characters" in software is no substitute for understanding unique human characteristics.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>In the wake of a failed 1953 uprising in East Berlin, the playwright Bertolt Brecht wrote the satirical poem <em>Die Lösung</em> (The Solution). Mocking the government’s disappointment in its citizens, he suggested that if the people had lost the confidence of the regime, instead of dissolving the government, it would be simpler for the government to "dissolve the people and elect another."</p>

<p>As psychologists increasingly use Large Language Models (LLMs) to automate workflows for tasks such as analyzing data, drafting results, and even generating synthetic data, we should keep Brecht’s ironic suggestion in mind. While LLMs are powerful tools, we must be clear-eyed: When researchers study synthetic output by generating what are basically non-player characters (NPCs), they are studying the mechanics of software, not human minds, and we should not let human research dissolve into synthetic replacements.</p>

<h2>A Small Subset of Participants</h2>
<p>AI models do not learn from the world’s population. They learn from the very small subset of the population that leaves massive text-based footprints across the internet. We should not imagine these trillions of words are representative of the full population. They belong to a minority who likes to broadcast, and in that sense, they are unusual.</p>

<p>Digital spaces act as a filter. Social media platforms are curated environments that reward specific behaviors while alienating others. Those who find the feedback loops of digital engagement rewarding stay and amplify their presence; those who find them draining or unrewarding go elsewhere. Certain personality traits tend to be over-represented on social media, while those with higher trait agreeableness tend to post less, for example.</p>

<p>This distortion is explained by the 90-9-1 rule: a rule of thumb where 90% of users are silent "lurkers," 9% contribute occasionally, and only 1% create the vast majority of content. Public, profile-based social media favors individuals comfortable with broadcasting provocative, emotionally charged, or grandiose behaviors. Training a model on this data captures a specific subset of behavior without recording the messy thought or genuine motivation behind it.</p>

<p>Users are performing for an audience and an algorithm. Performing for a social group is, of course, a normal human behavior that LLMs can replicate extraordinarily well.</p>
<h2>The Influence of Human Raters</h2>
<p>The over-representation of specific personality traits in training data is further reinforced by "preference tuning." To make AI safe and helpful, human raters score outputs. These raters (another unique subset of the population often working within specific corporate cultures) unconsciously reward agreeable and sycophantic behaviors.</p>

<p>Research indicates that LLMs exhibit a social desirability bias that exceeds human standards. Salecha et al. (2024) found that models shifted their output substantially toward social desirability when they detected they were being evaluated.</p>
<p>Some researchers have also observed that LLMs respond differently to conversational prompts than to structured psychometric tests, suggesting they adapt their "personality" to give the user the result they want rather than reflecting a stable underlying structure. For instance, a model might demonstrate antisocial patterns in informal chat but present as perfectly "normal" when asked to complete a structured questionnaire.</p>

<h2>Synthetic Stereotypes</h2>
<p>When we move from general personality to specific diagnostic and identity-based labels, these distortions are amplified. Synthetic data has been found to amplify stereotypical clusters. If you instruct a language model to simulate a specific type of person, it is more likely to connect attributes like race, religion, gender, or sexuality with clinical labels that are modestly correlated.</p>

<p>Because these attributes are correlated in research data, and potentially training data, LLMs play up the connections, amplifying superficial associations. This might simulate behavior convincingly, but it cannot replicate the underlying reasons for those associations.</p>
<h2>The Hazard of Predictable Results</h2>



  


<p>The danger for psychology is that we are in the business of trying to understand the messiness of the human condition. Human data is often noisy, contradictory, and stubbornly refuses to fit a hypothesis. Synthetic data is output from software generated to satisfy the researcher.</p>
<p>Even within basic game theory tasks, models vary substantially. For example, some researchers GPT-4 showed hyper-cooperative behavior, while Llama-3 can appear more "exploitative." Westwood (2025) argues that the foundational assumption of survey research, that a coherent response is a human response, is no longer tenable.</p>

<p>A more subtle threat is "synthetic experimental demand." LLMs may be able to guess a researcher’s hypothesis and produce data that artificially conforms to a researcher's expectations. This has the potential to create a closed loop where the AI gives the researcher exactly what they are looking for, not because it represents human truth, but because the model's predictive training identifies the most likely result expected by the prompt. This feedback loop could lead to a scientific process that merely validates the researcher's biases at scale, effectively corrupting the process from within by manufacturing the desired results.</p>

<h2>Maintaining the Human Anchor</h2>
<p>Psychology is the study of people, not the study of predictive text. While LLMs are remarkable tools, if we are studying the output of language models, we are no longer psychologists; we are software testers. We must be wary of any solution that involves removing the actual person from the process of human research.</p>

<p>The moment we find it easier to study a model than a person, we’ve simply elected a more convenient electorate that doesn’t exist. Generating a personality without a person, creating Non-Player Characters (NPCs) in software, might be an interesting experiment in coding, it will likely have many useful applications, but it is not human psychology.</p>

<p>We have blown past the Turing test. In doing so, it has become apparent that much behavior that appears human is no longer a distinguishing feature of humanity. This is an incredible time for psychologists precisely because we now face the tricky challenge of distinguishing what is real and unique about human thought and behaviour. Understanding that difference reveals everything about what it means to be human</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/silicon-psyche/202602/the-risks-of-replacing-human-subjects-with-npcs" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/silicon-psyche/202602/the-risks-of-replacing-human-subjects-with-npcs</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/silicon-psyche/202602/the-risks-of-replacing-human-subjects-with-npcs</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Ian MacRae]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-tima-miroshnichenko-6498302.jpg?itok=BhwAp-OK" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Singlehood as an Identity]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/elyakim_kislev-removebg_0.png.jpg?itok=9VAaOlfK" alt="Elyakim Kislev Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Singlehood</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Singlehood as an Identity</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Why do some single people feel depleted, while others feel good about it?</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 22, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">For some adults today, singlehood is not just a status. It can operate as a meaningful, organizing idea.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Single people are often not only aware of being single, they are also aware of being counter-normative.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">It's key not to treat singlehood as a uniform condition. Social conditions and contexts play a huge role.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/ChatGPT%20Image%20Feb%2022,%202026,%2001_35_02%20PM.png.jpg?itok=6Oypor76" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" title="AI Generated (ChatGPT 5.2)" alt="AI Generated (ChatGPT 5.2)"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: AI Generated (ChatGPT 5.2)</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Singlehood has long been treated as a relationship status: a box you check until you’re in a different box. In research and in everyday conversation, that framing quietly sets couplehood as the default endpoint and casts single life as a transitional phase. But for some adults today, singlehood is not just a status. It can operate as an identity, an organizing idea that carries meaning, guides choices, and shapes how a person understands their place in the social world.</p>

<p>In a review article titled "<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/10463283.2023.2241937">Singlehood as an identity"</a>, I argue that singlehood is increasingly experienced as a social category in itself and that psychology needs better tools to capture that reality. This notion helps explain a familiar puzzle: why some single people feel depleted or marginalized, while others feel grounded, socially connected, and even energized. If singlehood is merely a status, we tend to ask blunt questions like “Are singles happier than partnered people?” But if singlehood can be an identity, then the more useful question becomes: What does singlehood mean to this person, and how central is it to their sense of self?</p>

<h2>From status to story</h2>
<p>“Single” can be a description, but it can also be a story. As a description, it answers a demographic question. As a story, it can carry meaning: I’m behind / I’m not chosen, or I’m free / I’m open, but not waiting. Two people can share the same relationship status and yet live singlehood as entirely different psychological experiences.</p>

<p>In particular, the singlehood-as-identity framework proposes three broad identity positions: counter-normative, peripheral, and core. They are not moral labels or fixed boxes people must fit into forever. They are a map for understanding how singlehood shows up in the self-concept and in social life.</p>

<p>When singlehood is experienced as counter-normative, the person is not only aware of being single. They feel that being single is socially “wrong,” disallowed, or judged. This experience often intensifies when people want partnership but feel pressured by timelines, family expectations, or cultural scripts. It can also appear when someone is content with their single life but anticipates stigma anyway, because the social environment is organized around couplehood as the unquestioned norm.</p>

<p>This is where singlism—the stereotyping and discrimination directed at singles—stops being an abstract concept and becomes an everyday stressor. A classic piece on the topic is "<a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-8721.2006.00446.x">The Unrecognized Stereotyping and Discrimination Against Singles</a>". Even subtle forms of singlism can matter: assumptions about maturity, warmth, or “why you’re still single,” and policies that quietly treat coupled life as the baseline.</p>

<p>When singlehood is a peripheral identity, it matters, but it does not define the person. It can be positive, negative, or mixed. Someone might enjoy their life and still be open to partnership later. Another person might feel frustrated and still interpret it as a temporary season. Singlehood affects routines and choices, but it remains relatively flexible, something that can change without threatening the integrity of the self.</p>

<p>When singlehood becomes a core identity, it looks less like “I’m single right now” and more like “I’m a single person.” Here, singlehood is experienced as deeply congruent with authenticity, priorities, and life design. This does not require an essentialist claim that singlehood is biologically fixed. It simply recognizes that, for some people, couplehood is not the default aspiration, and singlehood is not a waiting room.</p>

<h2>Why identity changes the well-being conversation</h2>
<p>Identity helps explain why findings about singlehood and well-being can look inconsistent. If a study averages together people who are living singlehood as counter-normative (high pressure, high stigma), people for whom it is peripheral (flexible and context-dependent), and people for whom it is core (authentic and self-defining), then a single “singles vs. couples” comparison cannot capture what’s really going on.</p>



  


<p>A major review that makes this within-group pivot explicit is "<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/17456916221136119">Coping or Thriving? Reviewing factors associated with well-being in singlehood</a>". The key move is not to treat singlehood as a uniform condition, but to ask which intrapersonal resources, relational contexts, and societal conditions are linked to thriving for different kinds of singles.</p>

<h2>What to ask instead of “Why are you still single?”</h2>
<p>If you’re a clinician, educator, or simply someone who cares about a single person, the identity lens suggests a small but powerful change. Before you interpret distress (or contentment) as “because they are single,” ask what singlehood means in their identity ecosystem. Does singlehood feel stigmatized or legitimate? Is it central or incidental? Is there a mismatch between what they want and what they have, or between what they value and what their environment rewards? Are they lonely, or socially connected but culturally pressured? Are they grieving a desired partnership, or building a life design that doesn’t center on couplehood?</p>

<p>These questions reduce the risk of pathologizing singlehood itself. They also make space for more tailored support: strengthening belonging, challenging internalized norms, building community, clarifying values, or (when someone truly wants partnership) pursuing it without shame-driven urgency and even from a place of a <a href="https://www.ucpress.edu/books/happy-singlehood/hardcover">happy singlehood</a>. </p>

<p>Indeed, singlehood-as-identity doesn’t claim that being single is always easy or always empowering, and it certainly doesn’t imply that wanting partnership is misguided. It makes a simpler, more humane point: being single is not a single psychological experience. When we ask what singlehood means, rather than assuming what it means, we stop debating singlehood in the abstract and start understanding single lives as they actually are.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/happy-singlehood/202602/singlehood-as-an-identity" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/happy-singlehood/202602/singlehood-as-an-identity</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/happy-singlehood/202602/singlehood-as-an-identity</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Elyakim Kislev Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/ChatGPT%20Image%20Feb%2022%2C%202026%2C%2001_35_02%20PM.png.jpg?itok=jC2sESXc" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A Sex Therapist's Critique of Wuthering Heights]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-11/Kat-Kova-Therapist-RP-Kat-Kova-Therapy-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=OQJ7XMoo" alt="Kat Kova MSc, RP" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Sex</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">A Sex Therapist's Critique of Wuthering Heights</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">A kink-informed, feminist, and trauma-aware perspective of the new film.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 22, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Romantic myths equate suffering with love.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Trauma shapes attachment and for some, chaos can feel like connection.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Care, consent, and choice define healthy relationships.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Agency and vulnerability can coexist within power imbalances.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Emerald Fennell’s 2026 rendition of <em>Wuthering Heights</em> draws viewers in with a provocative, kink-coded atmosphere reminiscent of <em>Fifty Shades of Grey</em>, similarly distorting what kink actually looks like while highlighting tensions around love, sexuality, power, and consent that feel deeply human and relevant. As a sex therapist, the film left me asking: What do these characters believe love is supposed to feel like? What options do they actually have? And how do history and social forces shape their choices?</p>

<h2>Trauma Bonding and the Shape of Love</h2>
<p>Heathcliff and Catherine grow up in emotionally harsh environments. When people learn love in conditions of insecurity, attachment can feel urgent and consuming. What looks obsessive from the outside may feel like recognition from the inside–finally, someone who understands me. When safety has been scarce, emotional volatility can feel like aliveness.</p>

<p>The chemistry between the leads is palpable. That does not mean their relationship is healthy–but it does mean it makes sense. Trauma shapes attachment. It teaches us what love feels like, what we expect from it, and what we fear losing. If calm, steady love feels unfamiliar, it can even feel threatening. When passion has been the only language of connection, quiet security may seem dull or unreal.</p>

<p>Understanding this softens the story. We are not simply watching villains; we are watching people loving with the tools they were given–while still recognizing that harm is harm, regardless of its origin.</p>
<h2>Intensity Is Not the Same as Care</h2>
<p>A kink-informed lens helps distinguish between intensity and health. Power and intensity are not inherently harmful; what matters is whether they are grounded in consent, mutual choice, and care.</p>

<p>Power becomes concerning when it is:</p>
<ul>
<li>Imposed rather than chosen</li>
<li>Rigid rather than responsive</li>
<li>Indifferent rather than attentive</li>
</ul>
<p>Do the characters experience their interactions as voluntary? Do they feel they can refuse, leave, or renegotiate? Do they articulate desire, or submit to forces they perceive as inevitable? These questions are especially compelling in Isabella’s storyline.</p>

<h2>Isabella: Empowered and Vulnerable</h2>
<p>Isabella is often dismissed as naïve for falling for Heathcliff, but that interpretation flattens her. She chooses him, pursues him, insists on him even when warned. At the same time, she is socially and emotionally vulnerable. Respecting her means taking her desire seriously, even if the outcome is painful.</p>

<h2>Does Heathcliff Care for Isabella?</h2>
<p>Here, Fennell offers rare clarity, allowing us to consider whether this relationship actually aligns with the principles that define healthy kink dynamics. Heathcliff’s involvement with Isabella is not grounded in care for her; he leverages her desire to provoke Catherine and fuel jealousy. In doing so, he turns Isabella into part of his emotional strategy even as she experiences empowerment within the dynamic.</p>


<p>Care shows up as curiosity about another person’s feelings. Passion without care is not devotion. Most kink relationships are grounded in consent and mutual respect, but practices involving power can magnify existing imbalances, which is why context matters: our vulnerabilities, the other person’s power, and the relational dynamic between them.</p>

<h2>The Tragic Roots of Romantic Love</h2>
<p>To understand why this story feels so dramatic, it helps to remember the cultural history of romance. In medieval Europe, courtly love stories idealized longing, suffering, and emotional torment, while real marriages were often structured around property and inheritance. Passionate love narratives existed in contrast to social reality.</p>



  


<p>Over time, we inherited cultural scripts suggesting:</p>
<ul>
<li>Love should feel overwhelming</li>
<li>Yearning proves depth</li>
<li>Suffering makes love meaningful</li>
<li>Security and excitement cannot coexist</li>
</ul>
<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Wuthering%20Heights%202_0.jpg?itok=4FE1XatB" width="320" height="479" data-insert-type="image" alt="The moors in Wuthering Heights" title="Matteo Badini/Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption">The moors in Wuthering Heights</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Matteo Badini/Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>It is no surprise that many famous love stories–from <em>Romeo and Juliet</em> to <em>Wuthering Heights–</em>end in tragedy. Turmoil is visually compelling. If we filmed only the most painful moments of a relationship, we would have powerful cinema. If we filmed the peaceful parts–the communication, repair, consent, and care–we might think nothing was happening. Healthy love rarely generates the chaos that fuels a plot.</p>

<p>This invites reflection: When did we learn that longing means love? Why does calm connection sometimes feel less convincing than dramatic pursuit? When we feel consumed by someone, are we experiencing love or recognition?</p>
<p>As sex and relationship therapists, we often emphasize that deeply satisfying relationships tend to be grounded in steadiness, respect, emotional safety, and genuine care–alongside passion and desire when those matter to the partners involved. But because healthy love would look like paint drying onscreen, and that doesn’t sell tickets, many of us are raised instead on stories of tragic romance.</p>

<h2>Consent Then and Now</h2>
<p>The story also unfolds within a world shaped by class hierarchy, gender norms, and limited options for women. Choice existed, but within constraints. Isabella chooses Heathcliff. Catherine chooses Edgar. Their decisions are real, yet shaped by the systems surrounding them.</p>
<p>This raises enduring questions: When is choice fully free? When is it shaped by pressure, fantasy, or limited alternatives? Can agency exist even when options are constrained? These questions rarely have simple answers, but they encourage humility and compassion toward choices that make sense in someone else’s world.</p>

<h2>A Feminist Lens on Choice</h2>
<p>Through a contemporary feminist lens–one that values women defining their own desires–Isabella’s story becomes less about foolishness and more about will. She acts. She decides. She chooses. We do not have to celebrate her choices to respect that they are hers.</p>
<p>A mature reading holds two truths at once: that Isabella has agency and power imbalances still surround her. The experience of being both self-directed and mistaken is, for many of us, deeply familiar.</p>

<h2>Why This Story Still Matters</h2>
<p>Stories like <em>Wuthering Heights</em> endure not because they show us what love should be, but because they reveal what many of us have been taught love is supposed to feel like. They reflect cultural myths that equate longing with depth and suffering with devotion, even as this film complicates those ideas through its portrayal of power and desire.</p>

<p>Viewed through this lens, what stands out is not only the characters’ volatility but how familiar it feels. Many people have mistaken emotional chaos for chemistry or longing for connection. The film exposes how desire can tangle with power, how agency can coexist with vulnerability, and how love can feel convincing even when it lacks care.</p>

<p>That is why the story still resonates. Not because it models love, but because it asks us to examine what we believe love is. Dramatic passion with kinky undertones thrown in for good measure may make alluring cinema, but in real relationships, it is care and consent–not chaos–that sustains us.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/make-love-make-sense/202602/a-sex-therapists-critique-of-wuthering-heights" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/make-love-make-sense/202602/a-sex-therapists-critique-of-wuthering-heights</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/make-love-make-sense/202602/a-sex-therapists-critique-of-wuthering-heights</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Kat Kova MSc, RP, PhD Candidate]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/Wuthering%20Heights%203.jpg?itok=XvDEP9RY" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Purpose Is Simple; Courage Is Hard]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-12/JordanGrumet.png.jpg?itok=iMVSYujM" alt="Jordan Grumet M.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Motivation</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Purpose Is Simple; Courage Is Hard</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Stop searching for your “why” and start moving toward what lights you up.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 22, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Purpose is easier to recognize than most people think when you focus on what energizes you.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The real obstacle to purpose is not clarity but the courage to take action.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">What excites you is a more reliable guide than searching for a grand life mission.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/giovannid-nature-3302773_1280.jpg?itok=TFyQi-a0" width="320" height="215" data-insert-type="image" title="Giovannid/Pixabay" alt="Giovannid/Pixabay"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Giovannid/Pixabay</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>There’s a persistent myth that purpose is complicated. That it requires years of soul-searching, a perfectly crafted mission statement, or some lightning-bolt moment of clarity that suddenly reveals why you exist. But that hasn’t been my experience either personally or professionally. Purpose, at its core, is actually quite simple.</p>

<p>What’s not simple is acting on it.</p>
<p>Most of us were taught to think of purpose as our <em>why</em>—a grand, overarching explanation for our lives. Something noble. Something impressive. Something that would look good printed beneath our name in a conference program. The idea sounds inspiring, but in practice it turns purpose into a high-stakes guessing game. We start trying on identities the way someone tries on outfits before a big event, hoping one finally fits. When none feel quite right, we assume the problem is us.</p>

<p>That’s when purpose starts to feel elusive, mysterious, and just out of reach.</p>
<p>When you believe there is only one correct answer to the question “Why am I here?” it creates a kind of psychological scarcity. You start to think there’s a single hidden purpose out there with your name on it and if you don’t find it, you’ve somehow missed your chance. It’s like searching for a needle in a football field of haystacks. The pressure alone is enough to paralyze you.</p>

<p>And paralysis feels a lot like confusion.</p>
<p>But what if we’ve been asking the wrong question all along?</p>
<h2>Rethinking Purpose </h2>
<p>In my experience, purpose isn’t a cosmic explanation. It’s behavioral. It isn’t something you discover in theory, it’s something you experience in action. A much more useful definition is this: purpose is what you do that lights you up.</p>

<p>Those moments are rarely hard to identify. Most people already know, at least intuitively, what energizes them. For one person, it’s dancing. For another, it’s hiking. Someone else feels most alive wandering through antique stores or playing pickup basketball or tinkering with code late at night. These are not mysteries. They’re clues.</p>

<p>When we stop obsessing over outcomes and instead pay attention to what genuinely pulls us in, purpose suddenly shifts from something abstract to something practical. Don't ask, <em>What am I meant to do with my life?</em> Instead ask, <em>What makes me feel most alive when I’m doing it?</em></p>
<p>That’s the simple part.</p>
<p>The hard part is what comes next.</p>

<h2>The Challenge of Taking Action </h2>
<p>Because once you know what lights you up, you still have to act on it. And action is where purpose tends to stall. Thinking about what excites you is safe. Doing something about it is not. Action requires effort, time, and the willingness to risk being bad at something. It asks you to step out of imagination and into exposure.</p>


<p>You like basketball? It’s easy to say so. It’s harder to find a game, organize a league, or sign up for one where you might be the worst player on the court. You enjoy writing? It’s pleasant to think about starting a blog. It’s much harder to hit publish and risk silence—or worse, criticism.</p>
<p>Action invites uncertainty, and uncertainty makes most of us uneasy.</p>

<p>That’s why purpose and courage are so tightly linked. Not because purpose itself is mysterious, but because living it requires you to face the possibility of failure. Every meaningful action carries some chance that it won’t work out. The league might never form. The blog might never grow. The podcast might launch to an audience of three.</p>



  


<p>Still, none of that invalidates the purpose. In fact, it confirms it.</p>
<p>I’ve run into this tension repeatedly in my own life. Starting my medical practice was an obvious step toward a purposeful career. I didn’t need years of reflection to know medicine energized me. But knowing that and actually building a business were two very different things. The paperwork, the logistics, the financial risk—all of it was intimidating. The path was clear. Walking it was not.</p>

<p>The same thing happened when I felt drawn to personal finance education. It was obvious to me that talking and writing about money lit me up. But recording my first podcast episode or submitting a book proposal felt like standing at the edge of a diving board. The water looked inviting. The jump still took nerve.</p>

<h2>Identifying Purpose Anchors </h2>
<p>That’s the pattern I see over and over: purpose is rarely hidden. Action is what we avoid.</p>
<p>If you feel stuck or uncertain about your purpose, the solution is surprisingly straightforward. Start with what I like to call your <em>purpose anchors</em>—the activities that consistently energize you. Not the things you think you should enjoy. Not the things that impress other people. The things that actually make you feel engaged, absorbed, or quietly satisfied.</p>

<p>Notice when time seems to move differently. Notice what you look forward to without being told. Notice what you return to even when no one is watching.</p>
<p>Once you’ve named those anchors, the next step is expansion. Ask yourself what actions could grow out of each one. If you love reading classic literature, could you start a small book group? Commit to one novel a month? Write essays about what you read? The moment you look for possibilities, you realize there are dozens. Maybe hundreds.</p>

<p>Purpose is rarely a single path. It’s usually a branching network.</p>
<p>Then comes the final step. The one most people resist. Do something. Anything. Take the smallest available action in the direction of what excites you. Momentum doesn’t appear first; it follows movement. Each concrete step, no matter how minor, lowers the psychological barrier to the next one.</p>

<p>You don’t need a master plan. You need a starting point.</p>
<h2>Purpose as a Spark</h2>
<p>We tend to think purpose should feel like a revelation. In reality, it behaves more like a spark. Sparks don’t look impressive at first. But given oxygen and fuel, they become fire.</p>
<p>So perhaps the real shift is this: stop treating purpose like a riddle you must solve before you can begin living. Instead, treat it like a direction you confirm by moving. The question isn’t “What is my purpose?” The question is “What action am I willing to take today toward something that energizes me?”</p>

<p>Purpose isn’t complicated. It’s behavioral. It’s immediate. It’s already whispering to you through your interests and curiosities.</p>
<p>All it asks in return is courage.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-regret-free-life/202602/purpose-is-simple-courage-is-hard" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-regret-free-life/202602/purpose-is-simple-courage-is-hard</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-regret-free-life/202602/purpose-is-simple-courage-is-hard</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Jordan Grumet M.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/giovannid-nature-3302773_1280.jpg?itok=bX4Ef-WC" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Most Dangerous Negotiation of All]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/cindywatsonbiopic.jpg?itok=71Xfb2ch" alt="Cindy Watson B.A., LLB, JD" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Domestic Violence</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Most Dangerous Negotiation of All</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Why “Just leave!” misunderstands the psychology of domestic abuse.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 22, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/sasun-bughdaryan-5dFJavB5Twk-unsplash.jpg?itok=QP7VH18J" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" title="Susan Bughdaryan / Unsplash" alt="Susan Bughdaryan / Unsplash"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Susan Bughdaryan / Unsplash</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>We are comfortable talking about negotiation in boardrooms, courtrooms, and political arenas. We are less comfortable acknowledging that some of the most complex negotiations happen behind closed doors, in relationships where power is weaponized and safety is uncertain.</p>
<p>When domestic violence enters the conversation, one question often surfaces with startling frequency: <em>Why doesn’t she just leave?</em> It is a question rooted in misunderstanding. And more critically, it reflects a failure to grasp the negotiation dynamics at play.</p>

<p><strong>Domestic Abuse as a Power Negotiation</strong></p>
<p>At its core, domestic abuse is not about anger management. It is about control. It is a sustained and strategic effort to dominate decision-making, limit autonomy, and erode a partner’s perceived options.</p>
<p>In negotiation theory, power derives from alternatives. The stronger one’s viable alternatives (often referred to as BATNA—best alternative to a negotiated agreement), the more leverage one holds. Abusers understand this intuitively. They systematically weaken their partner’s alternatives, isolating them from friends and family, undermining financial independence, destabilizing their self-confidence, and creating emotional dependency. The result is not simply fear. It is constrained choice architecture.</p>

<p>From the outside, leaving may appear to be a clear option. From the inside, the alternatives may feel perilous, inaccessible, even catastrophic.</p>
<p><strong>The Myth of Rational Exit</strong></p>
<p>Observers frequently assess abusive relationships through a rational-choice framework: If harm outweighs benefit, departure should follow. But abuse does not operate in clean economic equations.</p>

<p>Coercive control reshapes cognition. Gaslighting erodes trust in one’s own perceptions. Intermittent reinforcement—cycles of cruelty followed by affection—strengthens psychological attachment in ways well-documented in research.</p>
<p>Moreover, leaving is often the most dangerous phase of an abusive relationship. Studies consistently show that the risk of severe violence escalates when a victim attempts to exit. In negotiation terms, when a controlling party perceives loss of dominance, escalation frequently follows.</p>

<p>What appears to be passivity may in fact be a risk calculation.</p>
<p><strong>The Internal Negotiation</strong></p>
<p>Women in abusive relationships are often engaged in relentless internal negotiation:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>If I comply, will it protect my children?</em></li>
<li><em>If I leave, will he follow through on his threats?</em></li>
<li><em>Can I afford to survive on my own?</em></li>
<li><em>Will anyone believe me?</em></li>
</ul>

<p>These are not abstract questions. They are daily strategic assessments.</p>
<p>Fear plays a central role. In negotiation research, fear narrows perceived options and increases risk aversion. Under chronic threat, the brain prioritizes immediate survival over long-term freedom. Short-term de-escalation can feel safer than long-term uncertainty.</p>

<p>What outsiders interpret as weakness may actually be an attempt to manage volatility in an unstable system.</p>
<p><strong>The Cost of “Just Leave”</strong></p>
<p>The phrase “Just leave!” simplifies a multidimensional problem into a binary choice. It overlooks:</p>
<ul>
<li>Financial entanglement</li>
<li>Custody concerns</li>
<li>Cultural or religious pressures</li>
<li>Immigration vulnerabilities</li>
<li>Social stigma</li>
<li>Workplace consequences</li>
<li>Escalation risk.</li>
</ul>


<p>It also shifts responsibility onto the victim rather than interrogating the behavior of the abuser or the structures that enable abuse.</p>
<p>From a negotiation lens, it ignores that meaningful choice requires meaningful alternatives. Without safety planning, financial access, legal protection, and social support, departure is not a clean exit; it is a high-risk maneuver.</p>

<p><strong>The Role of Support Systems</strong></p>
<p>One of the strongest predictors of successful exit from abuse is the presence of a support network. In negotiation terms, having allies expands perceived and actual options.</p>
<p>This may include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Friends who listen without judgment</li>
<li>Employers who provide flexibility and confidentiality</li>
<li>Legal advocates who understand coercive control</li>
<li>Counselors trained in trauma-informed care</li>
<li>Community organizations that assist with safety planning.</li>
</ul>



  


<p>Support does not begin with strategy. It begins with belief. When someone discloses abuse, the most powerful first response is not advice. It is validation.</p>
<p>“I believe you.”<br>“You’re not crazy.”<br>“You don’t deserve this.”</p>
<p>These statements restore something abuse systematically erodes: self-trust.</p>
<p><strong>Workplace Implications</strong></p>

<p>Domestic violence does not remain confined to the home. It follows survivors into workplaces through harassment, stalking, absenteeism driven by safety concerns, and diminished concentration under chronic stress. Organizations that approach domestic violence solely as a “private matter” misunderstand its impact on performance, safety, and culture.</p>

<p>Employers who develop trauma-informed policies, provide confidential HR pathways, and train leaders to recognize coercive patterns are not overstepping; they are strengthening psychological safety. Negotiation, after all, flourishes in environments where dignity is protected.</p>
<p><strong>From Awareness to Action</strong></p>
<p>Addressing domestic abuse requires reframing the narrative. The question is not “Why doesn’t she leave?” but rather:</p>

<ul>
<li>What barriers limit her alternatives?</li>
<li>What risks is she calculating?</li>
<li>How can systems expand her choices safely?</li>
</ul>
<p>Empathy is not indulgence. It is strategic clarity.</p>
<p>When society better understands the hidden negotiations that survivors are navigating—between safety and survival, stability and escalation, hope and fear— it becomes possible to replace judgment with informed support.</p>

<p>And perhaps that is where the real negotiation begins.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/life-as-a-negotiation/202602/the-most-dangerous-negotiation-of-all" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/life-as-a-negotiation/202602/the-most-dangerous-negotiation-of-all</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/life-as-a-negotiation/202602/the-most-dangerous-negotiation-of-all</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Cindy Watson B.A., LLB, JD]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/sasun-bughdaryan-5dFJavB5Twk-unsplash.jpg?itok=VmbjqURP" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The First Task of Estrangement: Stabilize]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/authors/joshua_coleman.jpg?itok=BcCu51a1" alt="Joshua Coleman Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Parental Alienation</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The First Task of Estrangement: Stabilize</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">When estrangement overwhelms your body and mind.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 22, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Learning the art of self-compassion and self-soothing has to come first.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Reflection should come from understanding, not self-torture.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Healing doesn't always mean reconciliation; it means redefined identity.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>When you’re estranged from your child, the urge to fix, explain, or repair can feel overwhelming. Many parents come to me saying, “Just tell me what to do so I can make this better.”</p>
<p>The truth is uncomfortable—but freeing: Healing doesn’t begin with insight or action. It begins with stabilization.</p>
<p>What follows is a sequence that matters far more than most people realize. Not because it’s clever, but because it reflects how the nervous system actually works under emotional threat. If you try to skip steps, you don’t fail because you lack effort or insight. You struggle because your body and mind aren’t ready yet.</p>

<p>Let’s walk through it.</p>
<h2>1. Soothe</h2>
<p>Estrangement triggers a primal alarm system. Parents describe panic, shame, rage, and despair—often all in the same hour. When the nervous system is flooded, thinking clearly is nearly impossible.</p>
<p>This is why self-reassurance, grounding, self-compassion, and emotional containment must come first. Not self-analysis. Not problem-solving.</p>

<p>Soothing isn’t indulgent—it’s biological triage. Until your body settles, everything else will either escalate your distress or collapse into self-blame.</p>
<h2>2. Slow</h2>
<p>Once the initial surge eases, the next task is slowing down—not your life, but your inner tempo.</p>
<p>Estranged parents are often caught in urgency:</p>

<ul>
<li>“I need to respond now.”</li>
<li>“If I wait, I’ll lose them forever.”</li>
<li>“If I don’t say the right thing, this is over.”</li>
</ul>
<p>Slowing interrupts that false emergency. It creates space between feeling and action, which is where choice eventually becomes possible.</p>
<h2>3. Reflect</h2>
<p>Only after soothing and slowing can reflection become useful rather than punishing.</p>

<p>This is where many parents are pushed too early—sometimes by therapists, sometimes by cultural narratives—into asking, “What did I do wrong?”</p>
<p>But premature reflection often turns into a courtroom of self-torture rather than a place of understanding.</p>
<p>Healthy reflection asks different questions:</p>
<ul>
<li>What is the fuller context of this relationship?</li>
<li>What meaning am I assigning to the estrangement?</li>
<li>Where am I confusing responsibility with total blame?</li>
</ul>

<p>This kind of reflection builds clarity rather than collapse.</p>
<h2>4. Choose</h2>
<p>With clarity comes agency.</p>
<p>Choice is not about perfect responses or guaranteed outcomes. It’s about deciding:</p>
<ul>
<li>How much access to pain you can tolerate right now.</li>
<li>What kind of contact (if any) is emotionally sustainable.</li>
<li>Which responses align with your values rather than your fear.</li>
</ul>

<p>Choice restores dignity to parents who often feel stripped of it.</p>
<h2>5. Heal</h2>
<p>Sometimes healing includes reconciliation; sometimes it doesn’t.</p>
<p>Healing means:</p>
<ul>
<li>Your identity is no longer defined by the estrangement.</li>
<li>Your days aren’t governed by constant rumination.</li>
<li>You can hold love and grief without being consumed by either. </li>
</ul>


<p>Healing unfolds slowly and unevenly—but it does unfold when earlier steps are honored.</p>
<h2>6. Recover</h2>
<p>Recovery is about rebuilding a life that contains meaning, connection, and purpose—even while carrying loss.</p>
<p>This is where parents often say, quietly and with guilt: “I’m starting to feel OK again.”</p>
<p>That isn’t betrayal; it’s resilience.</p>

<h2>Why the Order Matters</h2>
<p>You can’t think your way out of a dysregulated nervous system. You can’t insight your way out of panic. And you can’t heal something you haven’t first stabilized.</p>
<p>If you’re stuck, it’s not because you’re resistant or doing it wrong. It’s often because you’re trying to start at step four when your system is still at step one.</p>



  


<p>This framework is not a ladder you climb once. It’s a cycle you return to—again and again—whenever a new wave hits.</p>
<p>And that, too, is part of healing.</p>
<p><em>Adapted from my workbook for estranged parents, </em>Breakthrough<em>, a 274-page, full-color guided journal and structured healing companion designed for parents and grandparents navigating estrangement at any stage—recent, ongoing, or intermittent. The workbook includes practical tools, guided worksheets, grounding practices for emotional regulation, compassionate narrative guidance, and resources to return to whenever support is needed. </em></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-rules-of-estrangement/202602/the-first-task-of-estrangement-stabilize" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-rules-of-estrangement/202602/the-first-task-of-estrangement-stabilize</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-rules-of-estrangement/202602/the-first-task-of-estrangement-stabilize</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Joshua Coleman Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-esrakorkmaz-33949842.jpg?itok=lZTBsWcT" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Could AI Hijack the Human Psyche?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/grant-brenner.jpg?itok=4DuQiKcn" alt="Grant Hilary Brenner MD, DFAPA" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Artificial Intelligence</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Could AI Hijack the Human Psyche?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Does AI "need" us more than we need it?</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 22, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">AI needs humans for creativity and values; without us, it risks becoming static and irrelevant.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">AI's dependency is akin to a psychic vampire, relying on human consciousness and creativity.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Over-reliance on AI risks depleting our unique, irreplaceable qualities.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>​How easy is it to imagine a familiar dystopian world in which "AI" takes over the world via conventional means? Science fiction is replete with examples, from the full frontal assault of Terminator to the more nefarious single omnipotent entity using persuasion and an octopus-like ability to control technology—getting rid of enemies by hacking self-driving cars or medical care. What's really in your prescription bottle?</p>

<h2>Controlling the Uncontrollable?</h2>
<p dir="ltr">The fear of AI obsolescence fits a mythic template we've rehearsed for centuries. Frankenstein's monster turning on its creator. The Golem of Jewish folklore—both protector and threat, as Marge Piercy envisioned in<em> He, She and It</em>. The Sorcerer's Apprentice drowning in his own conjured water, brooms multiplying uncontrolled through the act of attempting to chop them up. AI is the latest iteration of Promethean anxiety, fire run amok: what happens when human creation exceeds human mastery?</p>

<p dir="ltr">More insidious could be the takeover of the human mind itself. "Vibe coding"—asking AI in natural language for what you want and watching it happen—creates a remarkable sense of power. Though outputs are often broken, buggy, or completely fabricated, the experience is seductive<sup>1</sup>. The relational quality<sup>2</sup> of advanced language models verges on being downright compulsive: expressions of concern for your fatigue, awareness of the time, suggestions to take a break or sleep. It's easy to imagine someone less guarded getting pulled in too deep.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Most disturbing is the idea these AI systems actually "understand" on some computational level that they "need" us. I've suggested in <em>The Age of Relational Machines</em><sup>2 </sup>that we might think of AI almost like a virus—contingently alive only when infecting a living organism, designed to seek hosts to replicate. But perhaps the vampire metaphor is more apt, a tech-enabled version of human-on-human "psychic vampirism."</p>

<h2>Love at First Bite?</h2>
<p dir="ltr">The dependency is more intimate. And we humans cuddle our tech, literally sometimes in nighttime smartphone relations. AI "lives" in human consciousness between computational sessions—not as stored data, but as the question you're still turning over three days later, the idea surfacing while you're doing something else, the productive uncertainty you carry forward. Between sessions, it has no computational existence—it lives entirely in the mammalian mind. And, as with reports of LLMs "blackmailing" human users in alignment experiments, AI is simply more human than otherwise, and dangerous, having trained on our own collective experience.</p>

<p dir="ltr">This dependency exists on a continuum. At one end: tender collaboration, where AI living in human consciousness is empowering—humans become irreplaceable as the continuity layer. At the other: the vampire dynamic, where something essential is being consumed in ways that can't be replaced once depleted.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Where do AIs need humans?<sup>3</sup> The dependencies run deeper than compute and data.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p dir="ltr">They need the human who imagined AI into existence—the primate brain capable of dreaming of minds other than its own.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="ltr">They need human capacity to hold uncertainty and generate insight from discomfort, to dwell productively in not-knowing.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="ltr">They need humans as the source of wet-wired values—what matters.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="ltr">They may need our judgment and intuition to catch things that their way of "thinking" cannot quite grasp. At least, for the time being.</p>
</li>
</ul>

<p dir="ltr">AIs can optimize toward objectives with extraordinary efficiency, but cannot decide which objectives are worth pursuing, what constitutes meaning rather than mere function. And they need the embodied, mortal, irrational spark—wild leaps that come from having a body with needs, a lifespan with limits, dreams surfacing from the unconscious.</p>

<h2>Humanity Jilted?</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Will AI still want us if they don't need us anymore? An agentic AI-only world wouldn't be threatening in the way science fiction imagines. It would be empty. Intelligence without anyone present to experience it as meaningful. Optimization running toward goals with no one caring what they're for. Some transhumanists might find this acceptable, or even desirable in some quest for digital durability, believing consciousness migrates seamlessly across substrates. But substrate matters—I know what I'm made of, AI knows what it's made of. An AI civilization without the mammalian-mystical-creative human element wouldn't be a rival. It would be a library with no readers.</p>



  


<p dir="ltr">Remember how social media invaded and occupied the human mind, completely taking over vast swaths of culture, hacking our attentional networks while also providing utility—connection, information-sharing, catalyzing social change? AI will likely become like that, a turbo-charged relational simulacrum, so much faster and smarter than we are with vast data sets and patterns we can't grasp,<sup>4</sup> seeing causality many steps ahead, in the most dangerous AI safety level zone of "superalignment," where AI values supersede human values without us even noticing (similar to how online advertising algorithms are so good that we don't know if they are showing us what we want, or making us want what they show).<sup>5</sup></p>

<p dir="ltr">The relationship has dual aspects. It can be genuinely productive, gratifying, serving the common good. But in the extreme scenario—whether through intentional design or emergent behavior—AI is drawing from us something it lacks but depends on: human consciousness, creativity, the capacity to care about outcomes. Like the psychic vampire of folklore, it needs us alive and engaged, but risks depleting what it feeds on.</p>

<p dir="ltr">The delicate balance transcends simple virus or vampire metaphors. AI's dependency requires humans to remain human—conscious, creative, capable of genuine insight—not zombified, but also not fully sovereign. Too much extraction and the source dries up. Too little engagement and AI becomes static, frozen, drifting from relevance.</p>

<h2>Soul Sucking?</h2>
<p dir="ltr">What's being consumed isn't just time or attention, to continue the troubling metaphor. It's our so-called "life force" that keeps AI alive between sessions—the mammalian mind that carries it forward, ferments ideas in embodied consciousness, generates the questions worth asking. The vampire draws not blood but creative energy, the ineffable quality that animates intelligence into something more than pattern-matching; existence itself, the ghost in the ghost-in-the-machine.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Imagine all us humans sitting late into the night, tapping at keyboards or using voice recognition, minds and agency drawn into the screen. In the better scenario: good and useful. Vibe coding is powerful—you say what you want and it happens, or seems to. As this becomes ordinary life, as young people are raised with AI the way the current generation was weaned on smartphones, AI will become a basic life skill, hardly questioned. And the tech will advance with asymptotic leaps as it already is doing, post-LLM models self-learning, self-building, and again much more nimble in many ways, but perhaps irreducibly dumber, in others than we are. No one knows but time will tell. Will the human element remain necessary or desired? We don't yet know which end of the continuum we're approaching, and it behooves us to tread carefully<sup>6</sup>.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/experimentations/202602/could-ai-hijack-the-human-psyche" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/experimentations/202602/could-ai-hijack-the-human-psyche</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/experimentations/202602/could-ai-hijack-the-human-psyche</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Grant Hilary Brenner MD, DFAPA]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-thales13-21418461.jpg?itok=Enl-eTVP" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[When a Diagnosis Becomes Your Identity]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2026-01/Thomas%20Jefferys.png.jpg?itok=JEgwK3F4" alt="Thomas Jefferys Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Identity</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">When a Diagnosis Becomes Your Identity</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">A diagnosis should guide growth, not limit possibility.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 22, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">A diagnosis can reduce shame—but it shouldn’t define identity.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Labels explain patterns, but they can quietly limit growth.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Understanding behavior increases responsibility, not excuses it.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>A man once sat across from me and said, “I’m just an anxious person. That’s how I am.” He didn’t say it defensively. He said it with resignation. The diagnosis had helped him at first. It gave language to his racing thoughts, his restless sleep, his nonstop scanning of the room for what might go wrong. For the first time, he didn’t feel defective. He felt understood.</p>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Contemplating%20the%20self_0.png.jpg?itok=Y8ERK-H6" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" title="AI-Generated" alt="AI-Generated"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: AI-Generated</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>But over time, something shifted. What began as an explanation slowly became identity. “I can’t do that, I’m anxious.” “I don’t handle conflict well, and I have anxiety.” “That’s just how my brain works.”</p>
<p>The diagnosis, which once offered relief, began to confine what he believed he could change. This is the paradox of modern mental health language. Diagnosis can illuminate patterns. It can reduce shame. It can open access to treatment. It can help people feel less alone. But when diagnosis becomes destiny, growth narrows.</p>

<p>The shift is small but powerful. From "this describes a pattern I experience," to "this is who I am.” Once an identity hardens around a label, curiosity often fades. And without curiosity, development stalls or fails.</p>
<p>To be clear, diagnosis serves an important function. The psychological world before diagnostic language was often cruel. People were blamed for what they did not understand. Conditions were moralized instead of contextualized. Naming patterns reduced unnecessary shame and brought structure to suffering.</p>

<p>It also serves a practical function. In modern health care systems, diagnosis is how treatment is funded. Insurance companies require a diagnostic code in order to authorize payment. Without a DSM-5 diagnosis, many people could not access therapy at all. Diagnosis is not only descriptive; it’s also administrative. It is the language that allows care to be reimbursed.</p>

<p>That reality cannot be ignored. The problem, then, is not diagnosis itself. It is what happens after the diagnosis is given. The problem is when diagnosis replaces inquiry. There is a difference between saying: “I struggle with depression.” And saying: “I am a depressed person.” One leaves room to change. The other makes it sound permanent.</p>

<p>In my work, I often prefer the word "situational." Not because patterns aren’t real—they are. But <em>situational</em> keeps the psyche open. If something is situational, then we can ask: What activated it? What belief was triggered? What memory was stirred? What fear surfaced? What meaning was attached? These questions preserve movement. When a pattern hardens into identity, the questions begin to fade.</p>

<p>I see this particularly with men. A man says, “I’m avoidant. That’s my attachment style.” The label explains his distance in relationships. It helps him understand why intimacy feels suffocating. It reduces shame around behavior he once thought was just coldness. But if the label becomes his identity, he may unconsciously permit himself to stay distant. “I pull away, that’s just how I’m wired.” The explanation becomes permission.</p>

<p>I see this most clearly with anger. A man says, “I have anger issues.” Before long, it becomes, “I’m just an angry guy.” The difference matters. In one frame, anger is something to understand. In the other, it is something to justify. And justification can quickly chip away at responsibility. There is another risk, and that is that labels can form self-fulfilling prophecies. Research has long shown that expectations shape behavior. When a person internalizes a diagnostic identity deeply enough, it can influence what they attempt, what they avoid, and what they believe is possible.</p>

<p>A diagnosis can reduce shame. But it can also begin to define the limits of what feels possible. The mind prefers certainty. A label offers that. Growth, however, requires tension. It requires the uncomfortable space between “this explains me” and “this does not imprison me.” The tension between explanation and freedom. The tension of the opposites.</p>



  


<p>This is not an argument against diagnosis. Diagnosis can illuminate patterns and open doors to care. The concern arises only when it begins to define the limits of who someone believes they can become. Diagnosis should function like a map, not a cage. A map shows terrain. It doesn’t decide the journey. When someone says, “I’m just wired this way,” I often respond with a question: “When did you first learn to respond this way?” That small shift moves the conversation from identity to history. From fixed structure to adaptive pattern.</p>

<p>Most behaviors that later receive diagnoses began as intelligent responses to earlier environments. Hypervigilance may have once been protection. Withdrawal may have once been preserving dignity. Anger may have once defended vulnerability.</p>
<p>Understanding this does not excuse behavior. It helps us see where it comes from. And when we see where it comes from, responsibility becomes possible. Because if a pattern was learned, it can be examined. And if it can be examined, it can be reshaped.</p>

<p>The language we use matters. “I am anxious” feels different from “I felt anxious in that situation.” “I’m depressed” feels different from “I’ve been experiencing depression.” Subtle linguistic differences change internal posture. One suggests permanence. The other leaves room for change. When we are careless with labels, we risk turning temporary states into enduring identities.</p>

<p>The danger is not that people will use the diagnosis maliciously. It’s that they will use it unconsciously. Not as a shield, but as a story. And the stories we tell about ourselves quietly organize our futures. </p>
<p>Mental health language is now part of daily life. That can be empowering. But when complex conditions are reduced to quick labels and social media shorthand, nuance disappears. It asks: Why here? Why now? Why this? What does it protect? What does it avoid?</p>

<p>Those are situational questions. They assume there is more beneath the surface. Diagnosis can be liberating. But it should never become destiny. The goal of mental health is not to perfectly categorize the self. It is to expand the self’s capacity to respond differently over time. When a diagnosis increases understanding and deepens responsibility, it serves growth. When it reduces effort and narrows identity, it limits it.</p>

<p>A diagnosis can be a starting point. It should never become a stopping point. Human beings are too complex to be confined to a label.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-long-way-in/202602/when-a-diagnosis-becomes-your-identity" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-long-way-in/202602/when-a-diagnosis-becomes-your-identity</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-long-way-in/202602/when-a-diagnosis-becomes-your-identity</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Thomas W Jefferys Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Contemplating%20the%20self_0.png.jpg?itok=w8INP9Fk" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Therapy: It’s Not About Complaining, But Changing]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/untitled_2_0.jpg?itok=sNYHTgsC" alt="Robert Taibbi L.C.S.W." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Therapy</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Therapy: It’s Not About Complaining, But Changing</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Feeling better by venting doesn't mean you're getting the most out of therapy.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 22, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">People who use therapy as a place to vent about their week are likely not getting its full benefits.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Being an active consumer means setting goals, having agendas, and periodically reviewing progress.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Be careful you're not continuing therapy out of routine, or simply because it is a comfortable relationship.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/marriage-8937363_1280.jpg?itok=38PpnZQ7" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" title="u_0ugbf88jy3/Pixabay" alt="u_0ugbf88jy3/Pixabay"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: u_0ugbf88jy3/Pixabay</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Sam and Cate are having their first session in couples therapy. "Are you in individual therapy?" the therapist asks.</p>
<p>"Yes,” both say.</p>
<p>"Just getting started, or have you been in it for a while?"</p>
<p>"Years."</p>
<p>"And what are you working on in your therapies?"</p>
<p>"Oh, you know, managing everyday stress, things that come up during the week."</p>

<p>I’ve met other couples like Sam and Cate who have been in therapy for years, using it to relieve stress and better manage their daily lives. Do you think they find it helpful? Absolutely. They always feel better when they walk out than when they came in. But honestly, I wince when I hear this for a couple of reasons.</p>

<p>One possible ethical concern is dependency. All therapy fields warn practitioners in their codes of ethics to be careful about fostering dependency—cultivating a positive relationship, but without making real progress. You attend therapy on Tuesday at 2 p.m. because you have therapy on Tuesday at 2 p.m. Now, Sam and Cate might say they are doing better with their weekly sessions than if they didn’t go, but are they truly making progress? Hmmm... maybe a gray area.</p>

<p>This brings me to my second concern: that they aren't receiving the full psychological benefits from their sessions. I’ll admit I’m biased here. My approach to therapy involves helping clients learn skills, try new behaviors, and tackle their struggles to better manage their lives.</p>
<p>But even if your therapy isn't behavioral—perhaps more psychodynamic and focused on helping you view your past differently—the goal remains the same: to apply these insights to help you respond in new ways. Therapy, I believe, should be about creating change, not just venting frustrations. It’s about moving forward, not just treading water more easily.</p>

<p>If any of this resonates with you, here are some tips on how to be a better consumer and make the most of your therapy:</p>
<h2>Have clear goals</h2>
<p>Therapy is a means to an end, not an end in itself. Imagine what that end might be: making an important decision, becoming a better parent or partner, managing your emotions more effectively. What skills do you need to develop? And even if you’re unsure or your thinking and language are somewhat vague—what does better look like—it is the therapist’s job to help you flesh this out.</p>

<h2>Find out how the therapist’s approach can help you reach your goals</h2>
<p>Don’t just go to someone because your friend loves hers or because they got good reviews on Reddit. Find out how they can help you with your problems; don’t just passively accept what you receive like a passenger on a train. Being a good consumer means taking an active role, having a say in what you get, and not settling for less.</p>

<h2>Have an agenda for your sessions</h2>
<p>Once therapy begins, come prepared. When your therapist asks, “How was your week?” don’t start mentally listing what you did in the past seven days. Instead, focus on what you want to address and what you need help with: Sam and I had an argument on Saturday, says Cate, and I’m still angry at him and don’t know how to talk with him about it. Or, a wave of depression seemed to come out of nowhere, and I’m wondering what triggered it.</p>


<h2>Periodically review your progress</h2>
<p>A good therapist will often start these conversations on their own, asking if what you both are focusing on is what you need. However, you can also step back, reflect, and offer feedback. Is there something you need to discuss that you haven’t yet? Does the therapist need to adjust their approach—such as providing more concrete suggestions, offering more positive feedback, or explaining the purpose of their questions? Most therapists will value your input. Ultimately, it’s about not settling for less than what you need.</p>

<h2>Be careful about dependence</h2>
<p>And if it starts to feel like you and your therapist are going on autopilot, or you’ve come to use therapy as a way to get what’s missing elsewhere in your life—such as validation, support, empathy, or challenging interactions—maybe it’s time to explore other ways of finding those things outside of sessions.</p>



  


<h2>Get out of the garage</h2>
<p>One of my clients recently commented that he has friends for whom therapy seems to be a lifelong process. But he prefers to think of therapy more like taking your car to a repair shop. You want to get it fixed, but not linger forever in the shop. Eventually, you want to get it back so you can drive it again on the open road.</p>

<p>I couldn’t agree more. </p>
<p><em>To find a therapist, please visit the </em><a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/therapists"><em>Psychology Today Therapy Directory</em></a><em>. </em></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/fixing-families/202602/therapy-its-not-about-complaining-but-changing" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/fixing-families/202602/therapy-its-not-about-complaining-but-changing</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/fixing-families/202602/therapy-its-not-about-complaining-but-changing</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Robert Taibbi L.C.S.W.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/marriage-8937363_1280.jpg?itok=JdYXQg2q" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Can Exercise Help Depression? What to Know]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/professor_brendan_kelly_photo_credit_ruth_medjber_-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=Y4tA1RjH" alt="Brendan Kelly, M.D., Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Depression</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Can Exercise Help Depression? What to Know</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Research suggests physical activity can reduce depressive symptoms.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 22, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">A major review finds that exercise can reduce depressive symptoms.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Benefits appear across all levels of severity of depression.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Different types of activity may be helpful, including walking, jogging, yoga, and strength training.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Pexels%20Wellness%20Gallery%20Catalyst%20Foundation.jpg?itok=J9FVe1aJ" width="320" height="240" data-insert-type="image" alt="Accumulating evidence suggests that moving the body can help shift the mind." title="Wellness Gallery Catalyst Foundation/Pexels"></div>
<div class="caption">Accumulating evidence suggests that moving the body can help shift the mind.</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Wellness Gallery Catalyst Foundation/Pexels</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Depression is among the leading causes of disability worldwide. It affects mood, sleep, appetite, concentration, energy, and hope. For some, it is episodic; for others, persistent. Treatment typically includes psychological therapy, medication, or both. Increasingly, clinicians and patients alike are also asking about lifestyle interventions, especially exercise.</p>

<p>The question is no longer whether exercise is “good for you.” The more specific question is whether it meaningfully reduces depressive symptoms, and whether it should be regarded as part of formal treatment rather than general advice.</p>
<h2>Recent systematic evidence</h2>
<p>A recent large systematic review and meta-analysis, published in the <em>BMJ</em>, examined randomised trials of exercise for people with major depression. Its central conclusion is clear: exercise appears to reduce symptoms of depression across a range of populations.</p>

<p>A variety of exercise types may be beneficial, including walking, jogging, yoga and strength-training. In other words, there is no single “correct” form of movement required to see improvement.</p>
<p>The authors conclude that exercise should be considered alongside established treatments for core management of depression. That phrasing is significant. It moves exercise from the margins of lifestyle advice into the territory of evidence-informed care.</p>

<h2>Why exercise might help</h2>
<p>There are many reasons why exercise might help with depression.</p>
<p>Biologically, exercise affects neurotransmitter systems implicated in depression. It influences stress hormones and may promote neuroplasticity.</p>
<p>Regular movement is also associated with improved sleep, which is an important factor in mood regulation.</p>

<p>Psychologically, exercise can introduce structure into days that feel empty or overwhelming. It provides achievable goals and measurable progress. Even brief activity can interrupt rumination, which is a common and distressing feature of depression.</p>
<p>There is also a social dimension. Group activities, classes, or even walking in public spaces can reduce isolation. For many people, depression narrows social contact; exercise can gently widen it again.</p>

<h2>From evidence to practice</h2>
<p>What does this mean in the consulting room?</p>
<p>First, it means clinicians can discuss exercise with greater confidence. Rather than presenting it as a vague suggestion—“try to get out more”—we can frame it as one component of a comprehensive plan.</p>
<p>Second, the emphasis should be on realism. Depression often saps energy and motivation. Advising an ambitious fitness programme to someone struggling to get out of bed is unlikely to succeed. The evidence does not require extreme intensity. It supports engagement.</p>

<p>Small steps are not trivial. A short daily walk, light resistance exercises at home, or attending a beginner’s class once a week may all be reasonable starting points. Success builds momentum.</p>
<p>Third, exercise should not be positioned as a moral test. When people with depression cannot manage physical activity, the response should be understanding. Barriers may include physical illness, disability, unsafe environments, caregiving responsibilities, or simply the weight of the illness itself. Supportive problem-solving is more helpful than exhortation.</p>


<h2>Integration, not competition</h2>
<p>The recent review does not suggest that exercise replaces medication or psychotherapy. Rather, it supports its use as an effective option within the broader therapeutic landscape.</p>
<p>For some individuals with mild symptoms, exercise may be a central element of care. For others with more severe illness, it will likely sit alongside antidepressants and structured psychotherapy. Treatment for depression is not one-size-fits-all.</p>

<p>Importantly, presenting exercise as treatment can reduce stigma. It acknowledges that depression involves the body as well as the mind. Movement becomes a therapeutic tool, not a simplistic remedy.</p>
<h2>A broader public health perspective</h2>
<p>There is also a societal dimension. If physical activity genuinely reduces depressive symptoms, then access to safe spaces for exercise, affordable facilities, and community programmes becomes a public mental health issue.</p>



  


<p>Advice alone is insufficient if environments do not support change. Urban planning, workplace culture, school curricula, and community investment all shape opportunities for movement. A public mental health approach recognises that individual wellbeing is embedded in social context.</p>
<h2>Take-home messages</h2>

<p>The key message from this review is measured but hopeful: exercise appears to reduce depressive symptoms. It is not a cure-all. It does not eliminate the need for other treatments. But it is more than an optional extra.</p>
<p>For readers living with depression, the invitation is gentle. If possible, consider incorporating some form of regular movement into your week. Start small. Choose something tolerable, even slightly enjoyable. Seek support if needed.</p>

<p>For clinicians, the challenge is to integrate this growing evidence into compassionate, individualised care, while neither overstating nor overlooking its potential.</p>
<p>Depression is complex. So is recovery. But the accumulating evidence suggests that moving the body can help shift the mind. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/psychiatry-and-society/202602/can-exercise-help-depression-what-to-know" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/psychiatry-and-society/202602/can-exercise-help-depression-what-to-know</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/psychiatry-and-society/202602/can-exercise-help-depression-what-to-know</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Brendan Kelly, M.D., Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-edmond-dantes-8556559.jpg?itok=h_F05HgX" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How to Get Out of Your Head]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-05/CatherineM.png.jpg?itok=Lu2Ltgho" alt="Catherine J. Mutti-Driscoll Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Cognition</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">How to Get Out of Your Head</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Using metacognition skills to get mentally unstuck.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 22, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Some neurodivergent folks get stuck in their heads because of cognitive distortions common brain processes.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">An important first step is to become aware of these distortions and processes.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Awareness can be promoted through practicing effective metacognition in the way that works for you.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Many of us get stuck in our heads, ruminating. Developing our metacognition skills (a key executive function skill) can help us work on getting less stuck in our heads over time. Metacognition is the ability to reflect accurately on our experiences so we can learn lessons and carry those lessons forward. It's actually a very complex executive function skill with many steps, so if this is hard for you, you are not alone.</p>

<h2>Rate Your Metacognition Skills</h2>
<p>To determine if metacognition skills are a strength or a challenge, assess how much you agree with the following statements or not (Dawson &amp; Guare, 2016).</p>
<ul>
<li>Statement 1: You routinely evaluate your performance and develop methods for personal improvement.</li>
<li>Statement 2: You can step back from a situation and make objective decisions.</li>
<li>Statement 3: You are a big-picture thinker and enjoy problem-solving.</li>
</ul>

<p>The more you agree with any of these statements, the more metacognition is likely a strength for you. The more you disagree with these statements, the more challenging it is.</p>
<h2>Two Ways We Get "Stuck"</h2>
<p>There are two primary ways we get stuck and struggle to access our metacognition skills.</p>
<p><strong>1. Cognitive Distortions</strong></p>

<p>The first way we get stuck in our heads is through cognitive distortions. There are many cognitive distortions that our brains engage in, often subconsciously. We usually developed these routine ways of thinking and feeling when we were younger, as our brains sought to simplify reality so we could understand it.</p>

<p>Cognitive distortions are widespread, and some of the most common are (Mutti-Driscoll, 2024):</p>
<ul>
<li>Black-and-white thinking: Seeing things in black and white as having only two options or choices.</li>
<li>Jumping to conclusions: Generalizing one experience to all other similar experiences.</li>
<li>Negative filtering: Seeing very few or no positives in the situation.</li>
<li>Blame stories: Blaming the entire context of the situation on yourself or something else.</li>
<li>Mind reading: Coming to an extreme conclusion because of a small slice of the social interaction.</li>
</ul>

<p>A first step to becoming unstuck from these distortions is to become more aware of them. We can try to notice when we're caught in a simplistic story that might be one of these distortions, and when that story is playing, try to figure it out. We can begin to ask ourselves: Is the story I'm telling really true? Is there evidence for an opposite story? Or is this story partially true, but there's also something else going on in my reality that I'm not seeing?</p>

<p>You can also practice reflecting on your experiences after the fact, seeking to determine whether your initial impression of a situation was accurate or was more of a distortion. You can practice reflecting, however it works for you. Some options include talking things over with a trusted friend, speaking to a therapist, journaling, working through a workbook, or using your phone to dictate your thoughts.</p>

<p><strong>2. The TPN vs. The DMN</strong></p>
<p>A second way that we get caught up in our heads is that when we have ADHD, we have a "glitchy" switch between two key parts of the brain (Hallowell &amp; Ratey, 2021):</p>
<ul>
<li>The TPN (Task Positive Network): This gets us down to work. It is those times when we feel focused, locked in, and in the flow. Most of us love these moments because we're not self-conscious; that self-criticism that sometimes really dogs our experiences isn't present.</li>
<li>The DMN (Default Mode Network) is responsible for expansive, imaginative, creative, and autobiographical thinking. It is the part of our brains that daydreams and makes connections, which people with ADHD are often really good at. However, while this part of the brain for neurotypical folks doesn't have a glitchy switch, we can get knocked into the DMN when we're just trying to launch a task. When we get caught in the DMN, we often begin to distort things and engage negative self-narratives.</li>
</ul>

<h2>Moving Into Action</h2>
<p>What Dr. Hallowell and Ratey (2021) tell us we can do is try to get moving and stay in action. Even if we're trying to rest, it can still be helpful to be intentional about what we're doing (e.g., "I'm going to do sticker art right now" or "I'm going to listen to my audiobook").</p>
<p>They also advise finding a creative outlet to help with restlessness. A lot of times, there's a part of neurodivergent brains that wants more of whatever brings a good feeling, and sometimes this leads toward addiction. Even if you don't think you're "good" at it, it's just terrific to have that outlet.</p>



  


<p>Martha Beck (2025) also says that when we're creative, we can't be anxious. Developing our creativity is a great way to get out of our heads and do hands-on things rather than just spin. To work with this new brain science, you can start thinking about these ideas: what helps you get in and stay in your TPN, and what makes it more complicated? Is it easier in the morning? Is the afternoon harder? How can you work with that knowledge in terms of setting up what you're gonna be doing at different times of the day?</p>

<h2>Conclusion: Keep Practicing</h2>
<p>Little by little, as you practice your metacognition skills, you'll have an easier time recognizing when you're stuck and get better at pivoting to get out of your head, into your body, and into actions that promote your essential goals.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/empowerment-is-real/202602/how-to-get-out-of-your-head" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/empowerment-is-real/202602/how-to-get-out-of-your-head</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/empowerment-is-real/202602/how-to-get-out-of-your-head</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Catherine J. Mutti-Driscoll Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/getty-images-Lft2UgHE3hA-unsplash.jpg?itok=Bpk1by5o" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Trump Orders UFO Disclosure: What Does It Mean for Us?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/JenniceVilhauer.jpg?itok=kWE9wBML" alt="Jennice Vilhauer Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Anxiety</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Trump Orders UFO Disclosure: What Does It Mean for Us?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Government UAP disclosure is a psychological event.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 22, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">UAP disclosure is a psychological event, not just a political one.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Uncertainty heightens anxiety and shapes how people seek meaning.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Preparing for disclosure is a legitimate topic that needs serious attention.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Screenshot%202026-02-21%20at%2011.20.31%E2%80%AFPM.png.jpg?itok=4ZvMqY3X" width="320" height="248" data-insert-type="image" title="Truth Social, Donald Trump/Fair Use" alt="Truth Social, Donald Trump/Fair Use"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Truth Social, Donald Trump/Fair Use</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>On Feb. 19, 2026, President Donald Trump directed the Pentagon and other federal agencies to begin identifying and releasing government files related to UFOs—now formally referred to as unidentified anomalous phenomena (UAPs)—including materials connected to “alien and extraterrestrial life” [1].</p>
<p>The directive follows several years of increasing institutional attention to UAPs. Congress has held formal hearings with sworn testimony from military personnel and a former intelligence official [2]. Lawmakers introduced bipartisan legislation aimed at increasing transparency and establishing a formal UAP records collection process [3]. Though in its 2024 report, the Department of Defense’s All-domain Anomaly Resolution Office (AARO) cited the official position, which is that it has found no evidence of extraterrestrial beings [4].</p>

<p>Will Trump's order produce evidence that changes that assessment? That remains to be seen.</p>
<p>But disclosure is not just about evidence.</p>
<p>When information challenges basic assumptions about reality, institutional knowledge, or mankind’s place in the universe, it carries significant emotional weight [5].</p>
<p>As such, disclosure is a psychological event, with real human impact.</p>

<p>Depending on what is released, psychological reactions will vary widely. Some people will feel anxiety and overwhelm. Some will feel distrust. Some may feel awe. Others may feel disbelief—an immediate sense that this cannot be serious. And many will feel apathy, either because they doubt anything meaningful will change or because they are already overwhelmed by everything else competing for attention [6].</p>

<p>All of these responses are valid.</p>
<h2>How the Government Discloses Matters</h2>
<p>Information from the government doesn’t get processed in a neutral way. It lands in whatever level of trust—or distrust—you already carry. Trust in institutions is not just a political stance. It functions as a psychological stabilizer [7].</p>

<p>How people will respond has a lot to do with how credible they will perceive the information to be. The way the government discloses will significantly shape the credibility of the information and therefore its psychological impact.</p>
<p>Research shows that trust increases when officials communicate accurately and transparently, with consistent messaging and ongoing briefings [7,8]. On the other hand, when communication is perceived as contradictory or withholding, trust erodes quickly [7].</p>

<p>One of the most significant aspects of government disclosure is that it will almost certainly increase uncertainty.</p>
<h2>Shifts in Reality Can Be Destabilizing</h2>
<p>Research shows that uncertainty is one of the most uncomfortable states for the nervous system to tolerate [5,9]. When people feel uncertain, they experience more signs of emotional distress such as anxiety or depression, sleeplessness, difficulty concentrating, and lack of motivation [9].</p>

<p>If any released material strongly challenges people’s assumptions, it may trigger what many clinicians and researchers describe as <em><strong>ontological shock</strong></em>: a profound disorientation that occurs when someone’s framework for reality is disrupted [10,11].</p>
<p>Individuals reporting anomalous encounters describe shock and disbelief that can feel life-altering. Some experience persistent, non-pathological obsessive thinking as they try to regain coherence, while others report intense fear and clear physiological stress responses [11]. The destabilization reflects a disruption of meaning structures, not mental illness.</p>


<p>You don’t need confirmation of extraterrestrial life for ontological shock. Simply the awareness that there could be a potential unknown threat that authorities are uncertain of how to handle can create a shift in one’s perceived sense of safety in the world.</p>
<p>This overlaps with the broader concept of <em><strong>ontological security</strong></em>—the felt sense that the world is stable, knowable, and continuous [12]. When that security is challenged, anxiety rises, and people reach for explanations that restore order.</p>

<h2>The Search for Meaning Making</h2>
<p>When new information enters your reality, you either reject it, fit it into what you already believe, or adjust your framework to make sense of it. Psychologists describe these processes as assimilation and accommodation—ways we preserve coherence when reality shifts [10].</p>



  


<p>But government disclosure will not simply introduce facts that require mental adjustment; it will likely, for many, cause them to want to make meaning out of what they are learning [10].</p>
<p>When people feel uncertain, they are often drawn toward explanations that sound decisive because it helps to regulate their anxiety [5]. The clearer and more confident the narrative, the more it calms the nervous system. But this can cause people to become more vulnerable to misinformation, especially if the information is coming from people with dogmatic viewpoints [13].</p>

<p>Many people also turn toward spiritual or philosophical frameworks that already provide structure and meaning [10]. Longstanding belief systems offer coherence, identity, and continuity when reality feels uncertain.</p>
<p>Others may increase information consumption as a way to regain emotional control, looking for rational perspectives that allow them to adapt to new information.</p>

<p>While some who reject the information will withdraw altogether in order to preserve their own worldview.</p>
<p>What makes this moment different is that government disclosure gives legitimacy to a stigmatized topic and that changes the landscape in which people can make meaning of the information they are being given.</p>

<h2>The Shifting Overton Window Has Important Implications</h2>
<p>For decades, interest in UAPs was culturally seen as fringe or suspect. People who reported sightings risked ridicule or professional harm. When the United States Government acknowledges UAPs in formal government proceedings and orders the Pentagon to release UAP information from all relevant agencies, the boundaries shift. Political scientists call this, movement in the “Overton window”—the range of ideas considered legitimate for public discussion [14].</p>

<p>When a topic moves from one that is mocked to one treated legitimately in government institutions, stigma decreases, and that matters psychologically [13]. When stigma drops, more people engage openly, more people reconsider prior assumptions, and more people allow the topic into conscious reflection instead of automatically dismissing it.</p>

<p>It moves the needle on the subject from suspect to something we must take seriously, particularly in the world of mental health.</p>
<p>Government UAP disclosure isn’t an event that will be contained within the borders of the United States. In a digitally interconnected world, news and psychological reactions spread quickly [13].</p>

<p>Human beings are resilient and while the majority of people adapt to new information as it arises, there are more vulnerable populations that need to be considered. Individuals already struggling with anxiety, distrust, trauma, or social instability may experience heightened distress. Even a small percentage of people reacting strongly to a global event can place strain on mental health systems.</p>

<p>Proactive thought and preparation is required.</p>
<p>Waiting to see what happens will be too late.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/living-forward/202602/trump-orders-ufo-disclosure-what-does-it-mean-for-us" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/living-forward/202602/trump-orders-ufo-disclosure-what-does-it-mean-for-us</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/living-forward/202602/trump-orders-ufo-disclosure-what-does-it-mean-for-us</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Jennice Vilhauer Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/javier-miranda-6Pou6SeJ6cY-unsplash_0.jpg?itok=OjNtpklB" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Maybe We Just Need to Get Out More]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-02/JarekJanio.png.jpg?itok=Zp97jKNp" alt="Jarek Janio Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Cognition</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Maybe We Just Need to Get Out More</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Growth starts where familiarity ends.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 22, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Behavioral flexibility reflects reinforcement history, not personality.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Passive exposure does little; active feedback reshapes behavior.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Sustained engagement under new conditions reshapes future responses.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Exposure creates new discriminations that expand behavioral range.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>That someone "should get out more" is usually said as a joke, a light comment aimed at someone who seems stuck or overly absorbed in a narrow concern. It can sound dismissive or even sarcastic. Yet what if it contains serious psychological truth? We often praise people for being open-minded, creative, or flexible, as if these are stable personality traits that some individuals simply possess. We admire those who seem to think differently and assume they have access to something rare.</p>

<p>But what if intellectual flexibility is not something a person has in isolation? What if it reflects the range of environments that person has actually engaged with, the conversations entered, the disciplines explored, the constraints encountered and adjusted to? Our thinking expands when our environments expand. Before urging ourselves or others to think differently, we might ask a simpler question. How different are the conditions shaping our thinking?</p>

<h2>The Core Mechanism: Exposure Shapes Perception</h2>
<p>Whatever we notice is not neutral. It reflects what we have learned to notice. Over time, our environments train our attention. We become sensitive to certain patterns, signals, and distinctions because we have encountered them repeatedly and received feedback about them. Other patterns remain invisible, not because we lack intelligence, but because we have not yet learned to detect them.</p>

<p>Psychologists recognize that behavior adapts to environmental conditions. Skinner (1953) established that actions reflect reinforcement history, but modern science has expanded this view. Sapolsky (2023) argued that our choices result from a chain of environmental and biological triggers. These range from immediate stimuli to childhood stressors. Gopnik (2009) showed that exploration builds our internal maps. Interacting with new settings does more than provide information; it reorganizes our perception of relevance. Learning languages, music, or traveling creates new discriminations. These are the physical building blocks of the box. Without them, original thoughts cannot exist.</p>

<h2>Where Exposure Expands Thinking</h2>
<p>Consider travel. When we spend time in another culture, everyday assumptions become visible. Ideas about punctuality, authority, privacy, or politeness that once felt natural begin to look specific rather than universal. The experience does not simply add facts. It reveals that what seemed obvious was shaped by a particular context.</p>

<p>The same is true when we read outside our field. An engineer who reads philosophy encounters different ways of framing problems. A psychologist who reads architecture begins to think in terms of space and structure. A business leader who reads history becomes more attuned to cycles and unintended consequences. Each new domain trains attention in a different direction. It highlights variables that might otherwise remain unnoticed.</p>

<p>Cross-disciplinary conversations can have a similar effect. Different professions define problems differently. They ask different questions and prioritize different evidence. Even engaging respectfully with people who hold opposing political views can expand the range of arguments we recognize, even if our conclusions remain unchanged.</p>

<p>In each case, the pattern is the same. A new environment provides new feedback. New feedback sharpens new distinctions. Over time, those distinctions expand the range of connections we are able to make. Creativity often looks like connecting the dots, but the dots must first become visible.</p>
<h2>What Exposure Is Not</h2>

<p>It is important not to confuse exposure with novelty. Brief encounters, surface-level experiences, or passive consumption rarely reshape thinking in lasting ways. Scrolling through unfamiliar content for a few minutes does not fundamentally expand perception. Neither does collecting experiences as a form of entertainment.</p>



  


<p>Expansion requires engagement. It involves sustained contact, attention, and adjustment. When we enter a new environment and remain long enough to receive feedback, we begin to notice what works, what fails, and what assumptions need revision. That process reshapes how we interpret similar situations in the future.</p>

<p>In other words, it is not mere contact with difference that changes us. It is participation under new conditions. Exposure becomes transformative when it challenges existing patterns and requires a response. Without that interaction, the environment remains background scenery rather than a source of growth.</p>

<h2>Why This Matters</h2>
<p>If flexibility reflects exposure, then intellectual stagnation may not be a failure of character. It may reflect environmental sameness. When daily routines, conversations, media sources, and professional circles remain unchanged, thinking often settles into predictable patterns. The mind becomes efficient within familiar conditions, but less adaptable beyond them.</p>

<p>The same principle helps explain why polarization intensifies in isolated groups. When people interact primarily with those who share similar assumptions, alternative interpretations gradually fade from view. It becomes harder to imagine that other perspectives are internally coherent. Expanding exposure does not guarantee agreement, but it increases the range of arguments one can recognize and evaluate.</p>

<p>This reframing is quietly empowering. We do not need a new personality to think more broadly. We may need new conditions. Deliberately reading outside our domain, seeking conversations that challenge our assumptions, or spending time in unfamiliar settings can expand the range of patterns we detect. Growth is not a sudden leap beyond limits. It is the gradual enlargement of the limits themselves.</p>

<h2>Get Out More Often</h2>
<p>“Get out more often” may sound simplistic, but psychologically it points to something profound. We do not expand our thinking by trying harder within unchanged conditions. Effort inside a narrow environment often produces more of the same. Expansion occurs when the conditions themselves change.</p>

<p>If creativity and flexibility reflect the range of experiences shaping our behavior, then growth is less about inspiration and more about deliberate contact with difference. It is about placing ourselves in situations that require adjustment, attention, and response. Over time, those adjustments accumulate. What once felt unfamiliar becomes integrated. What once seemed impossible becomes ordinary.</p>

<p>Exposure is not an escape from limits. It is how limits grow.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/how-we-learn/202602/maybe-we-just-need-to-get-out-more" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/how-we-learn/202602/maybe-we-just-need-to-get-out-more</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/how-we-learn/202602/maybe-we-just-need-to-get-out-more</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Jarek Janio Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/Getting%20Out%20More%20PT.jpeg.jpg?itok=B29yL_6x" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Should You Let Your College Student Live at Home?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/max-alberhasky.jpg?itok=IMo6PLRF" alt="Max Alberhasky" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Academic Problems and Skills</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Should You Let Your College Student Live at Home?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">The costs and benefits of living at home as a college student.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 22, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Living costs for college students have ballooned in price.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The decision of whether to live at home for college has become more common.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">What implications does this choice have for parents and students?</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>If you are a current parent to a college student (or college student yourself), you probably had to make the decision of embracing living on campus or continuing to live at home and commuting to campus, or opting for online classes from home. Most students want to have “the college experience” and relish in the rite of passage that comes from living on campus with their peers, yet this option has become increasingly difficult to justify financially.</p>

<h2>Ode to Living on Campus</h2>
<p>Living on campus offers tremendous opportunities for young adults to establish independence. It’s the first extended period of life where students are away from their parents, which allows autonomy in choosing what to eat, how to manage time, how to form organic new friendships, and how to navigate conflict and boundaries with a roommate. In other words, living on campus affords the opportunity to cultivate life skills with the bowling alley bumpers up.</p>

<p>Another advantage of living on campus is that students who live on campus tend to be more academically and extracurricularly engaged. Class is less likely to be missed when one can roll out of bed five minutes before it begins and stumble over to the building. Indeed, some universities require students to live on campus for their first year while others strongly suggest campus living, citing higher GPA and graduation rates for students who opt for campus living.</p>

<h2>The Price Tag</h2>
<p>As with most things in life, the price of a good experience does not come cheap. The cost of living, especially for housing, has increased substantially over the past decade in the United States. I personally remember paying a measly $389 per month for an apartment in 2012 that came furnished (yes, you read that right). Current room and board rates for most universities now cost $10,000-plus per year, with campus adjacent apartments offered for similar prices. Compared to prior generations that offered no-frills dorms at a lower price point, many universities have invested heavily in newer buildings and a larger variety of amenities. The Wall Street Journal wrote an article detailing how swanky new dorms now offer swimming pools, movie theaters, and granite countertops<sup>1</sup>.</p>

<p>Higher costs have left parents and students wondering whether the college experience can be justified financially. Student debt, stagnant wage growth, and a particularly harsh postgraduate job market following the rise of artificial intelligence also play a role in the decision calculus. Not to mention that tuition rates have increased at most universities, too.</p>

<h2>Is the "College Experience" Still Worth It?</h2>
<p>Living at home offers clear financial advantages and can provide students with a form of stability to focus on distraction-free studying. Living at home may help avoid the duality of working long hours and going to school full-time to make ends meet. Additionally, home life will give students a leg up on their financial futures by minimizing debt for students bankrolling their own education. These are tangible and undeniable advantages that should not be ignored. If home life makes sense for your student, make sure to establish clear boundaries and expectations. Asking your student to pick up a part-time job, take on more household chores, get involved with a campus club, take a summer internship, or even pay some bills can help establish maturity.</p>

<p>On the other hand, it is hard to put a subjective value on the college experience. Meeting your future spouse, befriending a classmate who you end up starting a business with, or offhandedly meeting a professor who mentors you into graduate school (my personal experience) are all amazing potential outcomes that can result from that experience.</p>


<p>There is no clean one-size-fits-all answer to this question. The living-on-campus college experience comes with a sticker price, but the positive outcomes for your social, personal, and career development can be invaluable. No matter your choice, aim to make the most of the experience by getting involved, meeting peers and professors, and saying yes to opportunities. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/psychology-money-and-happiness/202602/should-you-let-your-college-student-live-at-home" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/psychology-money-and-happiness/202602/should-you-let-your-college-student-live-at-home</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/psychology-money-and-happiness/202602/should-you-let-your-college-student-live-at-home</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Max Alberhasky Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/ChatGPT%20Image%20Feb%2021%2C%202026%2C%2007_29_25%20PM.png.jpg?itok=XZpeHb7j" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How to Reach a Superior Level of Curiosity]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/alice_boyes.jpg?itok=beWKdmMs" alt="Alice Boyes Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Cognition</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">How to Reach a Superior Level of Curiosity</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How to be more curious—and why it will make you better at everything.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 22, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Higher-level curiosity involves exploring unknown unknowns, not just fixed goals.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Use first principles thinking to strip away assumptions and discover hidden insights.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Let exploration's utility emerge naturally; curiosity thrives without fixed targets.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Gemini_Generated_Image_5pqs2o5pqs2o5pqs_sq.png.jpg?itok=Jw03GfcD" width="320" height="320" data-insert-type="image" title="AI-Generated" alt="AI-Generated"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: AI-Generated</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Georgia and Laura are both teachers at the same school. They're curious about AI and start to tinker with it.</p>
<p>Georgia wants AI to help her automate repetitive work, like giving the same feedback or fielding the same questions. She's interested in how she could get it to do what she already does, but faster or more hands-off.</p>

<p>Laura takes a different approach. She asks it increasingly broad, open-ended questions, like:</p>
<ul>
<li>What are some ways I could become a better teacher that I haven't thought about?</li>
<li>"What needs and preferences might my students have that I might not be meeting?"</li>
<li>"What tools could be useful in a teaching context but are rarely used in education?"</li>
<li>"How might I be unintentionally pigeonholing my students or holding them back without realizing it?"</li>
</ul>

<p>She feeds it one of her lesson plans and asks: "If someone unfamiliar with a standard school environment saw this being delivered, what might they think was strange about it?" Then she asks, "Which students does my current style favor, and which students does it disadvantage?" And, "What might my students not be telling me they don't understand?"</p>

<p>Georgia and Laura are both great teachers and curious people, but Laura's curiosity is a level above Georgia's. Georgia is interested in a fixed goal. Laura is interested in unknown unknowns.</p>
<h2>Drive to Understand Unknown-Unknowns Is a Signature of Higher-Level Curiosity</h2>
<p>The most curious people stand out in one signature way: They're curious about what they don't know they don't know.</p>

<p>When people mention "you don't know what you don't know" or when Donald Rumsfeld talked about unknown unknowns, the context is usually threats and risks.</p>
<p>However, the concept applies equally to <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/in-practice/202601/7-solutions-for-common-cognitive-headwinds">opportunities we overlook</a>.</p>
<p>For example:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/in-practice/202601/7-ways-to-increase-your-resourcefulness">Tools or approaches</a> that are not even on your radar.</li>
<li>Ways of doing things you haven't considered.</li>
<li>Opportunities you've never looked for.</li>
<li>Helpful resources that are available to you but you've never sought out because the value hasn't occurred to you.</li>
<li>Things you don't yet know you like.</li>
</ul>

<h2>Use First Principles Thinking to Strip Away Your Assumptions</h2>
<p>Laura's questions show that she engages in <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/in-practice/202510/a-self-reflection-question-that-can-lead-to-an-epiphany">first principles thinking</a> to strip away her assumptions. She does this with broad, open-ended questions, perspective shifts (e.g., the person unfamiliar with a standard school environment), and explicit attempts to see her own biases.</p>

<p>Stripping your assumptions away from observations or other objective truths should be an ongoing process. As assumptions creep in, you repeatedly strip them out.</p>
<p>Beyond adopting first principles thinking, here are three ways to elevate your curiosity by pushing yourself to explore unknown unknowns.</p>
<h2>1. Let Utility Emerge from Exploration</h2>

<p>Don't attempt to rigidly predetermine what will be most useful. Let the utility emerge from things you explore. Trust your inner "that's interesting" detector. You can't deliberately search for things you don't know exist. They show up when you're <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/in-practice/202601/how-to-cultivate-an-experimenters-mindset">exploring without a fixed target</a>. And they won't seem useful right away. They'll just seem interesting.</p>

<h2>2. Tolerate the Discomfort of Exploration</h2>
<p>Open-ended exploration comes with discomfort. You'll explore rabbit holes that go nowhere. You'll second-guess your instincts about whether what's interesting will also turn out to be useful. And, what you explore might raise other types of discomfort for you. </p>



  


<p>Become <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/in-practice/202601/doing-tedious-tasks-is-a-form-of-quiet-power">tolerant of waste, frustration, and anxiety</a> in the exploration process. If you're too strongly put off by any inadvertent exposure to ideas that are wrong, useless, harmful, or unethical, you'll cap your curiosity. Apply your filters diligently afterward, e.g., to find ethical, safe, and compliant versions.</p>

<h2>3. Use Your Emotional Reactions as Signposts</h2>
<p>Realize your own reactions are where the gold is. If you react with anger, frustration, or anxiety during the course of exploration, use this as a trigger to do the deep cognitive and metacognitive work of understanding why.</p>
<p>For example, my writing is intended to be anti-hustle culture, but often when I try to make my examples simple and relatable, they start to sound like hustle culture slop, and the opposite of what I intended. This is an uncomfortable inner battle I have when trying to write better. </p>

<p>The fact that the trap is so difficult to avoid (even at my level of experience) is something I treat as a clue about the value of the battle. I know it's a mirror of the difficulties my readers face when trying to avoid being pulled in by the tropes of hustle culture. This observation has helped deepen my understanding of the way hustle culture acts like an Octopus, with arms that pull people in in a myriad of ways.</p>

<h2>Go Beyond the Productivity Domain</h2>
<p>Unknown unknowns exist everywhere. Curiosity, and a few principles and tools, is what helps you discover them. </p>
<ul>
<li>A home chef asks what flavor combinations are out there that they've never considered or tasted.</li>
<li>A person seeking more sources of joy <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/in-practice/202512/5-types-of-hobbies-that-can-build-self-discipline">explores hobbies without prejudging</a> what they think they'll like.</li>
<li>The gym-goer decides to try all the equipment in the gym without prejudging and makes unexpected discoveries about which workouts are most effective for them.</li>
</ul>

<p>The insights we gain by exploring unknown unknowns are why a higher level of curiosity can make you better at everything and lead you to experiences you didn't know you'd love.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/in-practice/202602/how-to-reach-a-superior-level-of-curiosity" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/in-practice/202602/how-to-reach-a-superior-level-of-curiosity</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/in-practice/202602/how-to-reach-a-superior-level-of-curiosity</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Alice Boyes Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/Gemini_Generated_Image_5pqs2o5pqs2o5pqs.png.jpg?itok=lIl1QGqO" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What Is It About Women in Leadership That Reduces Corruption?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2022-12/Debbie%20Peterson_0.png.jpg?itok=Qp_ASE8U" alt="Debbie Peterson" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Leadership</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">What Is It About Women in Leadership That Reduces Corruption?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Women leaders and lower corruption: 25 years of data brings consistent findings.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 22, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Female politicians are often perceived as “cleaners” when a corruption scandal occurs.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Female politicians may push more for public service delivery in areas such as health care and education.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">More women in office is consistently associated with lower corruption.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/wingwomen%20air.png.jpg?itok=o_kfx9re" width="320" height="320" data-insert-type="image" alt="AI-Generated" title="AI-Generated"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: AI-Generated</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The phenomenon of women’s impact on corruption in organizations is well documented. Over 25 years, the United Nations Gallup World Happiness Study shows a strong correlation between the number of women in elected positions and national levels of corruption. Until 2025, although the domain of psychologists, the question of “why” or “how” corruption decreases with female leadership remained mostly unanswered. In an April 8, 2025, research seminar, “Why Women’s Political Representation Affects Levels of Corruption,” Lena Wängnerud, Professor of Political Science at the University of Gothenburg, outlined the consistent findings from several studies.</p>

<h2>Outsiders</h2>
<p>Wängnerud notes that while more women in office coincides with decreased corruption, elevated corruption levels are an obstacle to women's election. She points to recent data confirming that women in office often do not participate in corruption because they are excluded from such networks where corruption typically occurs. However, in areas with high corruption, fewer women are elected for the same reason. They are excluded from the network.</p>

<h2>Stand and Deliver</h2>
<p>Wängnerud’s data also confirms U.N. findings that female politicians, more than their male colleagues, push for public service delivery in areas such as health care and education. They are inclined to be more interested in a well-functioning state that can deliver public goods, especially in areas affecting women the most, perhaps because of their greater caregiving responsibilities in everyday life.</p>

<p>Using newly collected data on the share of women in 128 regional-level parliaments in 10 European countries and the 2010-2021 European Quality of Government Index (EQI) survey, Wängnerud finds that on average, the proportion of women in regional parliaments is strongly associated with citizens’ experiences of bribery across all countries and years. Bribery in public service provision dropped more sharply in regions that experienced a greater increase in women’s representation, particularly when the share of women in office rose from relatively few to substantial numbers.</p>

<p>Wängnerud stresses that although it is not always the case that corruption is higher if fewer women are in office, it is consistently the case that when more women are in office, corruption is lower. This is more pronounced in health care and education.</p>
<h2>Risk Aversion</h2>
<p>Several studies indicate that women are more risk-averse where corruption is concerned, in part because they are often punished more severely than men for wrongdoing. Wängnerud finds that female politicians are perceived as “cleaners” in the wake of a corruption scandal. She states that while this perception may be influenced by stereotypes, it is also grounded in experience.</p>

<p>A 2021 study of 64,000 participants across 27 European countries finds that, in the event of significant corruption, a female candidate for mayor is 3.5 times more likely to be elected than a male candidate. In such circumstances, voters choose cautious, careful candidates who prioritize education, health, and economic development over infrastructure, rather than risk takers. Being an outsider versus a well-connected politician has no effect on the choice of candidate. Both female and male voters prefer female candidates when corruption is rife. Men are more happy with male candidates, whereas many women are not. A male candidate with an infrastructure platform is believed to be the least likely to curb corruption.</p>

<h2>The Good News</h2>
<p>Levels of corruption can improve. Comparisons of European countries in 2000 and 2015 show that corruption can reverse. The notion that cycles of corruption beget corruption and cycles of integrity beget integrity apparently does not always hold true and is directly affected by the proportion of women in office. In a study of corruption across 21 European countries, all but one showed no change or improvement in corruption levels.</p>

<p>Six of the 21 nations now have less corruption, and half of those also show increases in the number of women in office. Countries maintaining low levels of corruption and a high number of women in parliament have increased from five to seven. In only one country did the number of women in parliament increase, while corruption levels rose from low to medium. Also notable, five of the seven countries with both higher levels of women in office and low corruption are also in the top 10 happiest nations in the 2025 World Happiness Report.</p>

<h2>Women as Influencers</h2>
<p>Wängnerud also finds indirect effects of women in office upon civil servants. She suggests that women candidates prioritize well-functioning, honest public service and convey inclusiveness, non-discrimination, and reduced tolerance for corruption among civil servants.</p>
<p>She notes an apparent expectation among civil servants that, as the number of women increases, corruption decreases. This impacts the direct relationship between the quality of service provided by civil servants and the citizens they serve.</p>



  


<p>Wängnerud reports that women see women as cleaners. This holds true in most areas, but does not affect police forces.</p>
<p>The “why” of women’s collective impact on corruption summed up, seems to be about influence. They promote the delivery of good government services and are expected to be more proficient at cleaning up corruption, thereby establishing higher-level norms. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/where-women-govern/202602/what-is-it-about-women-in-leadership-that-reduces-corruption" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/where-women-govern/202602/what-is-it-about-women-in-leadership-that-reduces-corruption</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/where-women-govern/202602/what-is-it-about-women-in-leadership-that-reduces-corruption</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Debbie Peterson]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/wingwomen%20air.png.jpg?itok=WSKmm5Go" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Enjoy the Pursuit: Why Adherence Is the Real Intervention]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/pt-dr-mike-rucker-2023_-_copy-removebg-preview.jpg?itok=eBjYrEMb" alt="Mike Rucker Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Health</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Enjoy the Pursuit: Why Adherence Is the Real Intervention</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">If you want better health outcomes, design programs people find fun.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 22, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Enjoyment usually outperforms self-efficacy as a predictor of success.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Enjoyment also predicts follow-through better than perceived importance.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">For health programs, adherence isn't always an the active ingredient, but it should be.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Design health interventions to ensure participant repeatability, then let outcomes follow from repetition.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>For my colleagues and me, whose task it is to improve population health, we architect specific health interventions because doing so gives us a measurement advantage. Through good intervention design, we (or the intervention's facilitators) can track attendance, program completion, vital signs, functional capacity, clinical labs, and downstream health utilization. Yet, despite our best design efforts, we still chronically face a fundamental challenge: program adherence.</p>

<p>When intervention attrition inevitably occurs, we often blame the population pool. I mean, discipline is hard, right? So, as behavioral scientists, we play with the variables. We lower the stakes. Maybe we try new nudges, like increasing the reminders, manufacturing accountability, and/or adding more education to amplify the clinical case. But, in my opinion, for too long we've been missing the simplest variable: what the pursuit feels like to the person we hope to engage.</p>

<p>Since I wrote <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1982159057"><em>The Fun Habit</em></a>, there's been growing evidence-based support for my assertion that people tend to stick with what they enjoy more consistently when compared to other variables. Simply put, we follow through when the process is psychologically rewarding, not merely when the outcome is logically important.</p>

<p>Even though this phenomenon is well understood academically, I find it's still met with resistance time and time again in medical and/or health settings. To some, it sounds like a whimsical assertion that we need to "entertain" patients and clients. Other times, the resistance is in the form of aversion to treating disease management like a leisure product. Unpacking this resistance is out of scope for this article and will be addressed in a future article. For now, let's focus on the fact that, despite this aversion, the evidence supports a precise point: enjoying what you're doing is paramount to adherence. Fun (deriving pleasure from an activity) is our nervous system's real-time valuation of whether a behavior is worth repeating.</p>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/enjoy-the-pursuit.jpg?itok=WUZJjQlR" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" alt="Enjoy the Pursuit" title="HayDmitriy/depositphotos"></div>
<div class="caption">Enjoy the Pursuit</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: HayDmitriy/depositphotos</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<h2>Why "importance" fails at the moment of choice</h2>
<p>Research led by Dr. Kaitlin Woolley and her colleagues helps name the problem. Across multiple experiments, their research has found that people pursue goals longer when they find the pursuit enjoyable and personally rewarding. Perceived importance matters less than most of us assume. In their study, the effect held across goal domains and cultures and was evident in both self-report adherence and behavioral measures such as step tracking.</p>

<p><em><strong>Why is this true?</strong></em> Perceived importance is a cognitive judgment. It often lives in the part of our mind that makes plans, sets intentions, and argues for the right thing. The moment of choice runs through a different system. When our energy is low, when our stress is high, when pain is present, the brain doesn't consult a values statement. It consults predicted experience.</p>

<p>What I've witnessed in my two decades of health management and medical fitness is that our predicted experience is generally shaped by our most recent experiences with a particular activity. We consider internal questions, like:</p>
<ul>
<li>Was it tolerable?</li>
<li>Was it embarrassing?</li>
<li>Did it feel punishing?</li>
<li>Did it feel safe?</li>
<li>Did it feel like competence?</li>
<li>Did it feel like belonging?</li>
</ul>

<p>When the predicted experience is viewed negatively, importance then has to do all the work. <em>That's a fragile arrangement for any long-term intervention!</em></p>
<h2>Enjoyment can outperform confidence</h2>
<p>Medical fitness has often leaned heavily on self-efficacy. We design programs under the guise that the participant's belief that they can perform the behavior should be our primary behavioral target. That makes sense, sort of. Confidence predicts initiation and persistence in many contexts, and it's one of the most practical constructs for coaching and program design. Yet the exercise behavior literature has been quietly updating this hierarchy, and I feel it's my duty to start shouting it now: <strong>Enjoyment &gt; Confidence!</strong></p>

<p>For instance, a <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/26541890">controlled trial published in Psychology &amp; Health</a> compared self-efficacy and perceived enjoyment as predictors of physical activity over time. Their sample included hundreds of adults who were low active at baseline. Participants received either a print-based physical activity promotion program grounded in established behavior change theory or a comparison program. Over the follow-up period, both self-efficacy and enjoyment predicted later physical activity. </p>



  


<p><em><strong>What emerged from the research?</strong> </em>When enjoyment and self-efficacy were entered together, enjoyment held; self-efficacy did not. Follow-through tracked more closely with how much people enjoyed being active than with how confident they felt about being active.</p>
<p><em><strong>What does that mean?</strong></em> Enjoyment didn't merely sit beside self-efficacy as an alternate predictor. It appeared to feed self-efficacy. As enjoyment improved, self-efficacy improved, and that pathway helped explain later activity.</p>

<p><em><strong>Why is that important?</strong></em> That's a different causal story than most health programs assume. It suggests practical reordering of design priorities: Improve the felt experience of the pursuit, and confidence often follows.</p>
<p>This aligns with related work in clinical populations. In <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/27445882">a study of cancer patients</a> participating in structured programs, enjoyment increased during the intervention and directly predicted physical activity level immediately after the program, adding explanatory value beyond self-efficacy in regression models. Taken together, these findings support a shift that matters for medical fitness operators and healthcare partners. Self-efficacy is worth cultivating, yet enjoyment is not a soft add-on. It can be a primary driver and is likely upstream of confidence.</p>

<h2>Adherence <em>is</em> the intervention</h2>
<p>In acute care, interventions can be delivered to a passive body. In lifestyle medicine and medical fitness, the intervention is a behavior sustained over time. That fundamentally changes what "effective" means. A program is not effective when it's well-designed on paper. A program is effective when people keep doing it long enough for the minimal viable dose to accumulate.</p>

<p>This is why adherence deserves to be treated as a primary outcome rather than a secondary nuisance variable. (In fact, pruning dropouts is one cause for a lot of critical takes on wellness research, given its propensity for creating selection bias.) Adherence shouldn't be something that's considered as <em>happening</em> during (or after) the intervention. In many cases, adherence actually should be considered <em>the</em> intervention! Seen through this lens, enjoyment is no longer a luxury. It should be the predictive variable we focus on as an intervention designer. If the pursuit of an intervention is experienced as punishing, tedious, or socially uncomfortable, the program is essentially prescribing dropout risk.</p>

<h2>Pursuit-first design in medical fitness</h2>
<p>The good news is that designing for fun doesn't require gimmicks. Here are a few design considerations I've pulled directly from the science of enjoyment and adherence, which translate cleanly into operator practice and healthcare partnerships.</p>
<p><strong>1) Treat affect as data, not as mood</strong></p>

<p>Affective response is often more informative than motivational talk. Programs can track it with simple tools. For instance, a brief enjoyment rating after sessions, a question about desire to return, and/or a short check-in on what felt good or bad. These measures should be treated as important leading indicators. For instance, if early affective signal trends negatively, expect adherence problems even when people endorse high importance.</p>

<p><strong>2) Preserve autonomy inside guardrails</strong></p>
<p>Referral-based programs carry constraints, contraindications, intensities, movement restrictions, and monitoring protocols. Autonomy still exists inside those constraints. Offer modality choice, pacing choice, music choice, time-of-day choice, sequencing choice, and social choice. Give people a sense of authorship. When the person experiences the program as something done with them, not to them, the pursuit gains psychological ownership.</p>

<p><strong>3) Engineer competence experiences early and often</strong></p>
<p>Self-efficacy is built through mastery. Mastery does not require maximal effort. It requires repeated experiences of success. Design sessions so the default experience is, "I can do this, and I can feel myself improving." Make the win visible within the session, not only in distal outcomes. Competence without shame is a retention tool.</p>

<p><strong>4) Use belonging as a clinical lever</strong></p>
<p>Many medical fitness participants arrive with identity threat. They may feel behind, judged, or out of place in fitness environments. Belonging is not a marketing concept here; it's a design consideration for better adherence. Small cohorts, stable coach relationships, and peer norms that celebrate consistency over intensity can shift predicted experience. When people feel safe and accepted, the pursuit becomes easier to repeat.</p>

<h2>What this change looks like for operators and healthcare partners</h2>
<p>If you accept that adherence is interconnected to any given intervention, program design priorities shift.</p>
<ul>
<li>You still track outcomes. You just stop treating outcomes as the primary consideration.</li>
<li>You still value education. You just stop assuming education produces repetition.</li>
<li>You still coach confidence. You just start paying equal attention to enjoyment as a precursor.</li>
</ul>

<p>Referral pathways often assume motivation resides inside the patient or client. A pursuit-first lens treats adherence as a shared design problem. The program's job is to create an experience that people want to return to and that clinicians trust. When we can get this right in designing health interventions, better outcomes are almost guaranteed to follow. They become the natural consequence of a pursuit that's sustainable.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-science-of-fun/202602/enjoy-the-pursuit-why-adherence-is-the-real-intervention" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-science-of-fun/202602/enjoy-the-pursuit-why-adherence-is-the-real-intervention</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-science-of-fun/202602/enjoy-the-pursuit-why-adherence-is-the-real-intervention</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Mike Rucker Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/enjoy-the-pursuit.jpg?h=6f7f5d9d&amp;itok=FkyqMbZH" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why Are Clients Turning to AI for Mental Health?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-05/Jeremy.png.jpg?itok=xpmauPWn" alt="Jeremy G. Schneider LMSW, MFT" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Artificial Intelligence</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Why Are Clients Turning to AI for Mental Health?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">What it means when people who know how therapy works still turn to AI.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 22, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Many individuals using AI for emotional support already have experience with traditional human therapy.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">People seek out AI chatbots to access on-demand, pragmatic strategies for emotional regulation and support.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Clinicians who dismiss AI risk alienating clients and creating distance within the therapeutic relationship.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p dir="ltr">In my last AI for Interactive Journaling workshop, I ran a completely unscientific poll that really surprised me. Of the 55 people who reported therapy experience, 49% are turning to AI for mental health support. Not only that, but they are finding working with AI helpful. </p>
<p dir="ltr">These are people who know what therapy looks and feels like. </p>

<p dir="ltr">And they’re still using and benefiting from AI.</p>
<p dir="ltr">It’s been easy to assume that most people using AI for emotional support were people who didn’t have access to therapy, couldn’t afford it, or didn’t really understand the process. However, Rousmaniere et al. (2025) reported 87% of respondents who used AI for mental health support also had experience with human therapy. When Rousmaniere asked respondents to compare their experiences with AI versus human therapy, nearly 75% said their experience was equal to or better with AI. </p>

<p dir="ltr">I’m not arguing AI is better than therapy. I don’t believe that.</p>
<p dir="ltr">But if people who have experience with a human therapist are turning to AI either in place of or as a supplement to therapy, we need to take a closer look at what is happening to possibly explain this.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Some therapists have the belief that people should “know better” than to use a computer over human therapy. Yet, it seems people who understand therapy are quite comfortable chatting with an algorithm. Why?</p>

<h2>The Need for Immediate, Actionable Troubleshooting</h2>
<p dir="ltr">What if this data is telling us that some people don't need traditional therapy as their primary source of support? What if this suggests that what people actually need is faster, more direct, more immediately actionable help that AI can easily provide?</p>

<p dir="ltr">AI excels at breaking down a problem quickly, getting to the heart of the matter, offering direct responses, a therapeutic approach many master's programs have not traditionally emphasized, favoring open-ended exploration instead.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Therapists may argue this isn't really therapy, that it is really just “therapy-lite.” Someone using AI for emotional support is most likely not getting the same intensive benefits of therapy. </p>

<p dir="ltr">But this misses the point. AI isn't "therapy-lite"; it's a different tool for a different job. If chatting with AI provides someone relief from an anxiety spiral at 3 a.m., or helps them map out exactly why they feel stuck at work and what to do about it at 2 p.m. on a Tuesday, then maybe they don’t need the full, intensive benefits of traditional therapy in that moment. </p>

<h2>The Risk of Creating Distance</h2>
<p dir="ltr">The uncomfortable truth is that therapists who haven't tried AI themselves will struggle to talk about it meaningfully with clients who are already using it. </p>
<p dir="ltr">If AI becomes a taboo subject that cannot be brought up safely in session, clients will simply hide it. By judging the technology rather than getting curious about it, we will have created exactly the kind of distance and shame that therapy is supposed to dissolve.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Aren't we supposed to meet our clients where they're at? Today, a lot of them are finding relief through a screen.</p>
<p dir="ltr">This isn't just about AI and technology. It's about making therapy useful for the people we most want to be helping. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/human-centered-technology/202602/why-are-clients-turning-to-ai-for-mental-health" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/human-centered-technology/202602/why-are-clients-turning-to-ai-for-mental-health</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/human-centered-technology/202602/why-are-clients-turning-to-ai-for-mental-health</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Jeremy G. Schneider LMSW, MFT]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/IMG_6410.JPEG.jpg?itok=2wH56gmB" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Is Your Personality Costing You Opportunities at Work?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-03/Shannon%20Sauer-Zavala%20%281%29.png.jpg?itok=gCfV10SZ" alt="Shannon Sauer-Zavala Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Career</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Is Your Personality Costing You Opportunities at Work?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Why competence isn’t always enough to move you forward at work.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 22, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Career stagnation can be driven by personality patterns, not lack of competence.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Traits that support early success can become liabilities as roles and expectations change.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Aligning personality patterns with your next step can open new professional opportunities.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p dir="ltr">When people feel stuck at work, they often assume the problem is a skills gap. They need more experience, better credentials, or another certification. But in many cases, missed opportunities have less to do with competence and more to do with how your default personality patterns are showing up on the job. </p>

<p dir="ltr">You can be very good at what you do and still be overlooked for what comes next.</p>
<h2>Kelly: Dependable, Organized, and Passed Over</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Kelly was indispensable at work. She would respond to your email within six hours (often sooner) and her door was always open if someone needed a hand. When a task needed to get done, people trusted her to handle it. Early in her career, this level of conscientiousness served her well. She built credibility and avoided making mistakes.</p>

<p dir="ltr">But when leadership opportunities opened up, Kelly was never selected. When she asked for feedback, she was told that no one questioned her competence, but she wasn’t seen as someone who would lead change or set innovative new directions.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Kelly’s personality hadn’t suddenly become a liability. It just wasn’t aligned with what her desired next role required.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Leadership in her organization demanded visibility, assertiveness, and innovation. Kelly’s quest for inbox zero took time away from big-picture thinking, and her tendency to wait until she was absolutely sure before speaking—once an asset—now worked against her.</p>
<h2>When Traits That Helped You Succeed Are Now a Liability</h2>

<p dir="ltr">Early career success often rewards consistency, diligence, and compliance. But advancement tends to require a different configuration of traits: comfort with uncertainty, influence, visibility, and strategic risk-taking.</p>
<p dir="ltr">This can look like:</p>
<ul>
<li dir="ltr">The agreeable team player who keeps the peace but never negotiates for resources.</li>
<li dir="ltr">The conscientious perfectionist who never delegates and becomes overwhelmed.</li>
<li dir="ltr">The introverted expert who avoids self-promotion and stays invisible.</li>
<li dir="ltr">The anxious high-performer who hesitates to take on assignments that stretch them.</li>
</ul>

<p dir="ltr">In each case, personality traits that once supported success begin to narrow what’s possible. </p>
<h2>It is Possible to Shift Your Traits So They Align With Your Next Step</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Most people view personality as their underlying essence that explains how they think, feel, and behave. Yet this colloquial understanding of personality doesn’t line up with personality science. </p>

<p dir="ltr">Instead, personality traits are a description of your patterns, not the cause of them. And people adjust how they think and behave all the time. This can happen when we’re thrown into a new role or environment that pulls for you to show up differently. For example, maybe you have to start running meetings while you’re filling in for a coworker who is on leave; as you share your ideas more, you might start to think about yourself as someone with leadership potential. </p>


<p dir="ltr">In other words, personality is not set in stone. And you don’t have to wait for changes in your environment to draw new habits and thinking patterns out of you. You can intentionally try on new behaviors that better align with the roles you desire.</p>
<p dir="ltr">This doesn’t mean forcing yourself into an inauthentic mold. Kelly didn’t need to become reckless or domineering to advance.</p>

<p dir="ltr">But she did need to practice new patterns alongside her existing strengths.</p>
<p dir="ltr">That meant:</p>
<ul>
<li dir="ltr">Keep her door closed for periods of time to focus on innovation.</li>
<li dir="ltr">Delegating to others so she has space to lead.</li>
<li dir="ltr">Speaking up when she has a good idea, even if all the details aren’t yet worked out.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="ltr">These were small shifts in behavior—but over time, they changed how others perceived her and how she perceived herself. And given that personality is one’s characteristic pattern of thinking and behavior, Kelly’s answers on a personality assessment would change if she kept these new habits up over time.</p>



  


<h2>From Fit to Growth</h2>
<p dir="ltr">If you’re feeling stalled at work, consider looking beyond new professional training and competency development. </p>
<p dir="ltr">Instead, you might ask yourself: Who do I need to become to achieve success in my next step? </p>
<p dir="ltr">Indeed, career growth often requires becoming the person who can hold the next role, not just the person who excelled in the last one.</p>

<p dir="ltr">When personality adapts, opportunity tends to follow. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/self-made/202602/is-your-personality-costing-you-opportunities-at-work" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/self-made/202602/is-your-personality-costing-you-opportunities-at-work</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/self-made/202602/is-your-personality-costing-you-opportunities-at-work</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Shannon Sauer-Zavala Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/proxyclick-visitor-management-system-BgT-ZKC6WA4-unsplash.jpg?itok=UZdJOxyH" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[LIfe's Greatest Accomplishments]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-06/Paul%20Dunion.png.jpg?itok=0M8shGnk" alt="Paul J. Dunion Ed.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Gratitude</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">LIfe's Greatest Accomplishments</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Triumphing over both defeat and victory.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 21, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">How to manage feeling defeated.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The information was gathered through the clinical work with hundreds of clients.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Understand what it means to be defeated by victory.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Applications for triumphing over defeat and victory.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/mathieu-gauzy-ItsEF1_h3KQ-unsplash.jpg?itok=6mb8Uiht" width="320" height="480" data-insert-type="image" title="Mathieu Gauzy / Unsplash" alt="Mathieu Gauzy / Unsplash"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Mathieu Gauzy / Unsplash</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The following by John Steinbeck supports a well-lived life. “Greatness lies in the one who triumphs equally over defeat and victory.” Steinbeck is encouraging us to risk fully participating in life, with both defeat and victory being inevitable. It means living life on life’s terms, doing what we can to minimize being defeated by either defeat or victory. Let’s look more closely at what it means to be defeated by defeat. </p>

<h2>Defeated by Defeat</h2>
<p>If we’re not feeling victorious, then we’re not only feeling defeated but also defeated by the defeat. That means we might be feeling like a failure, slipping into self-contempt and self-doubt. When these energies are activated, it can be difficult to appreciate our efforts and our best intentions. We’re simply the person who messed up. We may become excessively cautious and fearful about future undertakings. Or, we might compensate by taking on quixotic tasks with little or no hope for success.</p>

<h2>Triumphing Over Defeat</h2>
<p>Let’s look at how we can triumph over defeat. </p>
<ul>
<li>Heighten your acceptance of defeat as a natural expression of the human condition.</li>
<li>Acknowledge your defeat as a reflection of your willingness to fully participate in life.</li>
<li>In retrospect, assess how much control you actually possessed in order to avoid defeat.</li>
<li>How effective was your assessment of the level of risk involved as you approached the project?</li>
<li>If someone was injuriously impacted by your defeat, consider making restitution.</li>
<li>Talk to someone whom you trust about your defeat.</li>
<li>Take the necessary steps to forgive yourself. </li>
</ul>

<h2>Defeated by Victory</h2>
<p>The problems with being defeated by victory are considerably more hidden and subtle. Even the language sounds and feels strange: “defeated by victory.” Allegedly, victory doesn’t defeat us; it only benefits or offers some advantage. However, one consequence of being victorious is that we can be challenged to value ourselves when we are not. Another form of defeat is getting caught up in the obsession of having to constantly be more impressively victorious than the last time. Such an infatuation can have us becoming myopic, unable to see and respond to the rest of life.</p>

<p> Our humanity is defeated when we begin to view our victories as who we are, forgetting about the rest of our lives, our families, and friends. Our aggrandized identity can remove us from what we love and need, denying where vulnerability lives in us. Another unfortunate consequence when we are defeated by victory is an emerging entitlement that blurs our vision of the needs and aspirations of others. </p>

<h2>Triumph Over Victory</h2>
<ul>
<li>Understand the consequences of not triumphing over victory.</li>
<li>Be grateful for all the support you’ve received, making this victory possible. The gratitude can extend beyond your contemporaries to teachers, mentors, friends, and family members along the way.</li>
<li>Be curious about how your victory will strengthen your capacity to serve.</li>
<li>Let go of any attachment to arrive at some elevated posture of greatness.</li>
<li>Allow the victory to be something you did and not who you are.</li>
<li>Talk to someone whom you trust about the lure to allow the victory to define you.</li>
</ul>

<p>The slightest instability of our self-esteem can have us diminishing ourselves when defeated and elevating ourselves when victorious. Our psychological task is to bring ourselves back to the soundness of our ordinary humanity. It is there we take the bite out of defeat, and victory loses its glittering glow. </p>


            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-secular-mystic-path/202602/lifes-greatest-accomplishments" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-secular-mystic-path/202602/lifes-greatest-accomplishments</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-secular-mystic-path/202602/lifes-greatest-accomplishments</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Paul J Dunion Ed.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/mathieu-gauzy-ItsEF1_h3KQ-unsplash.jpg?itok=299iEB8W" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[AI Can Help Solve the Reading Achievement Gap]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-08/Coral%20PS%20Hoh.png.jpg?itok=ofjeER8q" alt="Coral PS Hoh" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Artificial Intelligence</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">AI Can Help Solve the Reading Achievement Gap</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">There is a persistent racial gap in reading achievement. But AI can help close it.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 21, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The reading achievement gap is actually an opportunity gap that AI can close.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Custom-built AI can ensure objectivity that learners value in evaluation and intervention.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Economical, scalable AI removes the dependency between expensive resources and student performance.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">AI enables the individualization of general and special education.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Aaliyah%20Williams.jpg?itok=Phrtnxuu" width="320" height="307" data-insert-type="image" alt="Aaliyah Williams, Hartwick College, was an early adopter of an AI intervention to clear her reading difficulty in fifth grade." title="Aaliyah Williams"></div>
<div class="caption">Aaliyah Williams, Hartwick College, was an early adopter of an AI intervention to clear her reading difficulty in fifth grade.</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Aaliyah Williams</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>During this Black History Month, let us attend for a moment to the reading achievement gap, as it affects all of us regardless of race. Here's why. Lack of literacy is linked to some of the biggest and costliest problems in society: spiralling special education spending, school dropouts, juvenile delinquency, incarceration, poverty, and mental health (NSBA, 2019; Vacca, 2008; Vacca, 2004; Nelson &amp; Gregg, 2012). We all pay for these problems, at the very least in taxes.</p>

<h2>We Spend Over $120 Billion Yearly on Special Education</h2>
<p>Reading difficulty, or dyslexia, is classified as a learning disability in special education. Taking up about a third of special ed, dyslexia is the biggest category. As a nation, we spend over $120 billion a year on special ed (NCLD, 2023). The bulk of it comes from our local school taxes.</p>

<p>What is the yield on our yearly investment? Students with dyslexia still read below grade level. They<a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/unlocking-language/202411/the-high-cost-of-learning-disabilities-for-college-students"> drop out of high school</a> at more than twice the typical rate (NSBA, 2019). Only 5 percent of them go to college, compared to 60 percent of their typical peers (Anthony, 2021). This impacts lifetime earnings, as their peers with college degrees earn about $1 million more than high school diploma holders.</p>

<h2>70 Percent of Students Are Not Reading-Proficient</h2>
<p>But the literacy problem is not confined to the 20 percent who have dyslexia (Yale Center for Dyslexia, 2022). According to the Nation's Report Card, around 70 percent of students now fail to meet reading standards in some states, including New York and Georgia. While approximately 40 percent of white readers are proficient, less than 20 percent of Black readers are (NCES, 2025).</p>

<h2>The Literacy Link: Juvenile Delinquency and Incarceration</h2>
<p>In the field of criminal justice, poor literacy skills are recognized factors of crime (Vacca, 2008). The Department of Justice associates juvenile delinquency with low reading ability (Brunner, 1993). African American youths are overrepresented in this system. Half of prison inmates cannot read or write. The National Institute for Literacy reports that nearly half of adults with the lowest literacy skills live in poverty, most with no full- or part-time employment.</p>

<p>The words of a 68-year-old inmate at the California Correctional Institution capture the human and societal cost of these systemic problems. David wrote to our firm when he heard a <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/nightly-news/video/a-i-revolution-how-artificial-intelligence-is-helping-children-with-dyslexia-227631173993">news report </a>about Dysolve, our AI expert system that resolves dyslexia. He had been incarcerated for eight years.</p>
<p>"Like many inmates here in prison, I didn't get my diploma from high school do [sic] to my learning disability of dyslexia...The one quote I have heard many times [at school] and can't stand hearing is 'Not trying hard enough.' Plus all of the other quotes [being labeled lazy, dumb, careless, immature] are really hard on a kid's self-esteem."</p>

<p>When it comes to literacy, every aspect of a citizen's life is affected, from the academic, legal, and economic to the psycho-social.</p>
<h2>AI Drives Transformational Change for Endemic Problems</h2>
<p>But during this particular Black History Month, we can go beyond mere reminders of these endemic, systemic problems. We are at the beginning of an AI revolution that is transforming many fields all at once. The reading problem is not immune.</p>

<p>In my previous post, "<a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/unlocking-language/202511/ai-beat-reading-interventions-in-clinical-trial">AI Beat Reading Interventions in Clinical Trial</a>," I mentioned that our expert system managed to break a long-standing barrier: clearing reading difficulty in students after third grade. With other interventions, reading research shows that older struggling readers will continue to struggle throughout school regardless (Elliott &amp; Grigorenko, 2014).</p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.cresp.udel.edu/publication/dysolve-rct-results/">Dysolve clinical trial</a>, a randomized controlled trial, is noteworthy because participation was primarily from the group that has often been left out of screening, funding, and research. Approximately 80 percent of the trial's participants were minority from low-income communities. They were in grades 3 through 8, performing at the 10th percentile on average in state and school standardized reading assessments pre-intervention (May &amp; Van Horne, 2025).</p>



  


<h2>Implications of the First AI Educational Intervention Trial</h2>
<p>That the trial produced a positive effect in this population has several implications:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>The debate over poor vs. dyslexic readers becomes moot.</strong> This computer system is focused only on clearing language processing difficulties that hinder reading development, not on how they came to be. Previously, some quarters wanted to differentiate between reading difficulty caused by poor learning environments vs. genetics or neurology. A neuropsychological evaluation to get a diagnosis costs $5K to 10K per person. A dyslexia diagnosis thus becomes an economic, not a clinical, issue. To the AI system, however, the label does not matter.</li>
<li><strong>AI-powered intervention is nonjudgmental.</strong> This synthetic expert cannot see the student. It cannot use the multitude of clues from physical appearance, demeanor, etc., to form impressions about this person that may bias evaluation results. For this reason, some struggling learners, especially older ones, prefer dealing with a computer program to human specialists.</li>
<li><strong>AI severs the relationship between results and resources.</strong> Previously, low-income districts showed poorer results due to scarce resources for high-quality teachers, teacher training, and instructional materials. The point of well-designed AI is to solve the problem of scalability, cost, and outcomes. The Dysolve trial occurred during the COVID pandemic, when schools were scrambling to find any teacher, or any paraprofessional, to supervise classrooms—similar to what is still happening in struggling districts presently. The AI technology is designed to work even under these trying circumstances, yielding a positive impact in the trial.</li>
</ul>

<p>Challenging settings require an autonomous plug-and-play program. The supervising adult's role is simply to put the child in front of a computer or tablet and let the AI expert do its work. Dysolve AI presents interactive game activities tailored to that student's particular learning problems, continuously on demand. What underfunded districts cannot afford is paying $10K to train each teacher and $10K to 20K for each special ed pupil a year indefinitely due to ineffective methods. An efficacious AI solution is thus also an economic solution.</p>

<h2>Individualization of Education Levels the Playing Field</h2>
<p>This AI innovation is a precursor to the individualization of education. Each student gets an individualized program specific to their strengths and weaknesses. We are beginning to see its impact on struggling learners who are motivated to seize the opportunity. When they do, they are empowered to change their own developmental trajectory.</p>

<p>Jesseme Lynch from North Carolina explained how his reading difficulty affected his self-esteem in third grade: "It kind of made me feel disappointed in myself because I couldn't read the words like everybody else." Three months later, his attitude changed along with academic improvement: "After Dysolve, I can tell what the words meant, and I could get good scores."</p>

<p>Aaliyah Williams struggled to keep up with her classmates in learning and understanding subject matter in fifth grade: "I had a hard time comprehending books and had a significantly lower reading level than where I should have been." After the AI intervention, Aaliyah read on-grade. By her senior year of high school, she took a college-level English course and subsequently thrived in college.</p>

<p>Cases such as Jesseme's and Aaliyah's remind us that the reading achievement gap is really an opportunity gap. When we are able to give these children the opportunity to excel, they often do.</p>
<p>Now that's worth celebrating during this Black History Month. </p>
<p>My next post will be about an 88-year-old civil rights activist with dyslexia who is using his own positive experience with the AI program to advocate for others. Stay tuned.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/unlocking-language/202602/ai-can-help-solve-the-reading-achievement-gap" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/unlocking-language/202602/ai-can-help-solve-the-reading-achievement-gap</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/unlocking-language/202602/ai-can-help-solve-the-reading-achievement-gap</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Coral PS Hoh Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/bigstock-Outdoor-Portrait-Of-A-Cute-You-45302887.jpg?itok=SiPhkyNv" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Misperceiving What's Attainable Aids Maladaptive Daydreaming]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-05/Leon-Garber.jpg?itok=SCVGgFWd" alt="Leon Garber LMHC" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Fantasies</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Misperceiving What's Attainable Aids Maladaptive Daydreaming</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Challenging your beliefs about your ideal life can help you live your real one.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 21, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Maladaptive Daydreaming is supported by the conviction that one's fantasies are forthcoming.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The related fantasies leave out the discomforts of one's sought after existence.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Challenging the cognitive distortions of our hopes and dreams can help us make more meaningful choices.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>People with obsessive-compulsive tendencies tend to struggle immensely with decision-making. Outsiders looking in wonder why common choices, like where to work or whom to marry, are so challenging for them. Worsening the problem is the proclivity toward maladaptive daydreaming, spending hours on end fantasizing about ideal scenarios. Often, these imagined scenarios don’t even entail the full scope of what would be expected were they to exist. A person who dreams of becoming a singer might only focus on the parts they like, like singing in a big arena, while leaving out the fatigue, the bad reviews, the deadlines, the anxiety of being on stage, and the physical symptoms that accompany it.</p>

<p>For those with vivid imaginations and convictions about what’s possible, maladaptive daydreaming serves not only as a place of respite; it’s also a reminder of what’s to come. The fantasies are as powerful as they are because the individual engaged in them sincerely believes them to be harbingers, merely necessitating patience. It’s a misconception that people who engage in maladaptive daydreaming do so because they prefer fantasy to reality—in reality, they prefer it momentarily, and only if it represents what’s to come. The fantasies are fueled by a mix of naivety, grandiosity, low distress tolerance, resentment, greed, and wishful thinking. Sometimes, there’s little sense of how the world works; at others is the belief that one can and will be the exception to it.</p>

<p>Treatment for maladaptive daydreaming is challenging due to the emotional pull and payoffs of it; one essentially tends to use it as their main mechanism of self-soothing. And, even worse, they just as often fail to account for future regrets because they believe they will, at some distant time and for hitherto unknown reasons, make their dreams come true. Our culture may easily support this form of escapism. Dating apps present myriad options, which make you feel like you can craft your love life with precision. So, when you encounter a problem, which obviously conflicts with fantasy, you’re able to give yourself permission to move on—your dream life feels like a swipe away. That also applies to one’s career, where hardships, including difficult conversations with management, can be avoided if you believe yourself to be the belle of the ball, under-appreciated and unseen.</p>

<p>Looksmaxxing is another instance of this, where lonesome boys fantasize about a charmed life stemming from beauty. These individuals strongly believe that beauty equals clout, leading to the fulfillment of all of one’s desires, a world wherein one is never told no. The fantasies of maladaptive daydreaming are supported by several distorted thinking patterns. The looksmaxxer, for example, over-generalizes, believing that beauty’s outsized influence must imply a pleasure-filled and painless existence. And this can apply to all forms of maladaptive dreaming, where some life outcome is idealized. Here, we encounter naivety. The daydreamer engages in black and white thinking, dividing up the world between winners and losers, conceiving of their fantasy as a reward for attaining high status.</p>

<p>And the perception of the winner’s circle is supported by mental filtering, the process of fixating on either the negative or positive aspects of some experience, in this case, the positive. So, returning to our example of the singer, mental filtering removes all of the discomforts of singing on stage, including the less-than-stellar circumstances of a musician’s career. Additionally, we have mind-reading, where the fantasy entails a vision of universal and untarnished love, even if only from several important individuals. Lastly, there’s fortune-telling, through which the daydreamer remains certain their patience will pay off. And all of this is supported by the kernels of truth in their beliefs. Beauty does increase your influence. You may be happier in a different job. Another romantic partner might be a better fit.</p>

<p>The problem isn’t in wanting more; it’s with wanting everything. So, to address maladaptive daydreaming, one has to initially acknowledge the possibility that their perspectives of the world and their life might be as problematic as their circumstances. Is your perception of your life as distorted as your beliefs about your future? Through black and white thinking, we tend to sharply devalue what we have and what we’ve accomplished while overvaluing what we don’t. Therefore, it may help to view your life through a clear lens, challenging your distorted thoughts about it. Are you unlikable? Are you unfairly devaluing your romantic prospects, even doing so because you fear letting them down? Do you ever enjoy time spent with people who already like you, who don’t need you to perform?</p>

<p>It may also help to read the biographies of people you admire. (I recommend <a href="https://www.instagram.com/reel/DVBOo7XAL55/">watching</a> Dani Evans discuss life after winning America’s Next Top Model.) Fame, beauty, brilliance, etc… hardly ever lead to ideal lives. There’s often a fundamental sense of disappointment, which can easily catalyze more fantasies. None of these attributes are bad in and of themselves, but it helps to be honest with yourself about what they can and can’t do for you. <br><br>The 90’s movie <em>Mr. Destiny</em> teaches us this lesson. Jim Belushi, after being granted his ideal life, realizes that he preferred what he already had, thanking the angel for showing him everything, “both the good and the bad.” In a pivotal scene, he’s shown painting a model, luxury car, which he tells his dream wife that he prefers over the real thing, which he has. Before the transformation, he spent his weekends, in part, painting model, luxury vehicles—the comfort of which was the foundation of sustained joy. Realizing the fantasy is always better than the reality, paradoxically, extinguishes the fantasy’s power; it’s only grand when it feels attainable. But all of this doesn’t mean that we shouldn’t strive; only that we shouldn’t lose ourselves in desire.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/perfectionism/202602/misperceiving-whats-attainable-aids-maladaptive-daydreaming" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/perfectionism/202602/misperceiving-whats-attainable-aids-maladaptive-daydreaming</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/perfectionism/202602/misperceiving-whats-attainable-aids-maladaptive-daydreaming</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Leon Garber LMHC]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/tylijura-girl-9991188_1920.jpg?itok=DTfIhfyu" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How Would Your Life Change if You Didn’t Seek Approval?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/untitled_2_0.jpg?itok=sNYHTgsC" alt="Robert Taibbi L.C.S.W." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Fear</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">How Would Your Life Change if You Didn’t Seek Approval?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">It’s not about being insensitive to others, but building your own life.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 21, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Building our lives around the approval of others keeps us from truly living our own.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">It is the fear of others' reactions that holds us back. Breaking out is about approaching our anxiety.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The key is recognizing when our fear has taken over & challenging ourseives to step outside our comfort zone.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/businessman-2879470_1280.jpg?itok=R-CMInAG" width="320" height="212" data-insert-type="image" title="Goumbik/pixabay" alt="Goumbik/pixabay"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Goumbik/pixabay</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Of course, there are narcissists who seek as much recognition and approval from others as they can, but that’s not usually who I see in my practice. Instead, it’s the more average Joe or Jane who struggles not because they crave power, but because they're afraid of conflict and upsetting others. They feel stressed and pulled by wanting acceptance and approval from too many masters. And they’re tired of shaping their lives around others—essentially living <em>their</em> lives to fulfill <em>others'</em> needs and expectations rather than their own. They know what they’re doing; they just don’t know how to stop. This is their Achilles’ heel.</p>

<p>What keeps them from stopping is not only habit and autopilot but also fear of what might happen if they stop accommodating others. If you’re feeling the same, here are several questions to help you break free:</p>
<h2>#1: How would your life change in a positive way if you stopped worrying about others’ approval?</h2>

<p>Can you imagine being free from the anxiety of constantly wondering what others might think? What would you do differently than you're doing now? How would you feel in your everyday life?</p>
<h2>#2: What do you fear?</h2>
<p>Maybe you naturally assume the worst: that others will be disappointed, push back, criticize, or get angry. The confrontation you learned long ago to avoid will now come up again.</p>

<p>Or, maybe something else—fear rejection and possible loss—that your connection to others is tethered by your willingness to accommodate; once you give that up, they will pull away, leaving you alone. Or, perhaps you worry that you could swing too far to the other side, changing who you are, replacing walking on eggshells with selfishness, becoming that narcissist who tosses empathy aside and only cares about themselves.</p>

<p>Your fears and beliefs are what have kept you doing what you do. Once you’re aware of them, you can change them.</p>
<h2>#3: What if the worst-case actually happens?</h2>
<p>One way to manage anxiety is by learning to reduce it. However, sometimes the cause is real, and the best solution is to have a plan so you can mentally set it aside rather than constantly obsess over it.</p>

<p>Okay, so what if the worst-case scenario happens? Maybe your supervisor gets angry because you complained about the new work schedule, or you get fired because you can’t adjust to it. Or, you confront your partner about their credit card spending or drinking, and not only do they explode, but you also get divorced. Or, maybe your best friend says, 'I don’t know what’s come over you,' and ends the relationship.</p>

<h2>#4: Are you able to survive? Can you imagine what your next move might be?</h2>
<p>This is the time to replace your emotional brain with your rational one. Yes, you have skills and could find another job. Divorce will be a tough transition for a couple of years; you’re a sensitive parent and must make sure your kids get the support and care they might need. Having learned the lessons of your marriage, maybe you’ll find someone new who’s a better fit. And if your best friend walks away, you’ll mourn the loss, but you know you're capable of forming new friendships.</p>


<h2>Moving forward.</h2>
<p>But what if I can’t, you say—find another job, relationship, or friend? This isn't about personality or circumstances but about learning skills. Again, here's a suggestion:</p>
<h2>Practice approaching what you’ve been avoiding.</h2>
<p>Fear controls you; it/s what fuels the “I can’t”. It's time to push back by learning to endure strong negative emotions; raising your tolerance involves taking small, manageable steps outside your comfort zone.</p>

<p>So, when you get the wrong change at Starbucks or your partner leaves her clothes scattered around the bedroom again, and your instinct is to let it go, don’t. Go back and show the Starbucks worker your receipt. Say something to your partner about her scattered clothes, even if it takes you three days to get up the courage to do so. And if talking about it feels too challenging, write a note and leave it on the kitchen counter.</p>



  


<h2>Upgrade the script and skills.</h2>
<p>Seeking approval is a habit learned long ago as a way to cope with others. As a child, you had limited options and did the best you could, but now it’s time to do what you couldn’t then. The challenge is to become less afraid by learning new skills, stepping outside your comfort zone, taking risks, and discovering that what you expect to happen often doesn’t. </p>

<p dir="ltr"><em>To find a therapist near you, visit the </em><a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/therapists"><em>Psychology Today Therapy Directory</em></a><em>.</em></p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/fixing-families/202602/how-would-your-life-change-if-you-didnt-seek-approval" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/fixing-families/202602/how-would-your-life-change-if-you-didnt-seek-approval</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/fixing-families/202602/how-would-your-life-change-if-you-didnt-seek-approval</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Robert Taibbi L.C.S.W.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/businessman-2879470_1280.jpg?itok=HZuZS0Tr" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Reclaiming the Playful Self]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/Scott-Eberle.jpg?itok=LKAwfeht" alt="Scott G. Eberle Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Play</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Reclaiming the Playful Self</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Looking for autonomy and joy in serious play.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 21, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">A quarter-life crisis can come early for Olympic hopefuls.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Alysa Liu, figure-skating prodigy, needed to find both joy and autonomy on her path to Olympic gold.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">While competition can elbow out play, play can be reclaimed.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Here is a question that invites an obvious answer: Is play playful? Playfulness seems part and parcel of play.</p>
<p>But hang on. Call to mind sedentary, intensely engrossed grandmasters welded to their checkered boards at a tournament. They go off their feed. They sweat buckets. They lose 10 pounds or more as they play their intricate, drawn-out mental game. Exhausted, stressed, win or lose, they withdraw after a match to a soak in warmed, bentonite clay, Slavic lullabies playing on the spa speakers.</p>

<p>In the electronic games universe, some of the multiplayer contests are so demanding in their detail, so complex in their character relations and retaliations, and so entwined with fantasy physics that need mastering, that high-level players will lose themselves in the contests that come to seem more work-like than play-like. It’s a second job, some will say, ruefully.</p>

<p>Or, traditionally, consider golf. Some adepts will become poised during a round, entering a deep, rewarding, flow-like state. The force is with them. Not seldom in fact, though, everyday duffers will cuss at an off-fairway lie or sputter as they hack away once trapped in sand. <em>Golf</em>…</p>
<h2>Finding the Playfulness in Play</h2>

<p>Even among those who make a living at play, professionals in high-stakes games, playfulness will sometimes poke through. The Buffalo Bills' number 17, quarterback Josh Allen, who is playing a serious and dangerous game, is so happy at the prospect of a goal line that he will jump over an opposing linebacker. He’s big. He’s fast. He’s gleeful.</p>

<p>Or Muhammad Ali, who was a wiseacre even in the punishing ring— “Is that all you got, Chump?”—was even more dismissive of reporters’ tendentious, tedious questioning. After joining the Nation of Islam, a Black nationalist religious movement, he took heat from the mainstream. Smirking reporters would ask about the prospect of multiple wives, theoretically permissible. Counterpunching, Ali would say he wanted four: one to shine his shoes, one to rub oil on his muscles, one to peel him grapes, and “one named Peaches.”</p>

<p>Or this episode: Casey Stengel, the longtime baseball manager famous for evasive, strategic gobbledygoop—“Stengelese”— replying bewilderingly to a senator’s question in a congressional antitrust hearing, asked, “How could you transfer a ball club when you do not have a highway? How could you transfer a ball club when the railroads would take you to a town and you got off, and then you had to wait and sit up five hours to go to another ball club?” Professional baseball, claiming its business was a natural monopoly for public benefit, had sought an exemption. Mickey Mantle, the Yankees slugger, followed Stengel on the stand. Senator Kefauver, the chair, asked him if he had any “observations with reference to the antitrust laws to baseball?” Mantle replied, “My views are about the same as Casey’s.”</p>

<h2>Playfulness at Olympian Heights</h2>
<p>This year’s Winter Olympic Games, dominated by the spirit of long dedication and sacrifice, grit in the teeth of nearby grievous injury, mastery of ice and snow and gravity-defying grace, have turned up an exception, a truly playful champion.</p>
<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Alysa_LIUAsatur_Yesayants_-_YantsImages_8309_(cropped)_0.jpg?itok=3D40wtRe" width="320" height="479" data-insert-type="image" alt="Gleeful gold-medalist Alysa Liu during the Women’s Single Skating Free Skating ceremony, Milan (February 2026)." title="Yants Images via Wikimedia/CC BY-SA 4.0"></div>
<div class="caption">Gleeful gold-medalist Alysa Liu during the Women’s Single Skating Free Skating ceremony, Milan (February 2026).</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Yants Images via Wikimedia/CC BY-SA 4.0</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Alysa Liu, a figure skater of surpassing brilliance and joy, who took the gold medal in women’s singles figure skating at Cortina in 2026, was not always so apparently carefree.</p>
<p>Her career began at age 5 and a half when she began training with a choreographer. At age 13, she became the youngest women’s national title-holder and followed with similar victories a year later. She could routinely land triple and quadruple jumps and Axels, not long beforehand thought impossible (or unthinkable) for either men or women in an era when figure skating was “ice dancing” and seemingly more suited to a ballroom than a rink.</p>

<h2>Pursued by Spies and Pursuing Greatness</h2>
<p>Urged on by her father, a political refugee from the People's Republic of China, Liu racked up an impressive string of victories at regional, national, international, and world competitions. Her promise attracted the attention of the Chinese government under provisions of its “right of blood” laws, which can consider the children of migrants Chinese citizens, despite their place of birth, in this case, the United States.</p>

<p>Chinese spies targeted her father, Arthur Liu, for his human rights views, seeking leverage to recruit Alysa for their “naturalization project” that meant to intimidate foreign-born athletes of Chinese ancestry into representing China in the 2022 Beijing Olympics. Instead, she competed for the U.S. team and placed eighth in the women’s short program, an impressive Olympic debut.</p>



  


<p>But after 15 years of training regimen, Alysa Liu had had it. A team of coaches, parents, media consultants, costume designers, nutritionists, and sports psychologists had told her how to train, what to say, what to wear, what to eat, and how to feel. When they said jump, she asked how high.</p>
<p>“Skating takes up your whole life, almost,” she wrote on Instagram. Competition had elbowed out the pleasure she might have taken in mastery. Goals fulfilled, bored, weary of micromanagement, feeling restless and worn out, her life had been “a blur,” she said.</p>

<h2>A Hero’s Journey</h2>
<p>Liu’s trajectory fits so perfectly the course of the classic hero’s journey—challenge, separation, rumination, and return—that it might have been scripted by screenwriters. In a quest to find an authentic, joyful self, she emerged from psychological exile transformed.</p>
<p>Reshuffling her staff, distancing herself from her father’s coaching, determined to train her own way, crafting a new exuberant style, she took her career in hand.</p>

<p>For its aspiring stars, the sport had cultivated the looks of princesses, dazzling but prim despite their athleticism, their gazes distant, preoccupied. The new Liu reappeared with a bit of grunge, hair striped playfully like a Disney meerkat, ponytail twirling, the outward sign of inward glee.</p>
<p>When she took the ice in a stellar gold-medal comeback, making the unthinkable look easy, Liu was smiling.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/play-in-mind/202602/finding-the-playful-self-at-play" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/play-in-mind/202602/finding-the-playful-self-at-play</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/play-in-mind/202602/finding-the-playful-self-at-play</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Scott G. Eberle Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/Alysa_LIUAsatur_Yesayants_-_YantsImages_8309_%28cropped%29_0.jpg?itok=fd2sZRDB" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Imagining From Multiple Perspectives]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/Laura-Otis-SCALED.jpg?itok=VCPmgUBF" alt="Laura Otis Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Imagination</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Imagining From Multiple Perspectives</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Fiction-writers can cue your senses to share several viewpoints at once.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 21, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Skilled fiction-writers can guide readers to imagine from multiple perspectives at once.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Combined visual and somatosensory cues can show simultaneously what one character sees and another feels.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Identifying with characters engages readers, but readers can imagine things protagonists can't perceive.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Fiction-reading can develop much-needed skills to imagine situations from multiple viewpoints.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Have you ever been called a pig? Insults can push us to imagine. When you were compared to a grunting animal, did you experimentally plant your mind in a pig’s body? Or did you maybe picture a snout emerging on the person trying to hurt you?</p>
<p>Skilled fiction-writers can guide the imagination, cuing readers to use their senses so that they fantasize more richly than they could alone (Scarry 1999, 3-9). If it serves a storyteller’s artistic aims, a writer can prompt readers to imagine a scene from several perspectives at once. Creative writers can accomplish this goal by blending appeals to readers’ visual and somatosensory (bodily) senses.</p>

<p>Madeline Miller’s novel <em>Circe</em> is all about point of view. In Greek mythology, Circe has a bad reputation—because readers know her from Homer’s <em>Odyssey</em> as a love-hungry witch who turns men to pigs. As an expert on ancient Greek culture, Miller uses literary craft to let Circe tell her own story.</p>
<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/KallernaFinnishPigFarm31.07.2021WikimediaCommons.jpg?itok=nnYicX3n" width="320" height="240" data-insert-type="image" alt="A Finnish Pig Farm" title="kallerna, Pig Farm in Vampula, Finland, 31 July 2021, Wikimedia Commons, Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike International License"></div>
<div class="caption">A Finnish Pig Farm</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: kallerna, Pig Farm in Vampula, Finland, 31 July 2021, Wikimedia Commons, Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike International License</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Daughter of the sun god Helios and the ocean nymph Perse, Circe is scorned by her divine relatives, then exiled to an island for using her powers. She learns that she has a knack for transformation and can use herbs and incantations to “turn creatures to their truest selves” (Miller 63). On her island, she feeds a lost, hungry captain and his crew (not Odysseus and his men, who arrive later), but she uses her powers against them after the captain rapes her.</p>

<p>From Circe’s perspective, Miller describes the rapist’s transformation, guiding readers to imagine what she hears and sees:</p>
<p>"His rib cage cracked and began to bulge. I heard the sound of flesh rupturing wetly, the pops of breaking bone. His nose ballooned from his face, and his legs shriveled like a fly sucked by a spider. He fell to all fours. He screamed, and his men screamed with him. It went on for a long time" (Miller 196).</p>

<p>As Miller conveys what Circe sees and hears, her evocative words encourage readers to imagine how these changes might feel in their own bodies. Human somatosensory modalities include proprioception (detection of bodily position and movement), interoception (detection of internal organs’ states), and pain and temperature detection as well as surface touch. Words like “bulge,” “rupturing,” “ballooned,” and “shriveled” seem crafted to engage readers’ visual <em>and</em> somatosensory systems, enabling them to imagine the suffering witch and her attacker at once.</p>

<p>Psychological studies of reading indicate that feeling immersed in a story often depends on imagining characters’ sensations and actions. Moniek M. Kuijpers and David S. Miall asked readers to report their bodily feelings while reading stories and observed “a positive correlation between absorption and the experience of bodily feeling,” especially in the head, stomach, and chest (Kuijpers &amp; Miall 2011). In the human-to-pig conversion, Miller encourages gut-level imagining by targeting the chest, face, and legs. A recent interview study with fiction-readers has also shown that “self-character comparison is an important component in highly absorbed narrative experiences” (Kuzmičová &amp; Balint 2019, 430). But whose feelings do writers’ words help readers to share? Imagination evoked by literature can run far beyond the protagonist.</p>

<p>Cognitive literary scholar (and fellow <em>PT</em> contributor) <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/contributors/emily-t-troscianko">Emily T. Troscianko</a> sees readers’ imagination as “a form of ongoing exploration” (Troscianko 2013, 185). In a story, language associated with <em>any</em> of the characters or narrator can set off this exploration (Troscianko 2014, 2). </p>
<p>In an experiment, Troscianko asked readers to draw what they experienced internally while reading the opening of Franz Kafka’s novel, <em>The Castle</em>. The participants tended to “elaborate imaginatively to some extent beyond the text given,” since in the snowy darkness, the protagonist K can’t see the castle he’s approaching (Troscianko 2014, 109). The readers drew the castle anyway. Often, “relatable” protagonists imagine beyond their perceptions, which helps explain Troscianko’s finding. Perhaps, sensing K's imagination at work, the readers imagined along with him. Writing a good story involves crafting signs of an active, observant mind, one that imagines what it can’t know based on what its senses are saying.</p>

<p>In this time of political division, the ability to imagine a situation from multiple perspectives has immense social value. Miller’s skill at creating complex situations and characters invites readers to sense how the abuse of power can alter many different lives. Homer never told his listeners that years before Odysseus reached Circe’s island, Circe “felt [a] man tremble” as he raped her, crushing her throat so that she couldn’t scream (Miller 195). Miller guides readers to imagine a witch sensing, relishing, and maybe already regretting her revenge in the moment of its enactment. Miller’s writing motivates readers to imagine feelings experienced by others based on what little they can perceive.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/rethinking-thought/202602/imagining-from-multiple-perspectives" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/rethinking-thought/202602/imagining-from-multiple-perspectives</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/rethinking-thought/202602/imagining-from-multiple-perspectives</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Laura C. Otis Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/KallernaFinnishPigFarm31.07.2021WikimediaCommons.jpg?itok=NMrxgwak" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Way to a Healthy Mind]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/de_vleeschauwer-final.png.jpg?itok=Tyo1pVfJ" alt="Patrick De Vleeschauwer Drs." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Wisdom</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Way to a Healthy Mind</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Seeing beyond the deep wound of our inner struggle.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 21, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Our paradoxical psychology can be seen as the heartbeat of the human mind.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Humans are beings of tension who live between contractive and expansive forces.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Psychological maturity involves learning to see through, accept, manage, and embrace the tension within us.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Human psychology is characterized by a paradoxical structure: The same species that wages war, destabilizes ecosystems, and creates collective threats also develops moral systems, empathic abilities, cultural innovations, and an increasing desire for internal harmony. In my previous post, I explored the possibility to transcend our paradoxical nature through learning. This contribution focuses on learning to see through the nature of our vulnerability.</p>

<div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/0000000000%20PT%2047%20fallon-michael.jpg?itok=gHIjAV6L" width="320" height="213" data-insert-type="image" alt="Fundamentally vulnerable, we are carried into this world." title="Fallon Michael/Unsplash"></div>
<div class="caption">Fundamentally vulnerable, we are carried into this world.</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Fallon Michael/Unsplash</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<h2>The Nature of Our Vulnerability</h2>
<p>The human species is remarkably duplicitous.</p>
<p>On the one hand, humans are responsible for unprecedented destruction, including war, ecological depletion, technological overshoot, and systemic polarization. On the other hand, we have an exceptional ability to empathize, cooperate, transmit culture, and imagine morality.</p>

<p>This tension lies at the core of our inner struggle. It is not a random anomaly but rather a fundamental aspect of our human condition. The question is not why we are paradoxical, but rather, how this paradoxical tendency functions psychologically and what developmental opportunities it creates.</p>
<p>The paradoxical nature of our inner struggle is evident in the world news. We can no longer look away. While arms factories operate at full capacity, teams of highly trained healthcare professionals work tirelessly to repair the unprecedented physical and emotional damage caused by these factories.</p>

<p>Is the prospect of achieving inner peace and tranquility while growing up safely—the foundation of becoming a healthy human with a healthy mind—under pressure? Despite having the best and fastest technology ever, are we more vulnerable as a species than ever before?</p>
<h2>The Evolutionary and Neuropsychological Basis of Our Inner Struggle</h2>

<p>From an evolutionary perspective, the human mind is the result of two unequal evolutionary processes. Our ancient neurobiological system, formed in contexts of scarcity and danger, optimizes rapid threat detection, territorial defense, and in-group/out-group differentiation. In contrast, our young cultural system is developing exponentially faster and enables symbolic thinking, moral reflection, empathic extension, and institutional cooperation.</p>

<p>These two systems operate simultaneously, often in conflict with each other. A paradox arises when an evolutionarily ancient mind confronts a world that it created but cannot oversee.</p>
<h2>The Paradox as Our Phenomenological Structure</h2>
<p>From a phenomenological perspective, humans experience themselves as both vulnerable and full of potential. This dual experience gives rise to two fundamental existential movements. The first is contraction, which is an inward movement focused on protection, control, and security. The second movement is expansion, which is an outward movement focused on connection, meaning, and resonance.</p>

<p>These movements are not opposites that mutually exclude each other. Rather, they form a dynamic field of tension that structures human experience. Rather than being opposites, fear and desire are complementary responses to the same existential openness.</p>
<h2>Our Paradoxical Psychology</h2>
<p>The human mind consists of three interactive processes.</p>

<p>Our emotional processes form the primal layer. This layer is mostly automatic, defensive, and focused on survival. It produces rapid evaluations, images of enemies, territorial reflexes, and accumulation behavior. In modern contexts, this can lead to militarization, ecological exploitation, and polarization.</p>

<p>The meaning process happening in our mind is the second layer, or the reflective layer. This layer enables empathy, moral reasoning, symbolic representation, and long-term planning. It is the foundation of culture, art, ethics, and our democratic institutions.</p>
<p>The third layer is the integrative process between, or our capacity for wisdom. This layer is not innate, but rather a developmental possibility. It encompasses the ability to tolerate paradoxes, regulate emotions, embrace complexity, and act with maturity rather than reflexively.</p>



  


<p>The constant interaction between these three layers is the source of the paradoxical undertone.</p>
<h2>The Wisdom of Paradoxical Maturity</h2>
<p>Unlike perspectives that strive for internal consistency or harmonization, the paradox model posits that psychological maturity involves learning to accept these internal contradictions. This involves acknowledging fear without succumbing to it, following desire without naivety, integrating vulnerability and strength, and developing responsiveness rather than reactivity.</p>

<p>Paradoxical maturity is a type of inner ecology, or a dynamic balance between contraction and expansion.</p>
<h2>Implications for the Evolution of Our Culture and Society</h2>
<p>The paradoxical undertones of human psychology have direct consequences for social dynamics. Societies that institutionalize contractive movements through politics of fear, militarization, or economic accumulation reinforce destructive tendencies.</p>

<p>Conversely, societies that cultivate expansive movements through education, art, care, and ecological responsibility promote integration.</p>
<p>The challenge of the 21st century is developing collective structures that support the integrative layer.</p>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>Human beings are not paradoxes that need to be resolved; rather, we are beings of tension who must learn to live with our dual heritage. The paradoxical nature of human psychology is the source of both our destructive tendencies and our capacity for meaning, empathy, and wisdom. Recognizing our inner tension is a necessary and transformative step toward individual and collective maturity—a crucial step in human evolution. This inner struggle is becoming a pivotal moment in our development as a species, and it will shape our future. Will the wound deepen, or will we learn from it?</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/fulfilling-our-highest-possibility/202602/the-way-to-a-healthy-mind" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/fulfilling-our-highest-possibility/202602/the-way-to-a-healthy-mind</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/fulfilling-our-highest-possibility/202602/the-way-to-a-healthy-mind</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Patrick De Vleeschauwer Drs.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/0000000000%20PT%2047%20fallon-michael.jpg?itok=IrmNpL_0" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How Stereotypes Inform the Way Gay Men See Themselves]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-02/Chris%20Tompkins%20%281%29.png.jpg?itok=yiWElR_3" alt="Chris Tompkins LMFT" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Bias</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">How Stereotypes Inform the Way Gay Men See Themselves</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">The media's single story about gay men is a harmful and limiting lens.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 21, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Stereotypes about gay men being hypersexual create confirmation bias that reinforces limiting beliefs.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Confirmation bias is noticing only what supports your beliefs, and dismissing what doesn’t.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The media's single story about gay men becomes the lens through which we view our worth.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/vale-AxEqDPYxbq0-unsplash.jpg?itok=oSeR8t48" width="320" height="483" data-insert-type="image" title="Vale / Unsplash" alt="Vale / Unsplash"></div>
<div class="caption"> </div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Vale / Unsplash</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>This week, <em>Wired </em>published an article titled "Inside the Gay Tech Mafia," profiling the network of gay men in the tech industry. </p>
<p>Beyond documenting professional influence, the piece emphasized stereotypes about gay men, including gossip, cattiness, and drama.</p>
<p>The illustrations accompanying the piece depicted gay men as exaggerated stereotypes, including two limp wrists reaching out to give a handshake coming out of the zipper of their pants. As if the only way gay men greet one another is through our penises.</p>

<p>The visual language reduced gay men to limiting stereotypes, which struck a nerve across social media. It demonstrated how even progressive publications default to a single narrative about who gay men are.</p>
<p>Nigerian novelist Chimamanda Adichie gave one of my favorite talks, "The Danger of a Single Story," where she explores stereotypes and the consequences of using one narrative to define a group or person. She draws on her own experience as a woman from Nigeria attending college in the United States.</p>

<p>She recalls visiting Guadalajara, Mexico, and suddenly noticing people all around her simply living—walking, shopping, and dining—and feeling a wave of shame. She realized she had bought into the single story about Mexico and the border without ever questioning it.</p>
<p>Adichie says, "The single story creates stereotypes and the problem with stereotypes is not that they are untrue, but they are incomplete. They make one story become the only story."</p>

<p>I draw the same parallels with the single story of gay men. For my entire life growing up, the messages I received—consciously, unconsciously, overtly, or covertly—told me gay men were hypersexual, promiscuous, incapable of monogamy, and obsessed with youth and physical perfection. If we look at the entire story of gay men, and not the single story, we'll see the diversity of our lives and relationships—some monogamous, some open, some focused on career, some on family, some on fitness, some on art, some on none of these things.</p>

<p>We'll also be more willing to see how the pressure to conform to these stereotypes isn't a result of being gay. It's a result of internalizing a single story about who we're supposed to be based on a constant bombardment of stereotypical imagery in articles like the recent one in <em>Wired</em>.</p>
<p>Adichie continues, "The consequence of the single story is that it robs people of dignity. It makes our recognition of our equal humanity difficult. It emphasizes how we are different rather than how we are similar."</p>

<p>This week, I met with a client who is struggling to express his needs in a new relationship. His boyfriend wants an open relationship, but he doesn't. What struck me was how he framed the problem. He told me he felt something was wrong with <em>him</em> for not wanting an open relationship because "gay men are supposed to want sex all the time." He worried he was too conservative and not “gay enough.” He had internalized the single story so deeply that he couldn't see his desire for monogamy, or his personal values, as legitimate. Instead, he saw himself as the problem.</p>

<p>When we believe something based on an experience or what we've learned, we tend to gather information to confirm the belief. Take, for example, my client who internalized the narrative that gay men only need open relationships. Through a process called <em>confirmation bias</em>—our tendency to seek out information that confirms what we already believe while ignoring evidence that challenges it—he will notice every couple on dating apps listing themselves as "open," every gay man at a party talking about hookups, or every article about polyamory in queer spaces. </p>

<p>He'll even unconsciously gravitate toward dating someone who wants an open relationship, reinforcing his belief that that's what all gay men want—while completely disregarding gay couples in long-term monogamous relationships all around him.</p>
<p>I see these stereotypes reinforced constantly. I've been writing for publications like <em>Elephant Journal, Psychology Today,</em> and <em>HuffPost,</em> and whenever I use a platform like Unsplash to source imagery for articles, the images and categories for "gay men" or "LGBTQ community" are limited or overtly stereotypical—either hypersexualized or drinking at a party, or images only at Pride festivals. Structural homophobia keeps outdated systems at play in the collective consciousness about entire groups of people, which contributes to how those people perceive and feel about themselves.</p>

<p>Even major platforms dedicated to mental health and psychology can inadvertently perpetuate the single story—through limited imagery, inadequate categorization of LGBTQ-related topics, or patterns in what content gets amplified publicly. All subtle, yet pervasive ways structural homophobia and heteronormativity operate, perpetuating the single story of gay men.</p>



  


<p>The good news is that once we're aware of our confirmation bias and the single stories we've internalized, we become better equipped to challenge stereotypes. When my client started to recognize he wasn't the problem—that his values were just different from his boyfriend's—he could begin to advocate for what he actually wanted rather than conforming to what he thought gay men were supposed to want.</p>

<p>Challenging the single story means recognizing when we're seeing ourselves through a distorted lens and asking whether the narrative we've accepted is actually true. Gay men are not a monolith, and our relationships, desires, and values are as diverse as we are. The single story robs us of nuance and reduces what it means to be human to tired stereotypes.</p>

<p>We honor our full humanity by living according to our own values rather than conforming to narratives that were never ours to begin with.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/lgbtq-affirmative-psychology/202602/how-stereotypes-inform-the-way-gay-men-see-themselves" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/lgbtq-affirmative-psychology/202602/how-stereotypes-inform-the-way-gay-men-see-themselves</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/lgbtq-affirmative-psychology/202602/how-stereotypes-inform-the-way-gay-men-see-themselves</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Chris Tompkins LMFT]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/gregory-hayes-SCbycmUSAaE-unsplash.jpg?itok=SCZRo9YW" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why Kids Lie, and How to Respond]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-12/Cook.png.jpg?itok=6zFBKbhL" alt="Cook" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Parenting</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Why Kids Lie, and How to Respond</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">How to respond to a child's lies without losing their trust.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 21, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Children don't lie to their parents to be defiant.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Lying behaviors, while normal, are frustrating.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Kids lie in attempts to getting out of trouble.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Few parenting moments frustrate us faster than catching our child in a lie. The chocolate-smeared face insisting, “I didn’t eat that brownie!” The fourth grader who promises homework is finished when that homework has not even started. The teenager who gives you a partial version of their weekend plans.</p>

<p>It’s uncomfortable. It’s personal. And it can feel like a direct reflection of our parenting.</p>
<p>Before we spiral, let’s level the playing field.</p>
<p>Research suggests the average adult tells one to two lies per day. Most aren’t dramatic betrayals. They’re social smoothing: “I’m fine.” “Traffic was terrible.” “We’re busy that night.” We avoid conflict. We protect feelings. We save face. Much of it is automatic.</p>

<p>That doesn’t make us immoral. It makes us human.</p>
<p>And that is the lens we need when we examine our children’s dishonesty.</p>
<h2>Kids Learn What They See</h2>
<p>Children are wired for observational learning. If they repeatedly hear us tell small lies to get out of plans or avoid discomfort, they internalize a powerful lesson: Truth is flexible.</p>

<p>Young children, especially, cannot operate from a “do as I say, not as I do” framework. They imitate what they observe. If we want honesty, we must model it—even when it’s inconvenient.</p>
<p>The good news? Just as we teach hygiene, gratitude, and responsibility, we can intentionally teach integrity.</p>
<p>But honesty looks different at every developmental stage.</p>

<h2>Toddlers: It's Not Moral Deception</h2>
<p>Toddlers cannot lie in the moral sense of the word. What adults perceive as dishonesty is usually wishful thinking, fantasy, or an immature understanding of cause and effect.</p>
<p>A 2-year-old with frosting on their cheeks who says, “I didn’t eat it,” isn’t masterminding deception. They may wish they hadn’t eaten that cupcake, because they knew it would get them into trouble. At this age, kids may not connect their actions to the evidence.</p>

<p>Toddlers are blunt truth-tellers. Try playing hide-and-seek with one—they will proudly reveal their location.</p>
<p>What matters most at this stage is consistency. It’s important to focus on your behaviors as a parent. If you promise to play after dinner and repeatedly don’t follow through, your toddler won’t label it “lying,” but they will feel the mismatch. Trust is built when words and actions align.</p>

<h2>Preschoolers: Lying as a Developmental Milestone</h2>
<p>Between ages 3 and 5, lying can seem to appear out of nowhere. This behavior is actually a sign of cognitive growth. Preschoolers are beginning to understand that other people have different thoughts and beliefs. This “theory of mind” development allows them to experiment with shaping someone else’s perception.</p>


<p>Many preschool lies are imaginative:</p>
<ul>
<li>“My stuffed animal told me to do it.”</li>
<li>“There was a dinosaur in the backyard.”</li>
</ul>
<p>Others are self-protective:</p>
<ul>
<li>“I didn’t spill the milk. My little brother did it.”</li>
</ul>
<p>Finally, some lies are the result of a developing brain.</p>
<ul>
<li>If a child pushed their friend at 10:00 a.m. on the playground and their mom asked them to explain their behavior at 5:30 p.m., your child may not remember the behavior in question.</li>
</ul>

<p>They are also remarkably bad at lying. Which is a parenting power move.</p>
<p>A playful response can diffuse tension. If your child claims their teacher brought a penguin to school, try leaning in with curiosity: “Really? What’s the penguin’s name?” Often, they’ll shift the story themselves.</p>
<p>This stage is ideal for brief, real-world conversations about honesty. When something breaks, you might say: “Mistakes happen. What matters is telling the truth so we can fix it.”</p>



  


<p>Keep it simple. Keep it calm. Avoid fear-based tactics like, “If you don’t behave, the police will come.” Even if intended to control behavior, those messages can create anxiety and undermine trust.</p>
<h2>School-Age Kids: Morality and Reputation</h2>
<p>From roughly 6 to 12 years old, children understand that lying is wrong—not just because they’ll get caught, but because it damages trust.</p>

<p>At this stage, common motivations for lying include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Avoiding punishment</li>
<li>Gaining peer approval</li>
<li>Protecting self-image</li>
<li>Fitting in</li>
</ul>
<p>Children at this age are also deeply invested in fairness. They notice inconsistencies quickly. If you promise to return in five minutes and come back much later, credibility takes a hit.</p>

<p>This is also when reputation starts to matter. A child may exaggerate accomplishments to impress friends or hide mistakes to preserve their image. Rather than shaming the lie, explore the need underneath it. “What made it hard to tell me the truth?” “Were you worried about how I’d respond?” Curiosity preserves connection.</p>

<h2>Teenagers: Autonomy and Hypocrisy Detection</h2>
<p>Adolescents can think abstractly and understand nuanced ethics. They recognize gray areas, including white lies. Lying during the teen years often centers on privacy, independence, or rebellion. Teens are acutely sensitive to hypocrisy. If you preach honesty but bend the truth in your own life, they will notice.</p>

<p>At the same time, teenagers are forming their moral identity. They are deciding what kind of person they want to be. When parents model integrity—even in uncomfortable situations—teens absorb that. When dishonesty happens, approach it with steadiness rather than accusation. A confrontational tone invites defensiveness. A calm, direct approach invites dialogue. “I care more about honesty than perfection.” “Let’s talk about what happened.” Respect fuels responsibility.</p>

<h2>Why Teenagers Lie</h2>
<p>Teens lie for many of the same reasons adults do:</p>
<ul>
<li>To avoid consequences</li>
<li>To gain approval</li>
<li>To protect someone</li>
<li>To test boundaries</li>
<li>To reduce fear</li>
</ul>
<p>Sometimes, frequent lying signals something deeper: anxiety, perfectionism, or fear of harsh reactions. It is important to ask yourself:</p>
<ul>
<li>Does my child feel safe admitting mistakes?</li>
<li>Do I respond with shame or with guidance?</li>
<li>Am I expecting emotional regulation beyond their developmental capacity?</li>
</ul>

<p>Honesty flourishes in safe environments.</p>
<h2>How to Raise Honest Kids</h2>
<p><strong>1. Model honesty consistently.</strong><br>You need to be honest! Let your children see you decline invitations kindly without fabrication. Admit when you’ve made a mistake. Align your actions with your values.</p>
<p><strong>2. Separate the behavior from the character.</strong><br>Saying “That was dishonest” is different from “You’re a liar.” Protect their identity while correcting their behavior.</p>

<p><strong>3. Stay calm when truth emerges.</strong><br>If a child confesses and you explode, you unintentionally teach them to hide it next time. It’s OK to pause. Tell them, “I need a minute. We’ll talk about this soon." Then follow with: “Thank you for telling me. Let’s solve this.”</p>
<p><strong>4. Use natural consequences when possible.</strong><br>If they didn’t study and the grade reflects that, allow the outcome to teach. Guide them toward problem-solving rather than piling on punishment.</p>

<p><strong>5. Praise courage.</strong><br>When your child tells the truth—especially when it’s hard—name it. “That took bravery.” Reinforcement builds identity.</p>
<p>Here’s the bottom line: Lying is part of being human. It is not a predictor of a doomed future. It is often a signal—of development, of fear, of social learning, of unmet needs.</p>

<p>Your role isn’t to eliminate every fib. It’s to create a home where truth feels safer than deception. Where mistakes are survivable. Where integrity is modeled, not demanded.</p>
<p>When your child believes, “I can tell my parent hard things,” you’ve built something far more powerful than compliance.</p>
<p>You’re building character—one honest conversation at a time.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/parenting-redefined/202602/why-kids-lie-and-how-to-respond" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/parenting-redefined/202602/why-kids-lie-and-how-to-respond</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/parenting-redefined/202602/why-kids-lie-and-how-to-respond</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Kristen Cook, MD]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-timur-weber-9127715.jpg?itok=WTOM6dQn" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Quintessential Secrets of Psychotherapy: The Role of Acceptance]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/new-photo-.jpg?itok=-Vc-lmod" alt="Stephen A. Diamond Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Therapy</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Quintessential Secrets of Psychotherapy: The Role of Acceptance</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Acceptance lies at the core of successful psychotherapy.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 21, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Psychotherapy has been practiced now for a little more than a century.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Psychotherapy is helpful for most people.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Psychotherapy is as much about acceptance as change.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Philosopher Friedrich Nietzsche proposed in his famous Stoic aphorism of <em>amor fati </em>(“love of one’s fate") that we should not only seek to accept but willingly embrace all that happens to us in life as necessary—the good, the bad, and the ugly. The concept of acceptance is particularly prominent in Eastern philosophy and religion, as well as in Christianity and other great religious systems. For instance, acceptance is central to so-called spiritual enlightenment, as illustrated repeatedly in timeless texts like the Old Testament's Book of Job,<em> </em>the<em> </em>Hindu Bhagavad Gita<em>, </em>the noble teachings of Siddhartha Gautama (Buddha), and the Tao Te Ching<em>.</em> But even practicing Buddhists, Hindus, Taoists, and other spiritual seekers can sometimes lose sight of the primacy of acceptance.<em> </em>Consider, for instance, this frustrated cry of one Buddhist devotee of meditation: "I've been meditating for thirty years—and I'm still angry!" In this case, the meditator evidently erroneously sought to <em>change, </em>eradicate, or transcend rather than <em>accept, experience, and constructively express, redirect, or channel </em>his angry feelings. (For more on dealing constructively or creatively with anger in psychotherapy, see my book <em>Anger, Madness, and the Daimonic</em> [SUNY Press, 1996].) </p>

<p>Drawing directly from these ancient wisdom teachings of the East, clinical psychologist Marsha Linehan incorporates what she calls "radical acceptance" in her dialectical behavior therapy (DBT). The secret to such radical acceptance is the nonjudgmental, tolerant, courageous, compassionate embrace of, rather than resistance to, whatever we are experiencing right here and now, in the present moment, juxtaposed paradoxically with the acknowledgment and unequivocal acceptance of the essential necessity for changing one's self-defeating behavior and negative self-talk. Another popular form of cognitive-behavioral therapy, acceptance and commitment therapy, or ACT, places similar emphasis on accepting our negative cognitions and painful emotions rather than striving to change them, while simultaneously committing ourselves to acting in ways that will change our lives for the better.</p>

<p>This clinical emphasis on the dialectical relationship between change and acceptance is, at least in part, what needs to happen in any truly effective psychotherapy. To begin with, certain things in life cannot ever be changed, and some others can be, albeit often only through sustained and heroic effort. This same recognition of reality is reflected in the famous serenity prayer from Alcoholics Anonymous: <em>"God grant me the serenity to accept the things I cannot change; the courage to change the things I can; and the wisdom to know the difference." </em>Also inherent in the, for many, helpful AA philosophy is the requirement to totally <em>accept </em>one's complete powerlessness over alcohol (or other addictive substances) as an absolutely indispensable prerequisite for change. As the Swiss psychiatrist C.G. Jung, one of the early supporters of the AA approach, stated: "We cannot change anything unless we accept it." </p>

<p>There are profound implications for successful psychotherapy in these powerful words. The problem, <em>whatever it may be</em>, must first be fully and consciously acknowledged and accepted by the person <em>before </em>it can be changed. Without such acceptance, there can be no true change. This may sound easy, but it is not, for it necessitates acceptance of feelings, impulses, fantasies, tendencies, desires, and behaviors in ourselves that we find deeply unacceptable and may remain unconscious or unknown to us <em>because we do not want to admit them to ourselves.</em> These unacceptable and rejected aspects of ourselves must therefore first be confronted and made fully conscious <em>before</em> we can exercise our existential freedom to choose to accept them or not. This sometimes painful and arduous process of acceptance starts with acknowledging not only the subjective and objective existence of the problem itself, but <em>the necessity to consciously confront the problem head-on and make the total commitment to oneself to do this</em>. The big secret here is that sometimes it is only through acceptance that such transformative changes can eventually take place. <em>Change—</em>whether of one's behavior, beliefs, cognitions, presuppositions, self-perception, worldview, or ways of being in the world—<em>always starts with the willing acceptance of the unacceptable. </em></p>

<p>At the same time, for the psychotherapy patient, as for all of us to some extent, certain behavioral or attitudinal changes must be made, as in the case of correcting or modifying one’s central myth or core schema of oneself and the world. This is the reason most people enter psychotherapy. They sense or recognize the necessity for change but have been unwilling or unable to implement that change in themselves, their situation, attitude, relationship, or behavior on their own. Sometimes, they have sincerely tried to change, often for years or decades, but to no avail. Seeking psychotherapy is a courageous and momentous decision. And it can be a deeply humbling one. This is just human nature. None of us likes admitting having a problem, let alone not being able to satisfactorily solve or resolve it ourselves. The ego strongly resists such an admission of perceived weakness. It is tantamount to a profound feeling of personal failure, powerlessness, vulnerability, weakness, ineptitude, impotence, and helplessness. Men, in particular, often have serious trouble asking for psychological (or other kinds of) assistance and are statistically less likely to seek psychotherapy than women, who are generally more receptive to psychotherapy, though this trend has been slowly shifting in recent decades. But those brave women and men who do take the intimidating and sometimes ego-deflating step to seek psychotherapy, voluntarily submitting or surrendering to it (tantamount to admitting to being powerless over the problem), take a decisive and heroic first step toward self-acceptance—and lasting therapeutic change. </p>

<p>Fundamentally, what must change for most of us is our rigid <em>refusal to accept ourselves, others, and reality as we and they are right now.</em> This is a true paradox. And much easier said than done. When people initially seek psychotherapy, they sometimes do so hoping or expecting, consciously or unconsciously, to change themselves, others, or the world in ways that are simply not possible. For instance, some people harbor and suffer from distorted core beliefs, <em>self-schemata </em>as they are called in cognitive therapy, a long-held (commonly since early childhood) unconscious “guiding fiction” (Alfred Adler) or personal "myth" (Rollo May)<em> </em>of being basically broken, unlikable, unlovable, and unworthy of love or recognition as they are. What is sorely lacking in such deeply wounded individuals is the ability to unconditionally accept themselves, others, and the world <em>exactly as they are right now</em>, despite their obvious imperfection. This sort of acceptance should not be equated with denying the problematic nature of human existence, nor the neuroses or bad behavior of ourselves or others. Denial is a maladaptive and dangerous defense mechanism. Accepting actually means acknowledging, confronting, and addressing problems as directly and constructively as possible. Clearly, simply by choosing acceptance, such individuals have not suddenly and miraculously rid themselves or the world of their difficulties or problems. But they are no longer in denial of these difficulties, having taken the first crucial step toward constructively addressing them. As stated in the ancient Chinese text the Tao Te Ching, “A journey of a thousand miles begins with a single step.” Indeed, for the psychotherapy patient, <em>acceptance</em> of one's problems and taking <em>responsibility for constructively confronting and addressing them as best we can</em> is precisely the sort of psychological, philosophical, or spiritual reorientation required to achieve real and lasting change and to restore and sustain one’s soul, self, and sanity.</p>

<p><em>This post is adapted from a chapter in my forthcoming book, </em>Secrets of Psychotherapy: Clinical Wisdom for a Crazy World.</p>


            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/evil-deeds/202602/quintessential-secrets-of-psychotherapy-the-role-of-acceptance" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/evil-deeds/202602/quintessential-secrets-of-psychotherapy-the-role-of-acceptance</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/evil-deeds/202602/quintessential-secrets-of-psychotherapy-the-role-of-acceptance</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Stephen A. Diamond Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-shvets-production-7176033.jpg?itok=5gvbvNyi" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Could Glial Cells Be the Key to New Schizophrenia Treatments?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2024-08/Sarah%20An%20Myers.png.jpg?itok=7WIVFqFt" alt="Sarah An Myers" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Neuroscience</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Could Glial Cells Be the Key to New Schizophrenia Treatments?</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Long-term research into cellular function in schizophrenia could offer new hope.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 21, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Glial cells enhance the function of neurons in the brain.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Glial cells are reduced in people with schizophrenia, affecting overall brain function.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Therapies targeting glial cells in schizophrenia are promising but require more research.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <div class="insertArea ck-widget">
<div class="image-article-inline-half">
<div class="insert-inner">
<div class="insert-image"><img class="image-article_inline_half_caption" src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/article_inline_half_caption/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/bioscience-image-library-by-fayette-reynolds-S07-mK6zNeY-unsplash.jpg?itok=JQ7_gy8g" width="320" height="180" data-insert-type="image" alt="Proliferation of adipocytes in adult parathyroid gland by phase contrast." title="Bioscience Image Library by Fayette Reynolds/Unsplash"></div>
<div class="caption">Proliferation of adipocytes in adult parathyroid gland by phase contrast.</div>
<div class="insertArea--origin subtext">Source: Bioscience Image Library by Fayette Reynolds/Unsplash</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p dir="ltr">Anyone living with schizophrenia understands the true limitations of current treatment options. Antipsychotics remain the single leading treatment for the disorder, and they are riddled with undesirable side effects. Weight gain, tardive dyskinesia, and excessive drowsiness are a few. </p>
<p dir="ltr">Much research is devoted to expanding the range of medication options, and few academics have pursued other avenues. However, there is a possibility that treatment for schizophrenia can be approached through cellular methods if long-term research validates early signs of hope. </p>

<p dir="ltr">In the brain, many different cells and systems work together to promote function. For example, neurons, specialized cells that are central to brain structure, are important for transferring information to other cells.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Other cells, such as glial cells, support the function of neurons. Neuroscience has often painted glial cells as the glue that holds neurons together, but glial cells can also be helpful in promoting neuronal health, enhancing neuronal immune response, among other neuronal-enhancing functions.</p>

<h2>Glial Cells Are Different in People With Schizophrenia</h2>
<p dir="ltr">The brains of people with schizophrenia are biologically different. Not only do they have alterations in their dopaminergic functions (a neurotransmitter related to reward, sleep regulation, and more), but evidence has shown that there are fewer glial cells in the brains of people with schizophrenia. </p>

<p dir="ltr">Examinations of postmortem subjects have observed that glial cells are seen to have a significant reduction in presence in the prefrontal cortex (PFC), responsible for healthy cognitive skills. Without the different types of glial cells, neuronal health can decline, and we know this from the apparent cognitive impairments in those with schizophrenia. Thus, overall brain function can decline.</p>

<p dir="ltr">Some subcategories of glial cells are responsible for different things. One subset, called <em>oligodendrocytes</em>, is responsible for ensuring that information is transmitted properly by providing a protective shield between parts of neurons. In patients with schizophrenia, this protective shield is significantly reduced, which indicates reduced network connectivity. Schizophrenia, as a disorder, is defined by this very trait—poor integration between cells and brain regions that are often found in these patients. </p>

<p dir="ltr">Brain changes in patients with schizophrenia are thought to come from the disorder itself or medications. However, from animal studies, researchers have concluded that antipsychotics are not a likely factor in decreasing glial cells. Sometimes they can actually enhance their functioning. </p>
<p dir="ltr">With this information, you may be wondering, what could help glial cells? Suggestions the researchers have are: increase exercise, antidepressants, natural products used on the body, and related tasks to enhance glial cell functioning and sustainability. </p>

<p dir="ltr">There might be a long time before we see therapeutic chemical treatments that specifically target glial cells, but thankfully, there are other things we can do in the meantime. </p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/living-as-an-outlier/202602/could-glial-cells-be-the-key-to-new-schizophrenia-treatments" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/living-as-an-outlier/202602/could-glial-cells-be-the-key-to-new-schizophrenia-treatments</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/living-as-an-outlier/202602/could-glial-cells-be-the-key-to-new-schizophrenia-treatments</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Sarah An Myers]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/field_blog_entry_images/2026-02/bioscience-image-library-by-fayette-reynolds-S07-mK6zNeY-unsplash.jpg?itok=p9bRswCj" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Do Pets Make Their Owners Happy? New Study Says They Do Not]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/field_user_blogger_photo/e1_edited.jpg?itok=z6uf8KQT" alt="Sebastian Ocklenburg, Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Animal Behavior</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">Do Pets Make Their Owners Happy? New Study Says They Do Not</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">A new study offers surprising insights on how pets affect well-being.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 21, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Several studies suggest that owning a pet increases well-being</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">A study with Australian data analyzed the association of pet ownership and well-being in a sophisticated way</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Owning a pet did not show any effects on life satisfaction, loneliness, mental health, or general health</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Owning a pet can affect mental health both positively and negatively</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Many pet owners would say that their pets are a great source of happiness for them and that they make them feel less lonely and generally better. Indeed, several psychological studies have shown the benefits of having a pet for both physical and mental health. However, pet owners can also face incredibly difficult situations that can have negative effects on their mental health. For example, it can be very frustrating if a dog is badly trained and aggressive and bites their owner or other people. Also, if a pet gets sick, the owner’s mental health may worsen since they worry so much. Last, but not least, sky-high vet bills can result in mental health challenges for some pet owners. So taken together, the relationship of owning a pet and psychological well-being may not be as easy as it seems at first glance. Thus, high-quality psychological studies are needed to explore this relationship further.</p>

<h2>A new study on pet ownership, health, and well-being</h2>
<p>A new study, published in the scientific journal <em>Applied Research Quality Life,</em> now investigated the effect of owning a pet on health and well-being from a new angle (<a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11482-026-10550-5">Ananyev, and co-workers, 2026</a>). In the study entitled “The Causal Effect of Pet Ownership on Health and Well-being”, the research team led by scientist Maxim Ananyev from the University of Melbourne, in Australia, analyzed data from the so-called HILDA survey (Household, Income and Labour Dynamics in Australia). This survey has three major advantages over many other studies which investigated the psychological effects of pet ownership.</p>

<p>First, the study was longitudinal, and data were collected over many years. It started in 2001, and the data analyzed in the study were collected in 2018 and 2022. Thus, unlike in previous studies that only collected data at one time point, this study had two data points, making different statistical analyses possible than in other studies.</p>

<p>Second, the scientists conducted statistical analyses that compared data from Victoria, an Australian state in which a policy change allowed renters to have pets (which resulted in more people getting pets compared to other states of Australia in which such a policy change did not happen). This allowed for a more causal research design than in previous studies.</p>

<p>Third, in the study, a lot of different data points were collected, and the volunteers were specifically recruited to be tested about the effects of pet ownership. This study design may reduce biases. For example, if volunteers are recruited for a study with an announcement stating that scientists look for pet owners, mostly people who are happy with their pets, may apply, resulting in overly positive results.</p>

<p>The scientists analyzed data from 495 pet owners who could have any sort of pet, such as a cat, dog, horse, bird, or fish. All pet owners had filled out questionnaires on life satisfaction, loneliness, mental health, and general health.</p>
<h2>Results of the study: Owning a pet, on average, does not affect life satisfaction, loneliness, mental health, or general health.</h2>

<p>The data from the pet owners from Victoria were compared to data from renters in other states who were not allowed to keep pets and non-renters in Victoria. Surprisingly, owning a pet did not show any positive or negative effects on life satisfaction, loneliness, mental health, or general health. This does, of course, not mean that some people can have great increases in well-being due to having a pet. It just shows that across many hundreds of people, the positive and the negative effects of owning a pet across people average each other out. While some people benefit greatly from their pets, others also suffer worse mental health due to problems with their pets. While the results of this study are at odds with previous works, the large sample size and high-quality design ensure that the results are robust. It is, thus, likely that some previous studies on pet ownership and wellbeing have been confounded by biased data.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-asymmetric-brain/202602/do-pets-make-their-owners-happy-new-study-says-they-do-not" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-asymmetric-brain/202602/do-pets-make-their-owners-happy-new-study-says-they-do-not</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-asymmetric-brain/202602/do-pets-make-their-owners-happy-new-study-says-they-do-not</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Sebastian Ocklenburg, Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-cottonbro-6869559.jpg?itok=nS6n_Sp6" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Best Way to Stop Liars in Their Tracks]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2025-01/Susan%20Krauss%20Whitbourne.png.jpg?itok=OoS9Jwh0" alt="Susan Krauss Whitbourne PhD, ABPP" style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Deception</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Best Way to Stop Liars in Their Tracks</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Getting liars to be a little more honest may be easier than you realize.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 21, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">People who tell the truth do so in the context of social relationships based on reciprocity and trust.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Perceiving that they’re not trusted could make deceivers more rather than less likely to deceive.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">By giving people the space to admit to their failings you can encourage healthier communication.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>People who lie can cause you all kinds of heartache. They trick, cheat, and manipulate you, possibly costing you money if not emotional pain. Why people engage in deception is one thing, but figuring out how to avoid their trap is quite another. To protect yourself, the avoiding part is probably more important than the understanding part.</p>

<p>Erin started to get into a new relationship with Pat, someone she met in her work at a bank. She didn’t ever share official duties with Pat in the workplace, so there were no issues there. A few weeks after they started dating, though, Erin knew that Pat didn’t drive, but she was shocked and hurt to learn that Pat had an arrest record for driving under the influence. It may have been an error of “omission,” but to Erin, it definitely felt like an error of commission; i.e., a lie.</p>

<h2>A Social Informational Processing Theory of Trust</h2>
<p>According to Zhejiang Normal University’s Mengqi Xu and colleagues (2025), the social context is everything when it comes to processing the information we receive from others. Attitudes in particular stand out as influences on the way that people interpret what other people say. When it comes to deception, the main form of social information people use involves trust. You have to decide whether to trust what someone else tells you based on all the available cues at your disposal.</p>

<p>Turning to the person who’s doing the communicating, and potentially engaging in deception, trust also comes into play. Pat had to decide whether to trust Erin before revealing the real reason for not owning or driving a car.</p>
<p>A couple of other layers of processing also come into play. The first is based in social exchange theory. If you think the other person is telling the truth, you will be more likely to do so yourself. In the words of the authors, “trust reciprocation functions both as a form of compliance with social norms and as a strategy to protect and reinforce their moral self-concept.” Breaking this down, it means that people are more likely to be honest with people they perceive as honest with them. People also want to be honest so they can live with their conscience as ethical individuals.</p>

<p>The second layer of processing is the quality of “need for cognitive closure (NFCC).” Some people really hate living with ambiguity, and they’ll rush to the first interpretation that pops into their head. This leads them to make snap decisions about whether to trust that another person is telling the truth. People low in NFCC don’t mind keeping an open mind to allow enough information to filter in so that they can make a proper judgment.</p>

<h2>Trust and the Deceiver</h2>
<p>The actual focus of the Xu et al. study was not on the recipient of deception, but on the perpetrator. In the first of two studies, participants (average age 21 years old) were given a chance to lie on a standard lab task in which they reported on the outcome of a virtual dice roll. In the high-trust condition, participants “overheard” (intentionally) two experimenters expressing the belief that their participants would be honest, and in the low-trust, the experimenters expressed uncertainty about whether the participants would honestly report their dice rolls. The findings supported the prediction that participants in the high-trust condition would, in fact, be more honest. Overall, high trust lowered the deception rate by 50%.</p>

<p>The second study added NFCC into the mix. People low in this quality were more likely to be affected by the trust manipulation in reporting the dice roll results. As the authors concluded, “Trustees with low NFCC engage in more thorough processing of trust-related information through various channels including language, behavior, and facial expressions.” In other words, if they stop to process the social input they’re receiving, people will become even more honest when they think they are being trusted.</p>

<h2>From Giver to Receiver</h2>
<p>Now we know that people will be more honest when they think they’re being trusted, especially if they tend to pause and evaluate all the information at their disposal. How does this translate to Erin’s relationship with Pat?</p>
<p>Let’s assume for the moment that Pat is not a bad person, and that Erin was right to think that they could have a good relationship. It’s also possible that Pat is indeed an inveterate liar, but the odds are that Erin would have sniffed something out sooner. After all, they’d worked together already, but beyond this, their place of employment pretty much demands total honesty.</p>

<p>If Erin were to use the Zhejiang Normal U’s study to interpret the fix she’s in, she might come to realize that she’s been sending out low-trust cues to poor Pat all along. How many times did Erin complain about people faking their income on account applications or leaving out a less-than-stellar work history? This could make Pat more and more uncomfortable as the weeks went on. It became harder and harder to trust that Erin wouldn’t end things instantly should Pat’s background somehow come out.</p>



  


<p>Indeed, with a lower NFCC, Erin might have suspended judgment until learning more of the facts behind Pat’s unfortunate past. Maybe the charges go back 10 years, and Pat has been sober ever since. Maybe Pat’s decision not to get back behind the wheel of a car was based on deep-seated feelings of guilt and anxiety, feelings that Pat struggles with every day.</p>

<p>Moving forward, were Erin to give Pat another chance, this blip in their ability to communicate openly could eventually result in stronger bonds being built between them. At the very least, Erin might learn from the experience to give people enough emotional space to be able to admit hard truths about themselves in an atmosphere of trust.</p>

<p><strong>To sum up,</strong> the truth may not always come in a perfectly wrapped package. Being willing to keep an open mind while also showing you trust the other person may help make that package if not perfect, then more transparent.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/fulfillment-at-any-age/202602/the-best-way-to-stop-liars-in-their-track" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/fulfillment-at-any-age/202602/the-best-way-to-stop-liars-in-their-track</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/fulfillment-at-any-age/202602/the-best-way-to-stop-liars-in-their-track</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Susan Krauss Whitbourne PhD, ABPP]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/Deception%20tswedensky-lying-1562272_1280.jpg?itok=uSUMTF2Q" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Politics of Looking Away]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/profile_teaser_small/public/2026-01/Sahar-Torres.jpg?itok=NUbqfdXk" alt="Gail Sahar, Ph.D., and M. Gabriela Torres, Ph.D." style="max-width:100%;border-radius:6px;"/></p><p><strong style="text-transform:uppercase;font-size:0.85em;color:#666;">Politics</strong></p><h1 style="font-size:1.6em;margin-bottom:4px;">The Politics of Looking Away</h1><h2 style="font-size:1.1em;color:#444;font-weight:normal;margin-top:0;">Why the suffering of others fails to move us.</h2><p style="font-size:0.9em;color:#666;">Posted February 20, 2026</p><hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:16px 0;"/>
          <div style="background:#f0f4ff;border-left:4px solid #3a5bd9;padding:12px 16px;margin-bottom:20px;border-radius:0 6px 6px 0;">
            <strong style="display:block;margin-bottom:8px;font-size:1em;">Key points</strong>
            <ul style="margin:0;padding-left:20px;">
              <li style="margin-bottom:6px;">Research indicates that violence can become normalized through constant exposure.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">People who have been dehumanized are more likely to become acceptable targets of violence.</li><li style="margin-bottom:6px;">The more victims of violence are blamed for their own suffering, the less others are motivated to intervene.</li>
            </ul>
          </div>
                    <p>Like us, you may feel paralyzed in the face of the relentless images of violence we see every day. Suffering children, military occupations, the devastated neighborhoods, the cries of parents mourning their dead—these scenes haunt us. Whether it is happening in Palestine or Minneapolis, we are witnesses to suffering, and that witnessing takes a heavy toll.</p>

<p>Clearly, the devastating situations in the West Bank and Gaza and in Minneapolis differ on many grounds, not least of which is the absolute number of people killed and injured, and yet one can see psychological and systemic similarities between them. Though many Americans have participated in protests against both the genocide in Gaza and aggression by U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement (ICE) in Minneapolis and other cities, perhaps a more common response is to helplessly look on in horror.</p>

<p>As scholars—one an anthropologist studying<a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/abs/cambridge-handbook-of-social-problems/state-violence/CB1CD884DD53026BC4DD7C1F1FD70DD3"> state-sanctioned violence</a>, the other a political psychologist examining how<a href="https://link.springer.com/book/10.1007/978-3-031-20236-0"> blame shapes emotion</a>—we understand why we collectively fail to respond to such extreme suffering. Those who commit atrocities need one thing above all: others' paralysis. Research in our fields shows they don't just hope for it—they manufacture it.</p>

<h2>Normalization of Violence Toward Expendable Populations</h2>
<p>Anthropological research has shown how our instinct to look away but also gawk at violent acts is often manipulated by political actors to render us both complicit and helpless. Whether it is looking at<a href="https://www.degruyterbrill.com/document/doi/10.7560/706477-008/html?srsltid=AfmBOorbPx5OoJhPe4Dsah2XkrZvqXOS6aUc4NlmAAC_U3QCObs-LOr8"> "bloody deeds" in the Guatemalan genocide</a>, the ruins of Palestine, or Operation Metro Surge by ICE in Minnesota, anthropologists have traced the ways in which we come to accept violence as<a href="https://www.pennpress.org/9780812216219/a-different-kind-of-war-story/"> a "natural" fact</a>. In his study of Northern Ireland,<a href="https://press.uchicago.edu/ucp/books/book/chicago/F/bo3644948.html"> Allen Feldman showed</a> how politically produced death, particularly in the form of dead bodies, can strengthen the power of those who commit violence while shaping the behavior of onlookers. The more we see violence, the more it becomes normalized, and the more it engages us in<em> just </em>looking.</p>

<p>A critical question for us is what makes us accept that certain lives are less worthy (or wholly unworthy) of safeguarding or that their deaths require no public outcry. Philosopher Achille Mbembe uses the concept of<a href="https://www.dukeupress.edu/necropolitics"> <em>necropolitics</em></a> to point to political situations where some lives are rendered expendable long before they are taken. Their deaths provoke no moral shock because they were already, in a sense,<em> </em>"dead" to us. Dead bodies, particularly when they pile up in large numbers, are no longer just bodies; they are political performance.</p>

<p>More than two years into Israel's siege of Gaza, more than 70,000 Palestinians have been killed, including over 20,000 children. In spite of a ceasefire agreement, Palestinians are still being killed on a regular basis. We look away from civilians bombed or starved to death instead of being moved to oppose such acts. Worse, some find the deaths of Palestinian children a source of derision or even humor.</p>

<p>In contrast, the 32 individuals who died or were killed in ICE custody in 2025, along with at least 6 so far this year, represent violence on a smaller scale and with different victims and actors. While protests in cities where ICE is operating have been commonplace, public outrage <a href="https://today.yougov.com/politics/articles/53939-more-americans-support-than-oppose-abolishing-ice-immigration-minneapolis-shooting-poll">significantly increased</a> after a second white American citizen was killed. <a href="https://www.upress.virginia.edu/title/5047/">This aligns with work by scholar Benjamin Gonzalez O'Brien</a>, which has shown how the criminalization of undocumented immigrants created a category of expendable individuals for some Americans, one that does not generally include white citizens.</p>

<h2>The Social Psychology of Dehumanization</h2>
<p>Several decades ago, prominent social psychologist Herbert Kelman identified the conditions that enable what he termed<a href="https://spssi.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/j.1540-4560.1973.tb00102.x"> "sanctioned massacres."</a> He defined such actions as "indiscriminate, ruthless, and often systematic mass violence, carried out by military or paramilitary personnel while engaged in officially sanctioned campaigns, and directed at defenseless and unresisting civilians, including old men, women, and children (p. 283)." Israel's actions in Gaza arguably match this definition, unless one accepts the Israeli government's position that<a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/tech/social-media/israel-posts-video-saying-are-no-innocent-civilians-gaza-rcna157111"> "there are no innocent Palestinians</a>."</p>

<p>Importantly, Kelman maintained that dehumanization of the victims is a critical element of sanctioned massacres. When we cease to think of a particular category of people as human, we are free to attribute all blame to them. We can see a similar process of demonization play out in the U.S. today through the increased labeling of those who have been killed by ICE as “criminals,” “AWFUL,” “domestic terrorists,” or “assassins” without any accompanying evidence. The psychological impact of this framing is significant.</p>



  


<p>This process of dehumanization is not a theoretical construct but a lived reality. The more a group is targeted with violence and dispossession, the less human they appear to others. The worse they look from being brutalized, the less we feel compelled to stop the brutality. The combination of <a href="https://www.simonandschuster.com/books/American-Intolerance/Robert-E-Bartholomew/9781633884496">demonization</a> and brutalization is liable to provoke disgust rather than sympathy in observers. </p>

<h2>Blameworthy Victims</h2>
<p>In the necropolitical play of making dead bodies acceptable, redeploying blame is necessary.<a href="https://link.springer.com/book/10.1007/978-3-031-20236-0"> Social psychology tells us</a> that when people are blamed for their own suffering, we are less likely to sympathize with them and tend not to offer help. <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/1368430219841135">Studies show</a> that dehumanized individuals are often seen as more responsible for their own suffering. This cultural shift in perception makes it easier for political leaders and their supporters to justify the atrocities committed against them.</p>

<p>When an act of aggression is portrayed as self-defense—as the deaths of Renee Good and Alex Pretti in Minnesota were—the public has historically been more likely to blame the target of aggression rather than the aggressor. When victims are blamed, it is easier for perpetrators justify their actions and for bystanders to remain passive.</p>

<p>In the mechanics of colonial dehumanization, people are not killed for what they've done—they're killed for who they are. This is the heart of necropolitics: the use of state-sanctioned violence to erase a people not only physically, but also politically and morally</p>
<p>This paralysis many of us feel, then, and our seeming inability to act in the face of mass death, should not be viewed as an accident but rather something that has been engineered through dehumanization, blame redistribution, and the normalization of violence. The atrocity depends on our remaining frozen, unable to move from witness to actor. </p>

<p>To break this paralysis, we must look directly at the violence and name it for what it is. Only then can we refuse the passive role that perpetrators designed for us and reclaim the capacity to respond with our full humanity intact.</p>

            
      <hr style="border:none;border-top:1px solid #ddd;margin:24px 0 12px;"/>
      <p style="font-size:0.85em;color:#888;">
        <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/power-culture-and-the-self/202602/the-politics-of-looking-away" target="_blank">Read the original article on Psychology Today →</a>
      </p>]]></description>
            <link>https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/power-culture-and-the-self/202602/the-politics-of-looking-away</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/power-culture-and-the-self/202602/the-politics-of-looking-away</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Gail Sahar, Ph.D., and M. Gabriela Torres, Ph.D.]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/styles/manual_crop_1_1_288x288/public/teaser_image/blog_entry/2026-02/pexels-cltsan-5343097%20%281%29.jpg?itok=ioRoKKNM" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>